Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
In today's exercise, we're going to be
talking about something that is brand
spanking new to CSS and that is CSS
variables. And now, I know what you're
saying, "Wes, we've had variables in SAS
forever and this is not new." But it
is new, smart Alec, because CSS
variables can be updated with JavaScript,
meaning that when you update a variable
in CSS, everywhere on the page that that
variable is referenced will update itself.
With SAS, you define them at compile time
and then it gets compiled and you cannot
change it. So let's take a look here. I've
got three variables, spacing, blur,
and base color. And when I change one of
those, like spacing, it will just
immediately update wherever that
variable is changed on the page,
same with blur. I'm only using that on
this imagery here. But as I change it,
it's going to update.
And then finally base color, I'm using it
for the background of this image as well
as the color of this JS highlight here.
So when I change that color,
it updates everywhere it's referenced on
the actual page. So let's jump in.
Let's take a quick look at our HTML here.
I've got h2 which has a span with a class
of highlight or hl around JS. And
then I've got a label and input for the
spacing which has a min of 10, a max of
200. And we've got a range which does our
blur. And we've got an input type of color
which gives you that kind of cool color
picker. You're getting at bit of a
different color picker off your own
windows or something like that but it'll
always open up whatever that default color
picker is on your system. Then we've
got the image and we're styling.
Now, let's actually jump into...opening
this up in our browser.
Let's jump into some CSS variables first
because we need to understand how they
work before we can write any of our
JavaScript to update them.
So the way that CSS variables work is that
you declare them on some sort of element
in our case, we're going to declare it on
root which is sort of the highest level
that you can get, very similar to
declaring it on the HTML element.
And here's where we're going to set our
default values for those variables.
So we're going to have a base variable
that's going to be set to the Wes base
yellow color. We're going to have a
spacing variable which is going to be
defaulted to 10 pixels and we're going to
give ourselves a blur variable which is
also going to be defaulted to 10 pixels.
Now, we've defined these variables,
and we can go ahead
and start using them.
So let's grab our image that's on the page
here and give it a padding of...and now
when you want to use a variable in CSS,
you say "var" and you pass it the spacing.
Now this dash-dash, I know you're like,
"What the hell are you doing,
Wes?" That is the standard in CSS, that's
how you do it. It's normally like dollar
in SAS or something like that. But in
CSS, it's dash-dash. Don't yell at me,
that's how they decided to go about it so
that it would be backwards compatible with
all the CSS that were older browsers spec.
And look, the padding is based on the
spacing and it's giving us some...you can
see the green there. Okay, that works.
Then we want to work on the background is
going to be our variable base which is
going to be that yellow color. Okay,
looking good. The image is taking a second
to load. Then if I were to change this
spacing to 50 pixels, refresh,
you see it's much bigger. Put it back down
to 10 it's going to take that variable
from spacing and I don't
need to re-declare it.
And then finally, we are going to give it
a filter which is a blur and we want to
use the variable "blur." Good. Now we want
to work with this JS highlight here.
So we'll say anything with the class
of highlight is going to have the color of
variable base. Great. So anywhere now
we're referencing this color right here
and right here, it's going to be changed
if I were just to change this to maybe
like red, everywhere on the page
gets...you get the point, right?
It's a variable and you reference it
and it's going to be used.
Now, how do we write some JavaScript to
update those? Well, let's go ahead and do
that. First thing that we need to do is we
need to select all three of these inputs
right here so that when they change, we
can then update the CSS variables which
will in turn update the colors on the
screen so we'll scroll down to our script
tags here and we will select all of our
inputs on the page, so const inputs
equals, and I'm going to use
document.querySelectorAll. And our
selector here is going to be .controls
input, so that's going to select all the
inputs on the page.
Real quick aside, in the last video, I
said that the querySelector will give you
an array. And what I really meant is it
gives you something called a NodeList.
If I run this in my console here, it
returns to you what actually looks like
an array. It's got square brackets. It has
index items. It has a length.
But it's not an array. And the difference
between a NodeList and an array is that an
array has all kinds of methods for dealing
with an array like map and reduce and all
the good ones. And if you open up the
prototype for the NodeList,
you see we only have a couple methods
here, entries for each keys and values and
then a couple other little things here.
Whereas if I had an array,
like one, two, three, R X equals, and
I have X, and I open that up and look
at the prototype of that. Oh, look at all
these good stuff. There's everything that
you're used to.
So sometimes you'll see people converting
their NodeList to an array.
And in some future exercises, we're going
to have to do that. But in our case,
what we're going to use to loop over these
inputs is the forEach method which has
just recently been added to the NodeList,
so it's not necessary for us to convert it
to an array unless you're using an older
browser that does not support having
forEach on it. So what we want to do now
is create our function called
handleUpdate, function handleUpdate and
we'll just console.log this.value for each
of them. And then we'll listen for a
change event on each of the inputs.
So we'll say inputs.forEach and then we
want to loop over each one.
We have an input, I'm going to use an
arrow function just to be nice and clean
here, the input.addEventListener.
We want to listen for the change event.
And when that is called, we're
going to call handleUpdate.
Good. Now when we open up our console here
and I change one of these and I move and
let go 75, 102, 167, you see my blur will
change as well. So I'm seeing the values
change whenever I change the value of
one of these. But one little thing is you
notice that as I drag it around, it
doesn't actually trigger a change.
What we can do is we can also listen for
the mousemove update which when you move
over it looks like it's going to trigger
every single time. There's some flags that
you could set where when click,
set it to true, when you click off,
set it to false. We're going to keep it
really simple here where when I move the
value, it's also going to trigger a
change rather than just when I let go.
So we're listening for change and mouse
move and it's going to call handleUpdate
regardless of which one that happened.
Now let's go into this handleUpdate here
and let's work on getting the values out
of it. So the first thing we need to know
is what is the suffix of the value that
we're working on. Because if we go up to
our variables here, this base doesn't have
a suffix, it's just a hex code or RGB
value that's going to come out of the
input. But the spacing and the blur,
they're going to give us values like 10
but they need to be 10px. So what I've
done is I've attached some additional info
to each of this inputs right here
where I've created a data attribute.
Again, a data attribute is just an
attribute that you've made up.you just
have to prefix it with data-dash
something. And I've put on a sizing or a
suffix value here called px. And then this
one, I haven't. So what we can do in here
is we can say const suffix
equals this.dataset because...
What is this.dataset? Let's take a quick
look at that a second.
Console.log this.dataset and if I change
it...you see, dataset is an object that
will contain all the data attributes
from that specific element.
In this case, it's just sizing. But if I
were to go up to this first one here,
data-name equals wes and data-dash cool
equals, we'll put a poop in there.
Now, let's see what we got. We got
a poop, sure do have a poop.
Here we go. Open it up, we've
got an object of all of the things.
So dataset is just an object that all
ready. You don't have to select it.
You don't have to use any attribute
selectors from it. It will just take
everything that has data-dash on that
element and put it into a nice tidy little
object for you.
So we want to go back down to this. We'll
say suffix equals this.dataset.
and what do we call it, sizing. Good.
And then for some of them,
they don't have a sizing like the color
one, so I'm just going to say "or nothing"
because if I don't leave it at that, we're
gonna upend undefined in the end and
that's not what we want. So it's "or
nothing," it's just going to fall back.
So let's console.log suffix, see
what we're working with here.
So pixels, good. Pixels for that one. And
then when I hover over this one,
you see nothing and that's because
there is no suffix for the hex code.
Now, what we need to do is update the
actual variable. So how do you select a
variable? And then the way that that works
is we are going to select our entire
document which is our root here and
we're going to set a property of base,
spacing, or blur and you'll notice that we
use the name here, name spacing,
name blur, and name base. So we go down
here and let's console.log this.name.
Blur, spacing, base, good. We say
document.documentElement.style.setProperty
and we're going to set the property of
usually --base or --spacing but those
things are going to be variable so
because we're using back text here,
we can plop that variable name in this
.name and then it's going to be set
to this, .value. Now, that's not
going to get us all the way there,
and I'll show you just a sec here.
Let's open up our elements panel and let's
change our blur. You see what's happening
here? The blur value is changing but there
is no pixels being upended to the end.
And that's why we created this suffix
variable, so we can tack on the suffix
variable onto the end. And now when I
refresh, let's switch out the image here
because the other one's having trouble
loading. And I change one of these,
you'll see that the value is being updated
124px, blur 10px. As you change it
it's going to be immediately updated.
Let's double check that the color one
works as well. Perfect. So that's today's
exercise. Again, when you use a CSS
variable, you can then update that
variable on any element and any selectors
that are inside of that element that
reference that variable will be using it.
So one other thing you could do is you
could also scope them to be just on a
specific div. So if I were to take
this h2 and add an attribute of
style equals and I want to change the
variable base to be a badass,
oh, look what happened there.
So even though this base variable is right
here, because I've specified the variable
lower down and inside of that, this
highlight is referencing the variable,
this one wins out over this one. Much like
the CSS cascade, the closer one will
always win out. And I can go ahead
and keep changing this value,
and this one's not going to change because
I've updated it at a lower scope.
Hopefully you enjoyed that.
See you in the next one.
♪ [music] ♪