Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
Today we are going to be making this super
snazzy, what I like to call a flex
gallery, and I really like this one
because it doesn't include all that much
JavaScript, and it leans heavily upon
CSS for flexbox, for transitions,
and for some events that CSS is going to
emit to us. So, this is really cool,
we're going to lean on CSS quite a bit.
Let's take a look at what we're starting
with here.
We've got this thing I like to call flex
panels, and if we scroll down to the HTML,
we've got a div with a class of panels,
and each of these panels is going to be
called a panel, singular. And then inside
of each of those panels is going to be,
"Hey," "Let's dance," "Give," "Take,"
"Receive." And these are going to be words
that, when clicked, they're going to grow
in size, as well as they're going to fall
from the top and come up from the bottom.
So, what I want to start to do is I've
given you some CSS if we open this up in
the browser now. You see, we start with
some CSS that looks, but it doesn't do
anything and it actually is not in the
right place. So, I wanted to write the
actual important part, which is the
flexbox piece with you, as well.
Let's go up to our CSS, and first of all,
we need to get our panels going side by
side. So if we go the panels div, you do
display: flex on them,
and by the way, if you are new to flexbox,
I have an entire series at flexbox.io
that you can visit, and that will guide
you through, similar to this one,
as well. And when I make those flex
they're going to go side by side by side
by side, and just stick them all there.
Next, what we need to do is we need to go
to each of the individual panels and tell
them, "Okay, well this is as much room as
the flex-child needs." It's as big as the
words are, so this one is the biggest
because it has the biggest word,
"experience." But what we want to tell it
to do is that we've got all this extra
space here, "Why don't you split it
amongst yourselves, children?"
So we go to our panel and we simply just
say flex: 1, and what that means is that
each of them are going to evenly
distribute the extra space among each
other. And that 1 might not make sense,
but we're going to come back to that in
just a second, so believe me. There we go.
Okay, so flex of 1 will make them evenly
distribute the extra space in between
them, so I'm pretty happy with that.
Now, let's move on to each of the panels
and get them visually looking like this,
where the items are going to be centered
in thirds. So we're going to go to our
panel here, and first of all, just put a
border: 1px solid red on it,
just so that we can see what's going on
here. Visually, I think this will really
help us. So, what's going on here? We've
got each of these panels...oh,
we don't want to put the border on each of
the panels, sorry. We want to put the
border on each of the flex items or the
flex children, which is here .panel > *.
Let's put a border there just so we can
see what's going on here.
Okay, so these are our three items. Now, I
want them to...again,
I have all of extra work vertically, how
do I get them to go up and down?
So we'll go back to our panel here and
we'll say justify-content: center.
Where does that get us? That gets them
centered left to right. I want to say
align-items: center, which still won't get
us much, but we also need to make this
panel here display: flex. And this is a
really good example of when you will nest
flexbox, because... Let's take a pause for
a second. What is the flex container here?
Panels. What is the flex item? Panel. But
we're also going to make panel a flex
container. An element in CSS can be both a
flex item, which it is right here,
as well as a flex container, which we are
going to do by making it display: flex.
So by doing that, we stack them left to
right, because that's the default of
flexbox. We want to change that and we are
going to say flex-direction: column,
and that will vertically center them in
the middle, but then I also want each of
these items to take up one-third, and
that's just exactly what we've done.
So let's scroll down to our flex children,
our flex items, and we already put a
border on it and here we're going to flex:
1 0 auto, and that will give us these
here. And we want to display: flex on
that, as well, which doesn't do too much
except bring the text to the left. But if
we do justify-content: center and
align-items: center. Now we've got
everything perfectly centered.
This is just a lot of flexbox nested and
nested and nested, which allows us to get
this really cool layout.
Okay, so looking pretty good to me so far.
Now, what I want to do is I want to hide
"give," all the way up, and I want to take
"you can," and "today," and "receive," and
hide them all the way down. So what we're
going to use is translateY for that.
Let's go down right here. I'm going to say
.panel > *:first-child is going to be
transform: translateY(-100%). So each of
the first children are going to be -100%.
Okay, so that puts them off-screen, and
then the last-child is going to be 100%.
The idea that we're going for here is that
when you take off this translateY,
it's going to animate itself. See what
it's doing? It's going to transition
itself in and out, in and out, in and out.
And the way that that's going to work is
that when the panel has a class of
open-active, we are going to
translateY(0). And when the panel has a
class of open-active, we are going to take
the last-child and translateY(0), as well.
So, what that means is that if we take any
one of these panels, and add a class of
open-active, it will animate itself in
take it off, and they go away. So you
can take the border away if you sort of
get it now, where the elements are on the
page. I think we've got a pretty good idea
of visualizing it. So that is
what we've got so far.
The last bit of the puzzle is that when
these panels also have a class of open,
what's going to happen is that it needs to
get bigger. You see that the font-size
already changed, but when the panel has a
class of open, scroll down to line 85 or
so, we want to give it a flex of 5. And,
now, what does that mean?
Well, earlier we said a flex of 1
means that each of them are going to
evenly distribute the extra room.
So by giving it a flex of 5,
what that means is that when it has a
class of open, it's going to take 5 times
the amount of extra room as the rest of
them, because they are regular flex of 1.
And now we are having a flex of 5, and
that means it should just grow a little
bit bigger. So if I go to one of my panels
here, give it a class of open,
you see that it will animate itself in,
take it away, animate itself out.
I keep saying "animate", I mean
"transition", and why that's happening is
because of this. The panel has a
transition in which we are transitioning
the font-size over 0.7 seconds, and we're
using these cubic-beziers that we've done
in previous classes. And what that
does is allows us to get this cool,
like, open and close where it goes a
little bit bigger and a little bit smaller
than it should, then snaps back into
place. Now that we've got all of the CSS
in place, we really just have to write a
little bit of JavaScript so that when we
click them, it will do that adding and
removing of classes. So first we want to
grab all the panels. Make sure that that's
querySelectorAll, not querySelector,
and that will give us a node list of all
the different ones that we have.
And then we want to write a function
that's going to toggle that class of on or
open. So function toggleOpen(). So
this.classList.toggle('open').
And then on each of the panels
we're going to listen for a click.
Good. So we're going to take each of the
panels, loop over each one of them,
listen for a click on each one of them,
and then run the toggle function when it
is run. Often I have people ask me, "Why
isn't it toggleOpen like that?" Because
that would run on page load. What we want
to do here is we don't want to run the
function. We just want to give it
reference to the function and say,
"Hey, when someone clicks me, make sure
that you go find this function and run
it." So, let's see where we're at right
now. Oh, we've got a bit of an error here.
Missing a parenthesis on line 133, got it.
Doesn't seem to be working,
let's debug this real
quick.console.log('Hello'). There we go.
Hello, hello, hello. Why is it not
toggling the class of open?
Oh, I see the error here. It's because we
are listening on each individual panel,
singular, not all the panels. Now, when I
click it, it's going to add a class of
open to that specific panel, and
remove that class. Add that class
and remove that class.
Now, the second step is that once this has
finished transitioning itself open,
that's when I want to bring in the word
from the top and bring in the word from
the bottom. So, in a previous exercise,
what we did is we listened for the
transition end event, which is exactly
what we're going to do here.
Go down to your panels and just duplicate
that line. We're going to listen for the
transition end event, and we're going to
toggle class of open-active with a
function called toggleActive .
So let's go up here and write that,
and we'll say...normally, what
we'd do is we would say
this.classList.toggle('open-active'),
however, there is going to be multiple
transition end events being fired, and
I'll show you how to figure that out.
We pass the event to this,
comment that out for now, and
console.log(e.propertyName).
Let's see what we got here.
So I'm going to click on one of these,
which is going to trigger a transition.
When that transition is finished, it's
going to tell us what transitioned.
Oh, font-size and flex-grow. So two things
are being transitioned here.
Why? Because if you look at our CSS, when
the panel is open, we are transitioning
the flex and the font-size. Both of those
things are getting bigger when the class
of open. And really, we only care about
the flex-grow here, so what we can do is
we say if (e.propertyName). And
normally we'd say flex-grow, however,
I did find some bugs in Safari, where in
Safari it's just flex and in the rest of
the browsers it's flex-grow. So even
though if you scroll up here,
we have explicitly stated that we are
working with flex here, some of the
browsers tell it's flex-grow, some of the
them tell it as flex. So what we need to
do is just cover both of our bases, and
rather than checking if it's explicitly
flex-grow, we'll see if it includes the
word flex, and if that is true,
then we will toggle the
class of open-active.
So, again, what's happening here? We are
listening for a click on each panel.
When someone clicks we're going
to open it. That's going to then,
in turn, trigger a CSS open and when
that finishes, the second one,
transition end will fire, and that's when
we're going to toggle open-active.
And then it will just go the other way
when you click it off, as well.
Here we go, open it up and they animate
itself in from the sky and down from the
bottom and then you close it up and
they open themselves up, and close.
So this is pretty cool when you open up
multiple... What I really like about this
is you do not have to specify a
width for this specific gallery,
because if each of them have a flex of 5
they will simply each take a little bit
less of the extra room. If one of them,
it's going to take a lot more.
Hopefully, you liked that.
I'll see you in the next one.
♪ [music] ♪