Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
Today we're going to create what I like to
call a type-ahead feature where I've got a
list of cities and states with their
population in it. When I type something in
like new, it's going to show me everything
that matches the word new.
If I type in New York or Boston or West
it's going to show me every single city
and state that matches whatever I've typed
in along with the corresponding population
Now this data is going to be coming in
from an external source.
What I've done is I just went in GitHub
here, and I found a cities.JSON
file which will include the city
name, the state name, as well as the
population that we have here and I've put
that into a URL. So first thing that we
need to do is, we need to actually go and
fetch this data which is a huge array and
then once that data is back, whenever
someone types into this specific box,
we're going to filter that array down to a
subset of all of the ones that either the
city name or the state name will match.
So how we're going to do that? Well, first
of all, we need an empty array to put our
cities into so let's say, const cities
equals an empty array and then we need to
go out and fetch our data. We're going to
be using a new API in the browser called
fetch. And if you've done an HTML or XML
HTTP request in the browser before,
you probably have used like JQuery.dol.
JSON or a library like axios.
However, the browser now has a new one
built in which is called fetch.
So that's what we're going to use. We're
going to call fetch and you fetch the end
point. And what fetch will do, if you're
used to maybe running a callback like this
function, and you have the data, and then
you can const log the the data,
it works a little bit differently than
that because fetch itself will return what
is called a promise and I'll show you
that. If you we were to just put this
in a variable, const prom equals fetch and
console log prom. Open that sucker up in
our browser, you see that, oh prom.
Prom, here we go. You see that?
It doesn't return the data, it returns
what's called a promise which is sort of
like a something will eventually
come back from this fetch.
So the way that we can work with the
promise is you call .then against it.
So it's a .then. And it's going to return
to us just like a blob of data.
I like to call it a blob. And I'll show
you why. You might think like,
"Oh why, wouldn't that just be the list of
cities?" So from that let's console.log
the blob. So this is what comes back.
Response of course it worked, Two hundred,
okay, is true, good. Headers, we open up
the body. There's just a readable stream
locked false T, like what's going on here?
And what's happening is that the data that
comes back from our fetch, it doesn't
know what kind of data it is just yet.
Just it could be an image, it could be
some HTML, it could be some music that's
coming back. We explicitly
know that it is JSON.
So you might think, "Okay, that's fine.
Why don't we just do JSON.parse, right?
That should you work." But it doesn't
because the blob has to be converted from
the raw data that it is in into JSON. So
what you do from this is you call blob.
And if you look at this blob, and open the
prototype, you'll see that there is a
method called JSON right there. So if you
call blob.JSON, that itself is going to
return another promise which we're going
to call .then on. This is getting a little
bit hairy, so let's do this. Oh yeah, that
looks much better .then and that is
going to give you the raw data which
we can console log this data here.
Now when I refresh, we get a massive array
of all 1000 cities and states and
population and latitude and longitude from
each of the ones. Now how do I get this
data into cities? You might think, "Oh
I'll just do a Cities equals data, right?
No problem there. Assignment to a
const variable. So we just tried to
wipe out a const variable by
reassigning it to be the data.
So what you could do is say let
cities and that's a fine way to go
about it as cities by array or if you like
to keep your variables const because you
do not want that array changing,
you can push the items into cities.
So you might think, "Okay, cities.push"
and we'll say data, and look at cities.
Okay, this is an array of one thing but if
you open that array then you say,
okay that's not it. It's an array of
an array. Now, we're nested.
So how do I get each and every item to go
into cities? Well, you might know that
cities.push, if you push something
like one, two , three, four,
and then look at cities, you'll notice
that every time I have another argument to
push, it will put it as its own item in
the array. And the way that we can change
this array into individual arguments is we
spread into it. A spread is part of ES6
I've got a whole bunch of videos
in my other ES6 series,
but you simply spread into a function or
spread into this push method and that will
give us proper cities, there we go. Now
that's an array of a thousand different
cities that we have. Good.
Now I'm happy with that.
The next thing we need to do is when
someone then types into this box here,
I need to run a function that is going to
take this massive array and filter it down
into a subset where you can then listen
for it. So I'm going to create a function
here called find matches. And that's
going to take in a word to match,
and it's also going to take in the cities
array as we want to pass in the data into
this function that it's going to filter.
And from that, we are going to return
these cities array, but we're going
to call filter on it which is going to
sort of chisel it down into a
subset of that initial array.
So each one is going to have a place which
is each individual city and state and
population and everything like that. And
from that, we need to figure out,
here we need to figure out if the city or
state matches what was searched.
Right? Like if I were to run find matches
with Bos, it should show me Boston and
whatever other cities have the word Bos in
it. So we need a couple of reg access
because you might think like, "Okay, we'll
just return place.city.match." And
normally you could do something like this
where you search for the word bos and if
it does match, then it will be true, and
we will give ourselves a subset.
But the problem is that the word to match
is not always going to be bos or always
going to be new, or always going to
be York, it's going to be a variable,
and the variable is where to match.
So just popped in the working match?
No that doesn't work because it's actually
going to look for the word to match
So how do you put a variable into a
regular expression? Well, you can't just
do it in this syntax here. We need to
actually create a regular expression
outside of it. So let's go above here and
we'll say const regX equals new regEXP
and you pass at the word to match, and
that's going to be whatever the person
passes in Bos, New, York, etc, etc. And
then you pass it any of the flags that
you want. So G is going to be global
meaning it's going to look through
the entire string for that specific one.
And I is going to be insensitive meaning
that it's not a terrible person or it's
insensitive, it's going to match lowercase
as well as uppercase regardless of what
you're searching with. So now we call dot
match with our regX in here. And
that's going to take the place.city in.
If we take a look at our cities here,
you'll see that as each place is New York
and the city is going to be New York. But
we also need to match the state
which...that's a bad example. Here we go.
State is going to be California.
So we've got to return the place
that city.match regX or the
place.state.match regX. And that will
check if the city or the state has either
one, so if this one is true or this one is
true, the whole thing is going to be true,
and therefore our filter is going
to be made much smaller.
So if I were to then run this, if we were
to say, find matches, and we are to search
for Bos and we need to pass our cities
array here. What it returns to us is a
small array of two things, Boston and
Bossier City, good. We've got our find
matches function done. Then what we need
to do is create our display function.
So I say function, display matches and
that's going to be called whenever someone
changes the value on here. So I'm
going to console.log this .value.
And then we're going to select
this input that we're working here.
So what is the selector on here. Input
type of text class is search,
that's good for me. So I'm going to go
down here in case. Const search input
equals document.query selector.search.
And then we also want to select this UL
here which is suggestions. Then we'll say,
search input.add event listener.
We're going to listen for the change
event and when the input changes,
we are going to run find matches. Save. We
should now see when we run it.
Type in here and I click outside then it
runs that function, oh we got an error.
Cannot read property filter of undefined
in our...oh because we're not running fine
matches directly, sorry, we are running
display matches not find matches.
So if I type in here, like Bos and click
outside, it then will trigger in console
log this, which is the input.value and
that's whatever someone has typed in
here, new, click outside. So why do I need
to click outside? That's because the
change event only fires when you go off
that input not whenever you type into and
key up. So if you want it to also fire and
key up, just duplicate that it will listen
for the key up event and we'll just rerun
display matches on that as well.
Now if I type new, hello, bos, you get the
point. Every time we key up,
it's going to tell us what the person has
typed into that box.
Now what we want to do is go back to
this display matches function here,
and we are going to use this find
matches function that we built.
So say const match array equals find
matches and we are going to pass it this
.value as well as our cities array
and that should give us the match array.
Let's try it out. Whenever I type into, it
should run this caller function find ones
that match it, Bos. There we go. So the
first time I type B, there is a lot
of cities. Second time I type O, a
little less and then the third type,
I type Bos, it's going to give me that
array of just two cities that have
matched it. Good. So we've got the data,
and that's really what I'd like to stress
when we're doing this stuff. Get your data
first, get all your functionality in place
and then we'll worry about hooking
it up to event listeners as well as
creating the HTML that we need there.
So we're going to first loop over it. So
say const HTML equals match array.map
and each one is going to be the place,
what did we use up here?
Yeah, place, I like to keep it consistent.
And from each of those return back texts,
it's going to hold our list item LI.
Inside of that, we want a span with the
class of name just going to contain the
place.city and the place.state and below
that we're going to have a span with a
class of population, place.population.
Then finally once we've mapped over this
array, we can simply call suggestions dot.
And what are suggestions? That's the
square selector that we've done down here,
.inner HTML equals HTML, which is this
HTML that we have here.
One last thing is this map is going to
return an array when we really want just
one string. So we can call it quick.join
on the end, and that will turn it into
from an array with multiple items into one
big string. Let's give it a shot.
Bos, there we go, Boston, Massachusetts,
Bossier City. New, looking good.
A couple of last things we need to do. If
we look at the actual answer that we're
working here is we want to format these
numbers here as well as we want to
highlight the actual words like Wes in
West Virginia and West Sacramento.
So how do we do that? Well, let's go back
to our map function here.
And before we return, what we can then do
is create a regX or match the city name
and then we'll use that regX to replace
the word that it matches like Wes with
just a span of the class of HL and the
word that it matches.
So we're just going to be like plucking
the word Wes out and replacing it with
a span class of HL. So say const
regX equals new regXt. You'll see this
top value which is whatever the person
searched for. We want to search for that
globally because if it's matched more than
once in the city name, it would be kind of
cool to show that and insensitively
we don't care about capitals.
And then we will create a city name
variable where we're going to take the
place.city and we're going to
replace the regX, which is whatever
it matches with just a span with the
class of highlight and we'll pop in this,
.value, oh, I got to use back text
there. Here we go. So it's going to find
whatever it matched in the regX and
replace it with a span with a class of
highlight and then the value that the
person had searched for.
So now when we take that city name, we can
replace it. Place that city with the city
name variable which is going to include
the HTML for us. Type in Bos and there we
go, it's matching it. If I type in
Wes, working so far but we also have to
do it for the state name. So we'll just
duplicate this and change it to state name
and place.state.replace. And then you
take that state name variable and replace
it right here. There we go.
Looks like it's working.
Finally, what we need to do is find a
function that is going to put in commas
for us. So I've just got a function right
here. You can grab this from the answer if
you don't feel like typing it or go to
your nearest stack overflow and take that
answer. And I'm just going to paste it in
here. Number with commas is just going to
replace it and again it'll
give you those nice commas.
So we can go to our population. We say
number with commas, and it will then give
us those nice commas instead of
everything that we have there.
So new...there we go, we're matching new
in the state, we're matching new in the
city name as well as we're putting in
those nice commas to display the data to
the user. That's it for today. If you want
to a little bit more of a challenge,
maybe go to this data and say, "What else
could I use to sort these data?" Maybe you
could figure out how does geolocation work
which is coming in a future video and
sort it by what are the cities that are
closest to me rather than just the order
that they appear in this array
explicitly. Thanks a lot and I'll see
you in the next one.
♪ [music] ♪