♪ [music] ♪
Today is Array Cardio day two, where we're
going to learn about a few new array
methods that come in handy when you're
working with data. So we've got two arrays
here with some people and some comments,
and first, we're going to learn about
.some and .every. .some will check if at
least one thing in your array meets what
you're looking for. So,
we will say const
is_adult = and call .some against it. Now
.some will take a function that will check
it for every single one that we have.
That's going to give us our person and we
will say if person.year...and now we need
like the current year, so you could take
the current year and minus that or what we
could do is we could say const
current_year =
new_date.get_full_year(). Say if
current_year - person.year >= 19,
then return true, and what that should do
if we console.log is_adult is give us true
because there is someone who is greater or
equal to. There we go.
Little thing you can do in console.log is
if you can pop curly brackets around it,
it's going to show you the name of the
variable as well as the value.
So the is_adult is going to
be equal to true. That makes sense.
Now we can make this a lot
simpler. I'm going to rewrite it
here.const is_adult = people.some(person)
and from that, we'll have a block and we
need the current year again and then we
can simply return current_year -
person.year >= 19, and that's going to be
a lot simpler than if writing it like
this. I think it
reads a little bit nicer. We used an arrow
function here, and we return the current
year. You want to be a total hotshot,
you could take this entire thing, pop it
in some parentheses here,
get rid of that, and then use the implicit
return without the curly brackets here.
Hotshot. That would do the same thing.
Let's save it. I would have to comment
this one out so we don't duplicate the
variable. You still get
true in there. All right, let's do the
next one which is going to be .every().
So is everybody 19. So we can simply just
take this, what we've done here,
and replace it with .every(), and then
const all_adults. So log adults,
and that's going to give us false. Why is
that giving us false?
Because not every single item in the array
is going to meet our criteria.
So, .some() will check if one, .every()
will check
for every single one of them. Next up, we
have array.prototype.find() and .find() is
kind of like .filter() but instead of
returning you a subset of the array,
it's going to return you the first item
that it finds. So we want to find the
comment with the id of 823423. So say
const comment = and we'll take this
comments array. We'll call .find() on it
and we will run a function against it
which will give us the comment
and we'll say if comment.id, I believe
it is. Let's double check that. There we
go. Comment.id = that...is it a string?
No, it's a number...then return true. And
then we should be able to console.log() a
comment. Good. We've got that one specific
comment, this is "super good." Now take
a second, pause the video, try and convert
this to a arrow function with an implicit
return. So what we could do instead is
const comment...
whoa, comment, there we go... comments.
find(comment), and then we simply just
return this bit right here. And because
that is going to be true or false,
we don't need to have an if statement,
because it's just going to return a
Boolean of true or false, and then that is
a nice one-liner, rather than having to do
it in that long, and then that should
still work exactly the same.
Good. Next up, and finally, we have
.find_index() which is going to find where
something is inside of the array. Let's
say I wanted to delete one of these,
but in order to delete something from an
array, you need to know where in the array
it actually is. So if we've only got this
id, we can say const index = comments.
find_index(), and then we'd do the
exact same thing we did before.
Comment is equal to that, and if we
console. log() the index, it'll tell us
that it is one which should mean it is the
second item in our array. There we go.
Now, how do you delete it? Well, there's
two ways you could delete it from the
array. We could simply just say comments.
splice(). We could start at the index and
go for one. Let's take a look at what
we've got here if we type in comments now.
Console.table() our comments. You see
that the "super good" comment is totally
gone, or what you could also do, and this
is very popular in the Redux world,
is you create a new array of the updated
comments, where you would say something
like const new_comments = an array, and
what you do is you just take a copy of the
comments before it. So we say comments.
slice(). We start at zero and we go until
the index, and then we start at the index
plus one and go until the end.
So, you don't pass it anything, and that's
just going to build a new array of the
comments. So if I console.table() the
comments, good. Console.table
(new_comments). Oh, what did we
forget here? It gave us an array of two
arrays, so what's wrong with this? It's
because we did not spread the items into
the new array. And again, if this is not
making sense to you, feel free to stick
with your splice, or go back into my ES6
videos and check out the spread operator
ones. So if we console.table() the new
comments, that one's gone.
However, we still have the original
comments array where it says "super good."
So that's just a couple more array methods
that you should keep in your back pocket.
Knowing all of the possible array methods
and when to use them can come in really
handy when you're massaging your data.
♪ [music] ♪