Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
This is a quick video on some
dev tools and console tricks.
Chances are you know most of these
already, but I hope that you just learn
like one or two little nuggets from
watching this quick video.
So what we've got here is I've got a
paragraph tag, when you click it,
it's going to run a function called
"makeGreen". This function here.
And I've just done that inline for
simplicity's sake. I could have added
event listener, there's no difference
there. And when I run it,
it will just take the first paragraph on
the page and make it green and up the
size, right? So that's something that
happens to people, where they ask me,
"Hey, I have some JavaScript running on
the page but I don't know what is causing
it. I don't know what is actually
changing it. I know it's JavaScript,
but I don't know where the JavaScript that
is changing that is running." So what you
can do it you can inspect it, find it in
your DOM here, break on,
attribute modifications. There's some
other ones here, like when you remove
a child or you were to change one of the
children's texts or attributes or
something like that. We want this one,
attribute modification. Now, when you
click it, it's going to pop a debugger
command in. It's a break point for us
here, and it will then pause. Exactly
where it paused, it will tell us what the
paragraph is, and it will show us the line
of code that is causing that attribute.
I can pause it and go through, and we're
done. So we can take that off just by
going back to our elements panel,
and taking that off.
Next up, we have a whole bunch of
console. things, and you probably know
about console.log, like, hello, which
will give you, obviously, you've seen this
a million times, will log it. You can
also interpolate values into it,
so console.log, Hello I am a %s string!
And then whatever you pass it in
the other ones, you may have done another
language like PHP in the past where it
does this for you, and that will
interpolate whatever you have passed as
the second one into the first one. Now, I
don't use that all that much anymore now
that we have ES6 back-ticks, I much prefer
to do, console.log('Hello I am $')
but it's totally up to you,
which one you would like here.
We can also style our text with %c.
So, console.log('I am some great text')
And if we put a %c in front of there, and
on the second one, we do things like
font-size, and you can apply any font CSS
to it, 50px. Whoa! I am some great text.
We can also do things like background:red.
Whoa! You can do things like
text-shadow: 10px 10px 0 blue.
You get the point here.
You can do some pretty fun stuff with it.
So you do %c in front of the thing that
you want to style, and then the second
argument that you pass to console will be
interpolated right into there.
I'm going to comment that out
because it's obnoxious.
We have console.warn, which will say,
"OH NOOO" And that will give us a warning,
and will tell us the stack trace as to
where it got called. We have
console.error which will throw,
well, sorry, it won't throw an error.
It will just display an error in the
console. And again, that will also give
you a stack trace as to where that was. If
we had a couple functions calling to get
to that point, it would give you the
entire stack trace there.
We have console.info which
will give you a little bit of info,
like, I had a fun...
Hold on, let me find you a fun fact, here.
Crocodiles eat three to four
people per year. That's a fun fact.
It should be console.funfact, but
it's info, and it will give you the little
"i" info one.
You can use console.assert to check if
things are true. So if one is equal to one
you will say "That is wrong!" And if
you run this, you don't see anything.
Why? Because that is true. Console.assert
will only fire if something is wrong.
And then it will tell you, "Assertion
failed. That is wrong." If I were to grab
the paragraph on the page, so,
const p=document.querySelector,
"paragraph', and then you could assert
that "p.classlist.contains(ouch)" and you
could tell the user, "That is wrong!" And
if the classlist does not contain "ouch"
it will tell you that is wrong or you must
supply class...you get the point here.
You can test for something and if it is
false, it will throw this error into your
console here. And if it is true, nothing
will happen. So you don't have to have an
"if" statement in here.
We have "console.clear" which will clear
your console. If you really want to mess
with a developer you could just put that
at the bottom of your javascript
file. Because that's really frustrating.
Viewing DOM elements. So I've got this
paragraph here, and if I were to
"console.log" that paragraph that we
selected earlier, you see this,
the actual paragraph.
But how do you know what
are the available methods
and all the properties on that
element? Well if you want to use
"console.dir", that's going to give you a
dropdown. So that's the element
"console.log". "Console.dir" is going to
allow you to open it up and take a look at
the class list. Whoa! Open that right up.
Child knows the children,
the dataset on that specific one, the
style, all the different properties and
methods that live. If you want to see all
the different methods, you crack open the
prototype. All of the stuff that lives on
that element, "console.dir" will show you,
whereas "console.log" is going to show you
the actual element itself.
Grouping things together. This one is
actually pretty cool. I'm just going to
run another "console.clear" in here. If I
were to take this "dogs" array that I've
got up at the top here and loop over each
one. So "console.dogs.forEach", "dog",
and then for each of these I'm just going
to do "console.log(`This is
$`)" and "This is Snickers,",
"This is Hugo." But what if I have some
other information? Age. I want to have
like another one, "dog.name" is "dog.age"
years old. Okay, and maybe another one,
"dog.name", "dog.age*7" dog years old.
So this gets a little bit hairy, got a lot
going on here, and imagine you were doing
more stuff than just console logging three
strings. You have a lot of stuff.
So what we can do is we can say
"console.group" and you can start it up
and we'll use the dog's name here,
"dog.name". And when you're done, you say
"console.groupEnd" and then you pass
the same string that you used to define
that group. Now when you open it up,
you've got "Snickers" and "Hugo",
these are the two groups that we've made
by passing it, and you can close,
open, and close them. If you feel like
this is still a little bit messy,
you can switch out "group" with
"groupCollapsed", and by default they will
be collapsed. Which is really nice because
you might not necessarily need that
information, but if you do, you can crack
open the associated one that you're
looking for and see all the info that is
associated for that one.
"Console.count" will count however many
times you use a specific word,
or number, or object, or DOM node, or
anything that you have. So "console.count"
"Wes", I run that a couple of times, it's
going to tell me how many times I have
run it. If I were to take and say "Steve"
in the middle, and then do a couple more
of those, another one down here and a
couple more. So I'm all over the place
here. It's going to just log them in
real time, telling me how many we've
counted at that time.
Finally, we have "Timing". If you want to
see how long something takes,
what you can do is start a timer. So
"console.time", we'll say "fetchingData",
then you could do something that takes
time, like fetch some data from github.
And when you are done, you simply run
"console.timeEnd" and then you pass the
same string that you used to start it. And
you can obviously "console.log" your data
at that time. Then that will tell us,
fetching data took 160 milliseconds,
this time 104 milliseconds, 57, 62, 75,
etc., etc. You can see how long these
things are taking. I know there also is
"performance.now" in the browser,
but this is a nice way just to get a quick
idea of how long your things are taking.
You don't have to have variables
or anything like that.
You just start and stop them.
Finally, there's one last one, which is
"console.table", but I've been showing you
that one in every single video so far.
You probably know about it.
But you can take an array of objects, so
an array which is "dogs" of objects,
which is each dog, and assuming that they
all have the same properties,
like "name" and "age", it will display
them in a nice table for you,
like that. It gets a little bit hairy
when you have a few other,
but you can always drag and drop the
things, different parts that you want.
That's it. Hopefully you learned
a thing or two. I will see you tomorrow!
♪ [music] ♪