Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
Today's exercise is, I think, a bit of a
tough one and I really want you to give it
a shot on your own. Let me explain what it
does and then I'll give you a shot to go
and do it on your own. The end code
is not actually all that complicated.
I found that it was a little bit tough for
me to come around to this idea at first
though. So, here's how it works. You click
a checkbox, you hold down your shift key,
you click another one, and all the
checkboxes in between the first one and
the second one that you clicked will then
be checked. This works top to bottom,
but also bottom to top. So, if I
click on this one, hold down shift,
click on here, it's going to go bottom to
top. So, it goes all ways depending on
what you're working on. You can go either
way. And this is a fairly common thing
that you're going to see in applications
such as Gmail, where you want to select a
whole bunch of emails and delete them
at once. Let's take a quick look at our
HTML here. We've got our input with the
type of checkbox and a paragraph type.
Probably a label would be more suited
for something like that, but whatever.
We are working with it. Then we've
got a script tag here. And by the way,
if you're wondering why I always
indent my script tags so far to the left,
it's just because I need the
horizontal space. If it bugs you,
I'm sorry, but I need to make sure
my code fits on the screen. Now,
give it a shot yourself and I'll see you
back here, hopefully triumphant,
maybe not, and we'll go through it
together. So, here we go. Well, first
thing we need to do is select every single
one of the checkboxes because we need to
listen for when they get checked.
So, we'll say, "const checkboxes =
document.querySelectorAll." And we want
to grab ".inbox" and we want to grab the
inputs. I have a type of checkbox that
I'll probably input on there as well.
Good. Let's just double check that we got
all those checkboxes, "querySelectorAll."
You have to spell it right,
"querySelectorAll." There we go.
Input, input, input. Okay. Good.
I've got all of the inputs
that I'm working with here.
Now we need to listen for when
one of them gets clicked or changed.
So, we will take the checkboxes,
and we will loop over each one.
Checkbox. And on that we are going to tick
the checkbox and "addEventListener."
We are going to listen for a click. I
initially thought that you had to listen
for the change event, but apparently the
click event will fire even if you use your
keyboard,.which is really handy to know.
We've got our "addEventListener,"
and when someone clicks it, we are going
to run a function called "handleCheck."
Now let's go up here and make that
function. We'll have this event and we'll
just console log the event. Click.
All right. Click. Click. Click.
We're getting the
information for every single one.
Now, this is where the hard
part starts to happen, where we need
to log, when I check my first one, we need
to put that into a variable. Because when
you check your second one and you're
holding down shift, we need to know what
that last one was. So, we're going to
make a variable up here called "let
lastChecked." And the reason why I'm
using let is because that's going to be
reassigned constantly. And then inside of
here, sort of the last thing that we're
going to do is we'll say "lastChecked =
this." That's like the last thing we're
going to do but we'll put it on there.
Now, when I click one and we type in
"lastChecked," we have a reference
to the input that was last checked.
Now up here, a couple of things we need to
do. We need to check if they had the shift
key down. So, I'm going to say, "if
e.shiftKey." If the event ".shiftKey" is
there, that means they were holding
it down. Then we'll go ahead and write our
code. However, the other thing
we need to do is when I uncheck,
it will also trigger "handleCheck." So, we
need to make sure that check if they had a
shift key down and check that they
are checking it. So, not unchecking it.
Right? Because you don't care if they're
unchecking it. You want to check if they
are uncheck... Okay, let's stop saying
the word checked. Let's gut it.
And "this.checked." Like it's taboo.
Stop saying it. So if the shift key is
down and they are checking the box, then
we can go ahead and do what we please.
And inside of here, now, this is where our
sausage gets made. What we are going to do
here, is we are going to loop through
every single checkbox. Every time this
happens, we are going to loop over every
single checkbox. And what we're going to
do is we're going to look for the first
one that was checked, and then I check
down here. What's going to happen is,
we're going to say, "Oh, you're not.
You're not the first one. Oh, you are the
first one. Okay, good." Then go to the
next one, check it. Next one, check it.
Next one, check it. This one, "Oh,
you're the last one that's checked.
Stop it." And then these two won't be
checked. So, rather than try and figure
out where in the dom they are and trying
to figure out like which elements are
in-between it, and finding parents and...
I find that's really fragile a way to do
it because you're depending on having the
HTML set just so, and then if someone else
comes along and changes the
HTML a little bit, it will just break.
So, we are going to loop over every single
checkbox. We're going to create a
variable called in-between. And what
in-between will do is we'll loop over this
one and I'll say in-between false. We'll
loop over this one, in-between false.
We'll loop over this one and it's going to
say, "Okay, this is where we started."
We are now in the area which we
wish to check, so let's check it.
Check it. Check it. Check it. Because the
in-between variable is going to be set to
true when we are here. And then when we
hit our last one, we are going to say
in-between is false, because we are done
and we're no longer going to check any
others. So, this will probably take a
couple of read overs, but let's get it.
So, we will go up here before we do the
f statement, we'll say, "let inBetween =,"
capital B on that in-between,
"false." So, we're not in-between.
And then here we are going to
loop over every single checkbox.
Say, "checkboxes.forEach" checkbox,
and let's just console log checkbox.
See where we're at. So, if I click
one, nothing. And now I'm going to
hold down my shift key and
click another one. Okay, so when that
happened, I get every single checkbox
along the way. Now we need to figure out,
as we are looping for this, we've got to
set this in-between variable to true.
And the way that we are going to do that
is we say "if checkbox is equal to this or
checkbox is equal to last checked, then
in-between is..." We normally would say
in-between is equal to true, but since we
wanted to go both ways, we say in-between
to the opposite of itself. What? Okay,
let's go through this. One sec. If the
checkbox is equal to this, so here we go,
check it. Let me do it backwards this way
so we can understand. So, check this
one. I hold down shift and I click on
"check one item." And what's going
to happen is we're going to go through
this one. It's going to say, "Is that
in-between? No." It's going to go through
this one and say, "Is the checkbox
equal to this? And what is this?"
This is going to be the one that got
checked. And that's the checkbox.
This one is going to be equal to the same
one that we are currently looping over.
So, that going to be true. So, we're
going to turn on that in-between variable.
And then the other way around it is if we
go this way, last checked, and then we go
down to good luck and click it again. It's
going to still go from top to bottom but
it's going to say, "If the checkbox is the
last checked one," mean that this is the
currently checked one, but "check
one item" is the last checked one.
So, I feel like I'm saying "checked"
a lot, but we got this. We got this.
So in-between, so you could console log
starting to check them in-between.
Check there, check there. And what happens
is, here we go, one, we get to this one
and it says, "Okay. Good. Now we're
starting, starting to check them
in-between. Down, down,
down, down, and then down.
And then once we hit this one,
that's the last one that we checked. So,
it console logs it again. That means we're
finished, which is why we
do this opposite thing. So, if it's true,
it's false. If it's false, it's true. And
then we hit these last two, which aren't
going to be. So, we can say down
here we have another "if" statement that's
"if inBetween," capital B, "then
checkbox.checked equals true."
Check it. Hold down shift, check another
one. Bam. Nailed it. Okay, let's see
what's going on there.
We set a flag variable called in-between
that is set to false. Once we hit that
first one, it's going to be true,
which is going to check if it's on and
then we're going to programatically set it
to checked with Javascript. And we're
going to do that for every single one unti
we hit that last one, which our flag
variable called in-between, gets set to
false and it will no longer run it
for these first two or for these last two.
And that works both ways from bottom to
top because we did this little diddy right
here where we checked if it's equal to
this, which is the one we clicked,
or if it's the one that we last checked.
So, that's it. It's actually fairly
simple now that we have it. It's not a lot
of code. It's just a little bit hard to
understand what's going on. So, maybe
go through that a couple more times.
Go do it yourself from scratch so you
totally understand it. Other than that,
I hope you enjoyed it. Let me
know what you think of that one.
See you tomorrow.
♪ [music] ♪