Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
Today, we are building in HTML5 video
player. If you've ever tried to style the
default video player, you'll know that
it's really not all that possible.
If I take a look at what the video player
looks like by default,
this is currently what it looks like in
Chrome. But that changes sometimes,
as well as it's different from browser to
browser. So this is what it looks like.
You get some basic controls. You get to be
able to scrub the video.
You can change the volume and full-screen
it, as well as a couple other things that
happen. Now, what we want to build is this
totally custom interface,
where we're going to hide the controls and
we're going to build our own interface
with a button to pause and play it.
There's going to be a button that just
does the volume, a slider. This is going
to speed it right up so it goes much
faster. It's going to bring it right down
to be nice and slow.
As well as we're going to have these nice
little Skip buttons that allow you to skip
forward 25 seconds, skip back 10 seconds,
and then finally when you click the video
itself, it will pause and play. So there's
a whole lot going on here,
and at any time during this tutorial, what
I want you to do is just pause the video
and try to maybe tear off just doing the
sliders, or just doing the scrubber,
or just doing the Skip buttons. See if you
can just get a couple of features on your
own, and then come on back and join me for
the parts that you're having trouble with.
So I've already done some CSS for you.
There's really not all that much going on
here. It's just going to be... I've just
got to take my... If Throttle Play is
annoying you, we take this little off.
Whoa, as I save. Okay. I've done some CSS.
Sorry. This hilarious bunny is getting me.
The CSS has been done for you.
But there's really not all that much here.
There's just a bunch of divs,
and then when you hover over it, I just
transition the position of that div up and
down, up and down, depending on where
we're at. What we have here is we've got a
div with a class "player". This is the
video element that we're working with.
Then, everything below it is just HTML
that we've built for the controls.
So we've got a progress bar here. Inside
of that, we have a field.
I've got a Player button here that we're
going to pause and play.
There's an input for the slider, which has
a Min, a Max, and a Step,
which is how much it's going to increment
each notch on the slider.
Same for playback rate. Then, I have these
Skip buttons. I'm going to talk a little
bit about why I chose to use data skip in
just a second. So this one is pretty big,
so I'm not just going to stick it in a
script tag here. We're actually going to
put it in a separate scripts.js file that
we're going to be working in here.
So let's get going. The first thing that
we need to know is there's going to be
pretty much three pieces of this. First,
we're going to get our elements,
and then we are going to build our
functions. Then, we are going to hook up
the event listeners. So let's start with
getting our elements on the page.
There's a whole bunch that we need here.
We're going to first get the player,
so "const player =
document.querySelector.player". Then,
inside of that player, because that's sort
of like the papa div here,
inside of that is we're going to grab
everything else. So we need the video
itself, and we're going to call
"player.querySelector", and inside of that
we'll look for the ".viewer", because
that's the class that that video has right
there. Okay, working good so far. Other
things we need is the progress bar,
the progress field, the toggle, the Skip
buttons, and the player slider.
So I'm just going to blow these out real
quick. Otherwise, you can just grab them
from the answer. I'm sure you understand
what's going on here.
We're just selecting elements from the
page. If you'd like to see me type them,
I'm sorry. But we've got them going right
here. So we've got our progress bar,
and I'll explain exactly what all of these
are. Next, what we want to do,
let's just start easy and work with the
Toggle Play. So we're going to have a
function called "togglePlay". When that is
called, we are going to either call
".play" on the video, or ".pause". So what
we can do is we can just say "if
video.pause", because pause is a property
that lives on the video...
There is no playing property. There is
only a pause property. We'll say
"video.play else video.pause". Good. So
now, if we open up our dev tools here and
call "togglePlay", you'll see that starts
to play. If I call it again,
it's going to pause it. One little thing
that you could do here is you could say
"const method =" and use a [turnery]
operator, I don't know how to say things,
"play otherwise pause". Then, because the
method name is in a string here you can
simply just call "video", access the
method name, and then immediately call it.
Some people don't like that, because they
find it hard to read.
Don't send me angry mail. Just don't use
it if you don't like it.
But that is sort of a way. You could even
just put this sucker right inside of here,
if you wanted to get really crazy. But
we're not dipping down here.
Let's just double-check that this still
works. Working good for me.
Okay. So that's our Toggle Play. Now, what
we need to do is hook it up both to when
you click the video, as well as when you
click this button. So first,
we're going to go down to hook up our
event listeners. We'll say
"video.addEventListener('click',". When
that happens, we are going to run
"togglePlay". Good. Now, let's try it out.
Click, it's going. It's going.
Click it again. It pauses on and off, on
and off. Good. Next, we want to hook up
this button right here. So what did we
call that button. That is the Toggle
button. You can say "video". Or we can
pretty much just duplicate that line and
switch out the "toggle",
"addEventListener('click', togglePlay".
There we go. It's working for us. You'll
notice that this button here isn't
changing, and for that we need to update
the actual text of this button inside of
here. So one way that we can do that and
you might think, "Okay.
We'll do that in here, where we'll get the
button and we'll say '.textContent =' and
figure out whatever the Play button is."
But the better way to do that,
because there are other ways that you
could pause a video other than clicking on
the video and toggling it, sometimes
people have plugins. Sometimes people
have, like maybe you want to pause the
video if a pop-up opens.
So rather than hook into this "togglePlay"
function, what we want to do is listen to
the video for whenever it is paused. So
whatever causes it to pause,
then we can just update the actual buttons
right here. So what we could do is we will
go to our video, and I'm going to group
these together, "video.addEventListener",
and we're going to listen for play. When
that runs, we are going to make a function
called "updateButton", and console.log
"update the button", we'll just say that.
Take that Update button. When the video is
played, run "updateButton",
and when the video is paused or pause is
the event, sort of like click,
it will also run. So now, if I click it,
see what's going on here?
Every time I click it, it's going to
trigger a play or a pause event,
which will in turn run our "updateButton"
function. So if we go inside of our
"updateButton" function, we will say
"const icon =" and we simply say
"this.pause". Why can we use "this" in
this case? Because it's bound to the video
itself. "This.pause" if that is true, then
we will put the Play button in there.
Otherwise, we will put the pause icon. If
you need to grab these icons,
you can just grab them from the answer
file. Then, we take that icon and say
"toggle". What's toggle? Well, if we go up
here, toggle is our Toggle button,
which is this button right here has a
class of "toggle". Good.
So we'll say "toggle.textContent = icon".
Or again, yes, you could take this,
and just slap it right inside of there.
I'm just going to do it in two steps,
and that should be it. Uh-oh. Error,
"online 17". What did I do?
I got two question marks. What a silly
thing to do. Here we go.
Oh. It doesn't seem to be working. Let's
debug this real quick.
Console.log, it ran. Okay. It's running.
Now, let's console.log the icon.
Oh, you know what? There's no property
called "pause". It's "paused".
There we go. Now, it's up and running.
It's working, and then if I click this
button itself it will also... But if I
also just call it from the console
"video"... Or is it "viewer"? No. I think
it's "video", which is the video.
If I just call "video.play" on it, it's
going to start playing.
But look. Ha-ha. It's worked. If I call it
again or call ".pause",
it's updated the button for us. So you see
how we didn't have to hook into this
function? We simply just listened for the
event. Good. What should we do next here?
We've got the Play button working. Let's
do these Skip buttons here.
So we're going to make a function called
"skip", and what we then need to do is
understand how much it's going to be
skipped. The way that I like to define how
much the video is going to be skipped is
to go to the actual DOM element,
and let's look at these Skip buttons that
we have here. They have a "data-skip" -10,
which means it's going to go back 10
seconds, and a data-skip of 25,
which means it's going to go forward 25
seconds. I really like this approach,
because that means I can put a "data-skip"
on absolutely anything.
It could be a picture of myself, and when
you click my face it will skip to the end,
because you don't want to see it at all.
So we can put a "data-skip" on absolutely
anything, and that's the way that it's
going to work. So before we run this skip,
let's just console.log "Skipping!".
[inaudible 00:11:45] down here,
and we'll listen for a click on anything
that has a "data-skip".
Now, let's look at the top here. Skip
buttons is equal to anything that has a
"data-skip" attribute, which is why I said
you could put a "data-skip" on absolutely
any element. So we'll say
"skipButtons.forEach(button =>
button.addEventListener", and we are going
to be listening for a click.
When that happens, we are going to run the
"skip" function. Good.
Let's try it out. Skipping, skipping,
skipping. Now, what's cool about that is
instead of console logging "Skipping",
let's console.log "this.dataSet" and see
what we have there, is we get an object
which has that skip value in it.
So we can take that "this.dataSet.skip",
and we say
"video.currentTime+=this.dataSet.skip".
Now, that's a string, so we should wrap
that in a parse bloat, and that will
convert it into a true number.
Now, if we play it, and we click our Skip
button, it'll jump back and forward,
back and forward. Next, let's work with
these range sliders here.
If you take a look, we have an input type
of "range". The name is "volume".
Then, we have another one where the name
is "playback rate". I've purposely done
that with "volume" and "playback rate",
just so that they line up with the
properties on the actual video. So what
we're going to do is first of all,
we're going to listen for a change on
those specific sliders. So we're going to
make a function called
"handleRangeUpdate". I'm just going to
console.log "this.value". Then, we're
going to go down here and listen for a
change event on each of those ranges.
[inaudible 00:13:46]
"ranges.forEachRange", and then the
"range.addEventListener('click'," is going
to run the function "handleRangeUpdate".
Oh, not "click", "changeEvent".
Give it a refresh. Now, if I change one of
these, .035, change one of these,
1.75, 1.5, 1.3. Another thing we could do
is we could just duplicate this and listen
for a mouse move event. This will fire
regardless of if you're clicking or not.
But what you can, if you want to have a
little bit more practice,
is go back and set a flag so that when you
click down and move it,
much like we did with the canvas, and
click up, you are only updating the
property when you are clicked down. But
for that, we've got it updating in
real-time, rather than just when we let go
of the button. So we have this step value,
and we could also console.log "this.name".
Coincidentally, volume and playback rate
are the two properties on the video that
we need to update. So we simply just need
to say "video", and the property you want
to update is called "this.name",
which is either going to be "volume" or
"playback rate". So we'll say "this.name =
this.value", because that's the value
that's already being piped in.
So now, if we go ahead and play it, there
the volume is right down,
all the way up, [run] super-fast,
super-slow. You get the point,
right? That one is a pretty simple one.
I'm going to [inaudible 00:15:37] those
console logs, as well as this console log
here. Next up, let's deal with the big
one, which is this progress bar here. So
first of all, when you play the video,
the progress bar should be updating in
real-time. Let's do that first.
Then, second of all, when you click on it
and drag, it should update the video to
correspond with that lace. So first, we're
going to make a function called
"handleProgress", and we are going to make
a percentage. Because essentially,
how it's going to work is we're going to
go in there, and we're going to inspect
this progress field here. You see how we
have a flex basis value?
We're just going to be updating that flex
basis value, sort of like updating the
width, of the progress bar. It's just
going to correspond with how long it is.
So if we have 0% being not started at all,
100% being totally finished,
we simply just need to calculate that
knowing, "How long is the video and how
far are we right now?" So we'll "const
percent =" say "video.currentTime /
video.duration". Current time and duration
are just properties on that video,
and we multiply it by 100. So we're
getting a not 0.5, but 50%.
Then, we simply take the progress bar,
which we've selected at the top here,
"progressBar", and we append the styles.
".style.flexBasis =" and we simply pop in
the percent variable and put a percent
sign on the end there. So that doesn't
work just yet, and why not? It's because
we've created the progress,
and if I were to run it manually it would
update itself. But we want it to run every
so often. So should we put that in like a
timeout or an interval and run it every
second? No. What we'll do is, again, we
will listen for the video to emit an event
called "timeupdate", and when that happens
we will run "handleProgress".
So you just duplicate one of these,
"video.addEventListener". We're going to
listen for the "timeupdate" event, and
we're going to run "handleProgress" when
that happens. There's also an event called
"progress" and I don't know the difference
between the two. I've looked and I don't
really understand. But as far as I've
tested, both "progress" and "timeupdate"
will just trigger when the video is
updating its timecode, and then if it's
paused it's not going to be unnecessarily
running that function. So now, we'll give
it a play and it seems to be working just
fine. If I use these Skip buttons to skip
ahead, you'll notice that it updates
itself nicely as well. Finally, the big
one that we want here is the scrub.
How this is going to work is we are going
to listen for a click on this video bar
here. Wherever I have clicked, let's say I
click right here, it's going to...
Say, like you've clicked... How wide is
this bar here? Six hundred and forty
pixels. So let's say I click at 320 pixels
in. We know that 320 pixels is halfway to
640. So I should scrub the video 50% or
50% of its duration. So we're going to
make a function called "scrub" here, and
when that happens we're going to get the
event. Let's just console.log the event
here, and we'll go down to the bottom
here, and we will get our progress bar. We
are going to listen for a click,
and when that happens we are going to run
"scrub". So let's see how we're doing
here. Open up your console. Play it. Now,
click somewhere on it.
I'm going to click about halfway. Okay.
Now, we've got this mouse event,
and inside the mouse event we are going to
see that we have "e.offsetX",
which is exactly what we used in the
canvas tutorial. So here it is.
It tells me I clicked 283 pixels into this
bar, because that bar is positioned
relative. So given that knowledge, we can
do a little bit of math.
So I'm going to say "const scrub time =
e.offsetX". I'm going to pause these
bunnies here. Hold on. "/" and now we have
to figure out what is the width of this
entire progress bar? Well, we've already
selected it into a variable called
"progress", and we can grab the width of
it with "offsetWidth".
That'll give us the entire width of the
bar. That gives us a percentage like 50.5
or 0.6 for 60%, and we simply just
multiply that by the video's duration.
So if it's a 60-second clip, you're
halfway through, it's going to tell us
that you should scrub to 30 seconds. Then,
we simply just update the video,
"video.currentTime = scrubTime". Let's see
where we're at now.
So if I play it and I click about halfway,
ah, it jumps exactly to where I've tried
to click it. Good. Now, let's work on the
actual dragging and dropping of it.
Because you don't want to just listen for
when someone moves it.
You want to listen for when someone clicks
and moves it all around.
So let's just do it where you mouse move
over top of it. So we'll take
"progress.addEventListener", and we are
going to listen for a mouse move.
We're just going to scrub it there without
thinking about clicking just yet.
Play it. Watch. As I move my... It's a
little bit jerky, because it's just firing
like a million times and the video can't
really keep up. But when I move my cursor
anywhere, it just catches up. Now, that's
not really all that great,
because I want to be clicking down. What
did we do in the canvas example?
We created a flag variable, set it to
"false", and then when you clicked we set
it to "true". So this is what we do. We
say "let mouse down = false".
Is the person currently clicking, or has
their mouse down? No.
That is false. Then, when someone mouses
down, we'll set it to "true".
We'll say
"progress.addEventListener('mousedown',"
and when that happens we will run
"mousedown = true". Then, when someone
mouses up, we will make the mouse down
equal to "false". Then,
the scrub, when someone moves their mouse,
what we want to do essentially is we would
run a function here that says "if mouse
down, then we want to scrub".
Right? However, we can do it a little bit
easier, and I'll show you a little trick
here. We'll run a function just in line
here, and we'll say "mousedown &amp;&amp; scrub",
and we'll pass it the event. So we need to
pass the event here.
Now, whoa. Hold on. What did we just do
here? When someone moves their mouse,
we say "mousedown &amp;&amp; scrub", and what this
does is it first checks this variable.
If this variable is "true", it moves on to
this. If this variable is "false",
it's just going to return "false" and it's
not going to do anything.
So we're sort of hijacking the fact that
we can use "&amp;&amp;" and if this is "true" it
will move on to running the scrub. If this
is "false", it's not going to run the
scrub. Then, because our "scrub" function
requires the initial event of when this
happened on mouse move, we need to pass it
in this error function,
and then just sort of like hot potato it
over to our "scrub" function here.
So now, if we play it and see I'm moving
my cursor over top no problem,
but if I click and drag you'll see it is
updating all that time.
Looking good. Awesome. So that is the very
basics of a video player.
It's not really all that basic. We've got
a lot here. The one thing that we did not
do, and this is my challenge to you, is
try to figure out how to make the
Fullscreen button work. So add another
button here, and they should nicely work
out. I've used flex box here, so if you
add another button it'll just shift on
over. When you click that button, make the
video go fullscreen.
Thanks a lot.
See you tomorrow.
♪ [music] ♪