♪ [music] ♪
Edited at https://subtitletools.com
Today we're going to learn
about key sequencing detection,
and that means when someone
inputs a certain sequence of keys
into your window or into an inputter,
something like that, then something needs
to happen. And what this is used
most for online is the Konami code
which is, if you grew up in the 1980s or
1990s, you'll know that you can type in
up, up, down, down, left, right, left,
right, B, A, start, and what that will do
is it will trigger like unlimited lives
in Mario or something like that.
So, I figured out Buzzfeed, of all
websites, has a Konami code.
If you go to the website and press
up, up, down, down, left, right,
left, right, B, A, enter, and it changes
all the words to Wilkie,
I'm not sure who that is, but it's pretty
funny. Different websites have little
Easter eggs that you can
surface. So, let's see how
that works. We'll go into our
scriptag, and we will listen for the
window.addEventListener. You're going to
listen for the keyup event,
and when that happens we are going to run
a function here, which we are going to go
into console.log(e.key), and that's going
to tell us the name of the key that they
have pressed. So if I press up,
it's arrow up, a down, arrow down,
A, S, D, F, you get the point right here.
So, now what we need to do is whenever
someone presses one of these items,
we're going to push it into an array. So,
we're going to first make a pressed array,
and then we also need to look,
what is it that we're looking for.
So, in this case, secret code... In our
case I'm just going to look for the word
"wesbos." Now we go into here,
and we'll say pressed.push(e.key),
[inaudible 01:47] console.log(pressed).
All right, see what's happening whenever I
type something? We get the specific key,
whatever is pressed, into that array. Now,
that's great, and it makes sense,
but that could get fairly big, and
that is essentially a key logger,
where you're logging everything the person
has logged. So what we want to do is just
trim this array to be the maximum that
we would ever need. And in our case,
if we're just looking for the word
"wesbos," then we are maximum looking
for six characters. So, just going to
splice that real quickly, we're going to
say, "pressed.splice." Now we want
to start from counting from the back,
because if I... Let me refresh this. If I
say "wesbos..." I guess I got to type it
up here. "Wesbos is cool." If I want
to...say I'm looking for "is cool." What
we want to do is we want to start
from the end and go forward.
We don't want to start from the start and
go in, so, the way that we do that is we
use a -secretCode.length - 1,
and if I'm looking for six letters,
that's going to go from the back, up seven
letters, and then we're going to trim from
there, which is going to be the
pressed.length, which is the length of the
array minus the secretCode.length, and
that will give us the exact number that we
need. So, now if I refresh, and we say,
"Wes is cool," you see as I start to get
over that budget of six letters, it starts
to push out the first ones that were
pushed. So I could keep typing, "Wesbos."
At that point it says "Wesbos," but if I
type, "i," the "w" gets
pushed out into the array.
Now all that's left is we need to check if
this array contains the secret code that
we are looking for. So we say if
pressed.join, because that we want to
turn it into a string really quickly,
and I'll show you what that does.
That will make it into a string, so,
if pressed.join, which is the string,
.includes(secretCode), then we can do
things like console.log('DING DING!').
You did it.
W-E-S-B-O-S, and there we go, ding, ding,
it includes what we're looking for,
and at that point we can do some fun
stuff. So, way back there was this thing
called cornify.js, and I'll show you what
it does. There is a function called
cornify_add, and when you run it,
"wesbos," it adds unicorns or rainbows or
random stuff to the screen. So if I do
it again, it's going to add another one,
another one, another one, another
one...you get the point, right?
We're just adding hilarious different
unicorns at random. And all you have to
do is call this cornify_add, so that's
it. That's the basics of getting up a
key sequencing detection, store them in an
array, and then check every single time
that they key up if it matches
what you're looking for.
♪ [music] ♪