Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
Today we are going to learn how
to build a slide in on scroll,
when you slide down the images,
the images will sort of slide
themselves in from the left or from the
right, and you can do whatever other
animations you like to do. I've actually
got this request from a lot of people over
the years and I'm always hesitant to do it
because I really don't like the effect all
that much. I think it's kind of
annoying to have to wait for it.
Use this with your discretion. However,
that said, I think that you can learn a
lot about window events, and then we're
also going to talk about debouncing,
which is going to make sure that this is
not just hammering on scroll.
Let's go down to our script tags here, and
you'll notice that I've already given you
a debounce function here, and we're going
to talk about that in a second.
But imagine it's not there, it's gone.
Okay, now what we want to do is first
thing is we need to do is select all of
the images that we are going to be
listening for, and if I open this up in
the browser here, you'll see that all the
images by default are being hidden. If you
inspect them, you'll see that I've just
translated them off-screen just a little
bit as well as the opacity here.
See, that's really where they are, and
then I've exed them off-screen.
You could really do them all the way
off-screen if you prefer and then I've
scaled them at 95% so it just gets a
little bit of nice little fade-in effect
here. By default they are going to be
hidden, and when they scroll into view or
when they are half-scrolled into view,
what we are going to do is we're going to
apply a class called active, which is
right here, and that is going to bring the
opacity to one and translate the X to zero
putting it where it was and scaling it
back up from 95% to 1 or 100%. We need to
select all the images that we're going to
be working with here, so we will say,
const slider images equals
document.queryselector all and we're going
to select every single image that we want
to slide in and they all have a class of
slide-in. Good. Now what we want to do is
create a function called check-slide
that will run every time the person
scrolls. So function, check-slide, and
let's just pass ourselves the event and
console log the event and then when the
window is scrolled, we are going to run
the function check-slide. Let's take a
look at what we got here.
Open up you devTools, watch this.
Whoa, look at this, I just logged like,
hundreds and hundreds of events when I've
gone. And this can be a little bit of a
performance issue because the amount of
times that it's actually running,
here, let's do console.count. How many
times are we going to count this event
here? I scrolled from top to bottom
and it logged it 50 times in like,
a second. Another 50 times. If I just like
flick my finger, we're gonna run that
function 50 times, and that is too much.
What we want to do is debounce it,
which essentially means that we will only
run this function at most,
however many seconds. What we've done here
is we have this debounce function and
there is a debounce in Lodash, there's
functions all over the place.
However, this is a framework-free
tutorial, so I've just grabbed a debounce
function off the internet here.
Essentially what you do is you pass at a
function and it will run debounce
all the time when we scroll,
but it will actually only run the function
check-slide once every 20 milliseconds or
once every 100 milliseconds, which is
going to give you a little bit more
control and it's not going to give you
that hurt in performance.
We're going to wrap that in debounce
here, and now when I scroll,
look, it's scrolling from top to bottom
it's only running 7 times versus 50 times
when I want to scroll up and down. Of
course, you can change that wait from 20
seconds or 20 milliseconds if you wanted
to do only it once every half a second,
you wanted to check for something like
this. You see it's very seldomly being
called. That's what debouncing is. Anytime
you're doing something on scroll,
you'll probably want to stop and you might
think like, "Oh, it's fine." But later
down the road you might have animation
jank and a whole bunch of other stuff
that's happening, so make sure that
you debounce your scroll functions.
Good, now we're going to do all of our
work inside of this check-slide here,
and we're going to talk about what's going
on here. The first thing that we need to
do is loop over every single image and
figure out where the image needs to then
be shown. The idea here is that once the
image is, I like to call this peaking.
Because like at this point, the image is
fully shown. At this point the image is
fully hidden, but at about this point the
image is just peaking out about 50%.
That's the point where when the image
should be on the page at least 50% of its
height, then we want to animate that on
in. We're going to take our slider images,
we're going to loop over each one with a
for each, that's going to give us a slider
image. And for each of those, we're going
to have to do a whole bunch of math to
decide whether it's on page or not. We're
going to say const slidein at equals.
Now, we need to get a couple of things
here. We need to figure out how far is the
page being scrolled down, and that's with
something called window.scrollY.
If I were to go here and just console log
window.scrollY, and open this sucker up,
if I just scroll a little bit,
window.scrollY. If I just scroll a little
bit at this point, you see like I'm 67
pixels scrolled down. I'm 100 pixels
scrolled down. I'm 151 pixels scrolled
down. That will tell us how much you are
scrolled down, but that tells us how much
we are scrolled down at the very top of
our browser. We want to know where
we are at the very bottom of our window,
the viewport that we have here. What we
can do is we take window.scrollY and then
we add the window.innerheight and that's
going to give us the pixel level for where
you currently are at the bottom of that.
And if we console log slidein at,
you'll now see 600, see even at the top of
the page, I'm at 663 pixels and then as I
scroll down, it's going to be telling me
how far down we are scrolled.
Good, but we need to figure out, we don't
want to slidein just at the bottom right
here, we want to slidein at halfway
through the image here. We're going to
minus the slider image which is each
individual image. The height of that,
and that will allow us to slide in the
image at the very bottom but we want to
slide it in when it's at the middle.
If we take that and divide it by two,
that will give us the pixel level of when
each of the images should be slid in at.
Let's take a look here. Now you see each
of the images are being a little bit
different because it's going to
be giving you that information.
The reason why we recalculate this every
single time is because if something
changes on the page, like, if you were to
put like a share this button and it bumped
your content down, or someone
in order to resize their window,
then we would need to recalculate
where the images lie on the page.
Okay, good. Now we need to figure out
where's the bottom of the image because we
also want to know if we scrolled past the
image, it should slide itself back out
because we don't just want to scroll from
the top down. Sometimes if you scroll back
up, you want to have that same animation.
Say, const image bottom equals slider
image, that's the each individual image
.offsettop. OffsetTop is going to tell us
take this image, it's going to tell us the
top of this image is how far from the top
of the actual window here. It's going to
give us a pixel level of how far down it
actually is. Then we want to know not
where the top of the image is,
we want to know where's the bottom of the
image. We just have to add the
sliderimage.height. That'll give
us the actual height of the image.
Okay, good. We have the slidein at,
which is halfway through the image.
Maybe we should write some comments here.
Halfway through the image,
and this is the bottom of the image. Now,
we need to figure out first,
is the image half shown? And second,
if we're not scrolled past it.
Let's do the first one here. Const is half
shown, these are going to go into an
if statement, but I always like to put my
variables that make sense for me to read
them, rather than just to stick
everything in an if statement,
come back a week later not sure what's
going on. Is half shown is equal to
slidein at is greater than the
sliderimage.offsettop and that will make
sure that our slidein at value is greater
than the top of where the actual image is,
so that's good. Then we will make
a is not scrolled past variable,
I realize that's a really long variable,
but it will help you in a second when we
do our if statements. Say window.scrollY
is less than image bottom.
We want to make sure that we are not
scrolled all the way past the image
because if we are, then we need to slide
it out again. And that's what this
variable is going to check, if that image,
if we're not scrolled past it.
Then finally, we have our if statement,
and that'll say if is half shown,
and is not scrolled past, so if it is half
shown on the page, and we are not scrolled
past it, then we are going to take that
image and we are going to grab the class
list and we are going to add active, else,
we are going to simply just remove that.
Because that means we have either scrolled
past it or have not got to it yet.
I've got a bit of red going on on my
editor it's telling me that that variable
has not been created because it is slider
image, there we go. Make sure you fix that
one as well. Looks like we're in good
shape. Now, if you're having trouble
understanding what these positions are, I
understand that scroll and position on the
page can be a little bit hard, just go
ahead and console log these values to
understand where they are. It sometimes
takes a little bit to get what's going on
here. But if this has worked, we should be
able to add a class of active to each of
our items here. Here we go. Oh, we got an
error, go to our console cannot read
property remove of undefined
classlist.remove. Class list. I'm sure
you're screaming at me, there we go. Now,
you can see as soon as we hit that halfway
point for the image, let's scroll all the
way out here, about to hit halfway,
and there we go, the image will add a
class of active and then as you go away,
as soon as you hit this value right here,
you can't see it, but as soon as it goes
off-screen, it's going to move itself on
out, and when we scroll back to it it will
show it again. Same with these ones
and this one as we scroll on down.
That's really it, there's not a whole lot
of code. It is a bit to understand all of
these scrollX and scrollY, especially if
you don't really like doing a bunch of
math at the same time. But again, what I
like to do is stick them into their own
variables before you do your if statement,
and console log these variables to
understand exactly what is going on.
Hopefully you enjoyed that,
and I will see you tomorrow.
♪ [music] ♪