Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
Today we are going to talk all
about Javascript reference versus copy.
And I found this to be a sticking point
and while it's not necessarily going to be
something that you're going to build
that's going to be sweet and your clients
are going to see it, but this is something
that is fundamental to understanding how
Javascript works. And more often than not,
this is a source of a lot of bugs because
people don't understand what the
difference between a reference and a copy
is especially when you get into
nested data. So let's take a look at some
strings, numbers, and booleans right here.
If I have a variable or let's use let
here, and age is set to 100 and then I
make another variable called age 2 and set
that to age, if I console log age and
age 2, what are we going to get?
100 and 100, right? Well, what
happens if age is equal to 200?
And then I also console log age and
age 2, what are we going to get?
Are we going to get 200, 200 or 200, 100?
Okay good. No we get 200, 100.
Why? Because the value of age goes
into the variable at the same time.
That works the same way with strings.
If I do const name or let,
I'm going to be reassigning these so I
need to use let Wes and let name two is
equal to pool. No let name two is equal to
name. Console log name and name two.
You probably will see Wes Wes
but if name is equal to Wesley,
and we also console log that, what
are we going to get? Wesley Wes.
Okay good. So the value of strings,
numbers, and booleans go into it and if
you change the original one, it's okay.
It's not going to update the other one.
Makes sense.
Now let's actually work with an array.
Let's say we've got some data here and we
want to make a copy of the array so we
say, const team equals players.
And that should make sense.
Console log players and team, just to
make sure we got both of them here,
okay good. That's the same array here. So
you might think that we could do something
like this where we changed team three
is equal to locks. Now if I look at team,
you'll see locks is the last one but if I
look at the original one which is players,
which should the last one be? Should it
poppy as it was, or is it going to be
updated to locks? It's locks again.
So what happened there?
Because we updated team but team is not
the array. Team is just a reference to the
original array which is players. So when
you edit that original array or when you
update any of the arrays, it's always
going to go back to the reference where it
was which is not the same as what
we did here with numbers, strings,
and booleans. So that's interesting.
If you update an array,
it will always reference back.
And that is what I find people do is
say, "I just want to make a copy of the
array and update it." So what we then need
to do is make a copy rather than a actual
reference. And there's a couple of ways
that you can make a copy of an array. Say
const team two equals and you can take the
players and just call slice against it.
And if you call slice, players.slice
that's just going to return the
entire array because generally
what slice does is you ask for two
and three and that will give you one
of them whereas the original array is
untouched, right? But what slice will do
if you pass at nothing is it will take a
copy of the actual array here.
Let me just comment out this changing
up here. So let's take a look.
We got players, and we have team two,
and if I were to change team two to
locks, team two has locks in it but
players still has poppy because we made a
copy of it with our array. Another way you
can see people do it is if we make a team
three, you take a blank array and you can
concatenate in the existing array and that
will just concatenate all of the
items from that player's array into the
emptier right here. That will work the
exact same way. And then finally
we can do is the ES6 spread way
which looks like this, const team
three or four equals, you create a
new array, and you spread into that
array with the players. And what a spread
will do is it will take every item out of
your iterable and put it into, in this
case it's the containing array although we
have also used spread to spread into a
function as well. So that will take
a copy of it just as well. Team four,
the last one equal to E and console
log team four. The last one but if I go
back to my player's array, it's untouched
Then finally you could say const
team five is equal to array.from and then
you pass it, your player's array. And if
we were to look at team five,
that's our array, and we were
to change one of them,
then player's array untouched whereas
team five has been updated.
So a whole bunch of different ways.
Array.from and the spread is probably my
favorite way but any of these ways will
work just fine. Now, the same thing
happens for objects as well. If I have a
person object here and I want to make a
copy of it, you cannot do this const
captain equals person because
if you change the captain's number to 99,
so person is now 99 even though person
should be 80, we just update the number to
99, we made a reference to the original
one. So how do you take a copy instead,
that is with something called
object.assigns. Object.assign, the way
that it works, is you start with a blank
object. You pass it the object
you wish to copy all the properties from
which is person, and then you sort of fold
in your new properties that you wish to
overwrite which is number is going to be
99. And then you stick that entire thing
in your own const cap two equals,
stick it into its own variable.
Now when you console log cap two, you'll
see we have... I've got to comment these
ones out here, 99. However if I go back
to person, the number has not been
added to that one at all. So if we just
added them in...same goes if I wanted to
have a number of 99 in age of 12. The
captain is now 12 but the person is 80.
So what happened there is we'd take a
blank object, we overwrite or we sort of
fold in all of the properties and values
from our object, and then we use the third
argument to fold in our own ones.
We are going to be getting or
hopefully, it's not confirmed yet, but we
will be getting a cap three which is
called an object spread. And you may be
used to this if you've ever done any react
before and it's dot dot dot person. And
that works exactly the same way as we
spread into an array but you can spread
into an object. Now one thing that we do
need to know is this is very shallow,
meaning that it will only ever go one
level deep. So if we create
a new object here, const
Wes equals name is Wes, age is 100,
and maybe it will say social and Twitter
is equal to @wesbos, Facebook is equal to
Wesbos...okay good then I've got this
object here, Wes. Pop a quick
console.clear above it so it
will clear out whatever is in here.
Obviously this is not going to work dot
dot dot why? Because object's spread is
not in Javascript yet so we have to
comment that out. There we go. So we've
got this object here. That's the person.
You open up social and we have the object
there. Now if I want to make a copy of
Wes, we would say const div equals object
dot assign. We take a blank object and you
pass in Wes we have here.
Good. So now I have div, that's good,
div.name equals Wesley. Now Wes is still
Wes and dev is Wesley.
So you see how we took a copy of that
object and when we update it,
it's not going to update the original one
so it's not a reference.
However what if we do this,
div.social.twitter is equal to
@poolman. Now div.social, the
Twitter is there but what if I look at
Wes.social now? Shit. Look what happen.
Because when you use object.assign,
it only does one level deep. If you need
to do a clone, you have to get out a
function and go online and find it where
it's called clone deep and that will clone
every level as deep as you want. Although
before you do that, you should
ask yourself, "Do I really actually need
to do this? Maybe I could be doing it in a
better spot because very rarely do you
actually need to clone an object that
deep." So we have that.
And then another sort of cheating way,
the poor man's deep clone, and I'm not
recommending this but you could say const
div two equals Jason.parse,
Jason.stringify then you pass it your
person. Now we have div two and
then we say divtwo.social.twitter equals
@poolman. And now if we look at
Wes.social, it has not been touched.
Why? Because what you can do is you can
take Jason.stringify and pass it an
object, and that will return to you a
string. That's no longer an object.
And then you immediately Jason.parse it to
turn it back into an object,
and then you get a full copy of
it rather than and you shake all the
references. I have no idea about
performance with that. You might want to
look it up before you use it but that's
often referred to as the poor man's deep
clone. Other than that, hopefully you
learned a thing or two about object
references and array references versus
actually copying them. See you tomorrow.
♪ [music] ♪