Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
Hello. Hello. Hello. Today, we are going
to be learning about two main things.
First, we're going to be learning about
local storage and, second,
we're going to be learning about something
called "event delegation".
So what we've got here is sort of a
[tapas] menu, where you can add things,
and then if you want them you can check
and uncheck them. But kind of the cool
thing, where if you were to type in like
"taco", I'm going to say "pork taco",
hit Enter, and then when I refresh the
page it's still there. If I click on one
of them to taco it or check it, as normal
people would do, you refresh,
it's still going to be there. So that's
going to be persisting our state with
local storage. Next up, we're also going
to be doing something called "event
delegation", because when I add another
item here, like fish, and I click on it,
I can taco it right away. Why can I do
that? Because if you add an event listener
on something that doesn't exist, you'll
know that in the future it won't be
clicked. So we're going to look at that
error as well, and use event delegation to
fix it. So I've gone ahead and just
selected the Add Items, which in our case
is this form element right here. So when
someone submits that form,
we're going to add an item. Then, I have
also selected this UL with a class of
"plates" here. That's where we're going to
load all of our tapas dishes into.
Then, finally, we're going to be storing
all of our data in an array.
It's going to be an array of objects,
which has the name of the array,
as well as the status whether it's tacoed
or done, or whatever it is that we are
here. So we're going to go ahead and grab
that form element, which is Add Items,
and we're going to listen for the submit
event. Why do we listen for the submit
event here? Because that's what we
actually need. A lot of times people,
they listen for a click on this button.
But you want to listen for a submit,
when someone hits Enter, when someone
clicks a button, when some external thing
submits it. We need to make sure that we
are covering all our bases,
and by listening to the submit event, we
cover all of our bases with that.
So we're going to run a function called
"addItem" when somebody submits it,
and we're going to create that function
here. It's going to give us the event,
and let's just console.log, "Hello". I'm
going to open mine up here,
and I'm going to go to the console here.
Now, when I type in something like "fish,"
you see that, oh, "Hello" is quickly
flashed there. Let me do it again.
Oh, if you click on this button here,
Preserve Log, you can see what's happening
here. I'm going to hit Enter, and then
automatically we log "Hello",
and then we see "Navigated to" and this is
the URLs of where I'm working here.
So what's happening is our page is
actually refreshing, and we don't want
that. So what we can do is we can say
e.preventDefault, and that's going to stop
the page from reloading. Because by
default, a form is just going to reload
the page or send the data to an external
source, generally what's your server side.
In this case, we're going to be doing an
all client side, so prevent the default of
that happening. Now when I type in
something and submit that, we don't get
anything. Why is that? Because nothing is
happening. If I were to console.log
"hello," once more, I'm going to say
"hello," we see "hello" in the thing but
the page does not reload. Okay. Now that
we have that, what we need to do is to
take that text of this box and put it into
an object. So first of all,
we are going to make an item and that item
is going to have two.
It's going to have text of item name, and
we'll replace that in a second.
It's going to have a done state of
"false". So by default, it's not going to
be checked or tacoed. Now, how do we get
this text here? Well,
we can do this, "const text =" and we're
going to first grab this input box,
which has a name of item on it. So we
could say "document.querySelector"
but we can also do "this.querySelector."
Why can we do that? "Name=item"
why can we do that? That's because this is
going to be the actual form.
That's the whole form tag, and then we'll
look inside of that form tag for something
that has a name attribute of "Item".
That's really helpful if you have multiple
forms on a page. You don't just want to be
globally selecting it.
You want to narrow down your search inside
of the one form that we're working with.
So we've got that text. If we were just to
wrap that whole thing in parentheses,
it's going to execute first and we can
call ".value" against it.
Because that's going to give us the input,
and then input has a property called
"value," which is whatever the user has
typed into it. Then, we can go here.
Type "text." Or if you've watched my ES6
videos, then you know instead of saying
"text: text," we can use the ES6 shorthand
property, which is just "text".
So we just created this object here. Let's
console.log the item.
Let's go over to our console. Let's type
in something like "fish."
Now, when I run that, you should now
see an object in your console that has a
done of "false" and a text of whatever the
user has put in there.
If you run it a couple times, you're going
to get it console logged.
One thing we want to do is clear that
input. What we can do is we can say
"this.reset." Because "this" is the form
element, and form elements have a method
called "reset" on it. You've probably run
into this where you've spent an hour
filling out a form online somewhere, and
you accidentally click the Reset button
instead of the Submit button. That's what
it's hooked up to is the ".reset."
So let's see where we're at now. "Fish,"
there we go. It refreshes it,
it clears that, and we create this object.
We're not seeing it,
because we're not console logging it. Now,
what we want to do is take that item here
and put that into this item's array. So
what we do is we just say
"items.push(item)." Now, let's take a fish
and we will say "squid."
Now, if we look at our item's array, you
see that we have "Object" with two things
in it. We can go one step further and
console.table the item's array,
and you see that we have "Fish" and
"Squid". Now, that's all we've done to get
our data in it. It's not going to persist
when we refresh just yet.
We'll do that in just a second. But at
this point, we need to create a second
function that we're going to call
"populateList," and that's going to create
the actual HTML here. So we're going to
say "function populateList".
That populateList function needs two
things. First of all, it needs a list of
plates to populate. We've stored that
where? We've stored that in our item's
array. Let me show you once more. If I
type "fish" and look at our item's array,
you see that we have an array of things,
which has a text of "fish" and done.
So we need to pass in what that's going to
be called, and you can call that "Items"
if you prefer to name the variable the
same thing. But let's call that "plates"
and we're going to set that to be a
default of an empty object.
The reason why I do that is because if for
some reason you forget to pass in
something, it's not going to break your
JavaScript. It's just going to loop over
an array of nothing, and then your map
function will work just fine.
Then, second of all, we need a place to
put the HTML and that's called the "plates
list." We are going to pass in our items
list. So why am I doing that?
Why am I not just like reaching outside
and grabbing the list of items and
grabbing the place where we will dump
them? That's because I want this
populateList function to be a little bit
more resilient. Meaning that I could pass
in any array of plates and any destination
HTML element, and it will work.
So if in the future I decided to have two
different lists or two different menus,
that would be fine. I could still use a
single populateList function and just pass
it a different array of items and a
different HTML element to dump it.
So we go inside of here and we take this
plate's array here, and we are going to
map over it. So we hit Map. We take our
item, or let's call it "plate,"
singular, and then we have the index and
I'll show you why we need that in just a
second. Now, from here this is going to
return some HTML. So we're going to use
back text. The last thing we need to do
is, in front of this plates.map,
we need to stick this either in a variable
or directly into the HTML.
So I'm going to say "plateslist[removed]
=" and I'll show you what this does in
just a second. So we're going to loop over
every single item in our array,
and that's just an object and we're going
to map. Which again,
a map will take in an array of raw data
and return an array of some other data.
In our case, we're going to take in the
objects and return a string from each one.
That's why we're using these back texts
here. So we're going to give ourselves a
list item, and then let's just take a
label and let's forget about all of the
stuff. Let's just get it working. We'll
put "plate.text" inside of it.
Then, the last thing we need to do is call
a ".join" on here. Because map is going to
return an array, when really if we're
setting inner HTML, we just need one big
string. So this little ".join" on the end
is going to take this array that map makes
and turn it into one big string. So if we
have six or seven items,
it's not going to give us an array with
six strings. It's going to give us one
huge string. So now, if we take this
populateList, you go back up here right
before we run it, and we run populateList.
We are going to pass it our list of items
and our itemsList. Let's try it out. So if
I type "fish", aha,
"fish" and "squid," and "tacos," and you
see what's happening here is that every
time we add an item, we are calling this
populateList function,
which is then going to create a list item
with a label inside of it.
You can inspect this and see what we've
got going on here. It's going to create a
list item. One thing that I should say is
this populateList function,
every time we add an item, it's recreating
the entire list. So if you are really
worried about performance, in this case
it's not a big deal. It's very,
very fast. But if you were doing this
maybe every half a second or every second,
or you had a bunch of animations, you
would want to look at, "How do I update
just that one list item that I have,
rather than rerender the entire list?"
That's where something like React or
Angular becomes really helpful,
because they're smart enough to know,
"Okay. Rather than just blowing away this
entire unordered list and rerendering the
whole thing, let me just figure out what's
the minimum HTML that I need to change on
the page without having to change the rest
of it. So we've got this label here, and
above it I'm going to have an input with
the type of checkbox. We need a
"data-index," and I'll show you why that's
helpful in just a few minutes. We're going
to set that to the index that we have
here. We're going to have an ID, which is
going to be Item I, because that's going
to be Item 1, Item 2, Item 3, Item 4.
Here, we need to go back to our label and
hook that ID up. So we'll say "Item I",
and that's how when you click on the label
the input will check itself. That's how we
link the two. The ID and the "for" are
exactly the same thing. Then, finally, we
need to know whether or not these items
are going to be checked or not. Because
when I rerender it, if it's already
checked, if it has a Done status, we need
to put the "checked" attribute.
So if I were to say "checked," then all of
them would automatically be checked.
So if I add "fish," see that has a
"checked" state? But we have to look at
the items in there, and the first one has
a property of "done".
So if it has a property of "done," put the
"checked" attribute.
Otherwise, we leave it off. Because you
might know that you cannot say
"checked=false." That will still make
it... Watch. If I say "checked=false" and
I type in "fish," it still checks it. If I
say "checked=emoji poop,"
it's still checked. That's because
anything, any existence of the property
checked or the attribute checked will make
it check. So we need to create a turnery
operator here, where we say if the
"plate.done" attribute is true,
then we're going to put the checked.
Otherwise, we're just going to do nothing.
It's just an empty string. Sometimes I
thought to put "null" here.
But the word "null" will actually show up
in your HTML. So you need two blank
strings. Let's see if anything is broken.
Good. "Fish" is working.
Then, when I click it, it will check the
taco on and off. If you're wondering how I
did this custom thing here, if you take a
look at the input box,
you'll see that I've displayed "none;". If
I take that off, the input box is actually
still there. I've just hidden it with CSS.
If we open up our CSS here,
let's look for the tacos, here we go, what
we say is the plate input,
the label before it, has a blank sort of
emoji that's just a square,
but then when the input is checked, turn
that content from a blank square into a
taco. So you could really put anything you
wanted here, and it will turn it on and
off. It's sort of a little trick that you
can do to make it work.
I think it looks a little bit better, and
that's a way that you can still have your
proper checkbox for data. But you can
display them with whatever HTML or CSS
that you want. So we've got that up and
running. Every time I add a new item it
will add it to the list, and I can check
it and uncheck it. The other problem here
is that when I refresh the page, that list
is not persisting. So what we're going to
do is we're going to be storing our data
in local storage. Now,
if you've never worked with local storage
before, essentially how it works is that
you have this object in the browser called
"Local Storage." If you open that up,
this is just a list of things that have
been saved to this domain.
So this is only a computer by computer,
browser by browser, website by website
basis. But you're able to save text to the
browser, and then when you reload the page
you'll be able to grab this text out of
it. So if you go to your Application tab
in Chrome Dev Tools, there's a whole bunch
of stuff here. If you go to Local Storage
and you click on the domain that you're
working on, in this case I'm working
locally so it's just "file," you should
see that there's a key of Items and a
value of something else. Now, you might
see a whole bunch of other stuff here,
depending if you've ever run other
applications on your local host.
This is where I've stored the text of what
we're going for and the property of done
to "false" or "true," etc., etc. So how
do we actually save that to local storage
or done? Well, it's actually pretty easy.
When we populate the list here,
what we also need to do is set this item's
array into local storage.
So you think you might be able to do this,
localStorage. , and then the API is
.setItem, .getItem, and .removeItem or
deleteItem. I'll double check that.
So localStorage.setItem, and then we're
going to set the item,
"Items." That's the key right here, what
it's going to be called.
Then, what are you going to set the data
to? Well, you might just think,
"Okay. I'll just pass items, because
that's my items array." "Fish."
Okay. So we just ran it. We gathered the
item, we populated to the list,
and then we called
"localStorage.setItems." We go to our
local storage here, and you see this,
"object Object." What does that mean?
Well, what's happening here is that local
storage, although it seems like it's an
object, it's simply just a key value store
and you may only use strings in local
storage. So if we were to take our items
here and call ".toString" on it,
you see "object Object". What's happening
is that when you try to put something
other than a string into local storage,
the browser goes, "Oh,
I don't know how to handle this. Let me
just convert it to a string,
and let me just use the .toString method
that exists on the number or the object,
or the array." In our case, it's an array.
What returns is the browser goes,
"object Object" and that's its
representation. So we can't really do
that, because there's not actually an
object here. It's just the word "object
Object". So what we actually need to do is
stringify it before we convert it.
So in the browser, we have this thing
called "JSON.stringify" and when you pass
it your items, it's going to convert your
objects and arrays into a JSON string
equivalent. So we just need to wrap this
sucker. You send out "parse(items),"
and now when you add an item in here,
"fish," oh, "Unexpected token o at JSON."
What is our problem? Oh, we're not parsed.
JSON.stringify. Parsed is going to be the
other way. "Fish" and "tacos," and "yum,"
and now when you go to your Application
tab here, you see that this is now being
stored. It looks like an array of objects,
but it really is just text. I can show you
that, because we can say
"localStorage.getItem('items')." That is
just a string. However,
what you can do is you can wrap that thing
in the JSON.parse and that's going to then
take it from the string and put it back
into whatever it was initially.
In this case, it's going to be an array of
actual objects. So that's what we need to
do on page load. We go down here and when
the page loads, the very last thing,
we'll say "populateList" and we can say
"items." But again, you don't know.
Do we have to do JSON.parse? No, not here.
We are going to say "items" and
"itemsList." But the "items" doesn't exist
on page load. Remember,
the first thing we do up here is we create
an empty object? So what we can do is we
can say "items =
JSON.parse(localStorage.getItem('items'))
or a blank array. What that will do is
it's going to try and get it from local
storage, and then if it isn't there it's
going to fall back to an empty array.
Then, on page load, before we do any of
this stuff, our Items is going to be
populated, and then when we reach here we
can call our "populateList" just as we did
right here. So if we refresh the page now,
oh-ho, you see that our "fish,"
"tacos," and "yum" is now persisting. I
can refresh all that I want,
and the data is always going to be there.
So a real quick review of what we just did
there. When we add an item, you put it
into local storage and you update your
local storage every single time. Then, on
page load, what's going to happen is that
we check if there is something in local
storage, and then we fall back to an empty
array. Now, I just want to make sure that
that still works with nothing.
So we can go to our application, File,
click on this thing, and exit.
Then, when we refresh the page, you see
that there is nothing there.
So if I type in "items", you see that it's
fallen back to this square bracket,
which is a blank array. Okay. Good. Good.
Good. We are in good shape.
Next, what we need to do is persist the
toggling of it. Because if you add in
"fish" and "tacos," and "yum," and you
check one and refresh the page,
that state is no longer handled. So what
we need to do is create a new function
called "toggleDone," and then we're going
to pass the event there.
Now, when will this function run? Let's go
down here. You think that you would select
each of the checkboxes right here, and
then listen for either a change or a click
event on those checkboxes. Then, when that
happens you will go ahead and perform
something. Now, let me show you a real
quick example. If I say "const checkBoxes
= document.querySelectorAll, and I'm just
going to select every input on the page,
and I'll say checkBoxes.forEach(input =>
input.addEventListener('click'".
Then, when that runs, I'm just going to
run a quick function here,
that will alert I. Okay. What I did there,
when I click on a checkbox,
we should alert "hi." So click it, and
when I click one of them,
we showed alert "hi," but it's not
working. Hmm, what's going on here?
Well, if we look at our checkboxes array,
there's two things in there and it's this
thing. Okay. So when I click on that, that
works. When we click on Add Item,
that works. So where are these three
inputs? Why are they not showing up in my
note list? The problem that we've run into
here is that when this code runs,
when our event listener runs, when our
selector runs, this doesn't exist yet.
Why? Because we need to populate the list
first. So you might think,
"Okay. That's fine. Let's populate the
list first and let's take a look at our
checkboxes array." Okay. Look at it.
There's more. There they are.
Okay. Are we out? Now, if I click on one
of these, okay, now it's working.
But what happens if I add an additional
item like here? "Hello."
It adds it. Okay, good. Now, I'm going to
click on this checkbox.
It doesn't work. Does "yum" still work?
No. None of these work now.
What's happening is because these inputs
here are created after we listen for them,
they don't have event listeners attached
to them. The whole idea behind event
delegation is rather than listening for a
click or a change on these checkboxes
directly, what we do is we look for
somebody who is going to be on the page at
the time of listening. If we look at our
HTML here, you're going to see that that
unordered list that holds everything, UL
with a class of "plates,"
that does exist. So what we're going to do
is we're going to listen for a click on
the plates, and then we're going to figure
out, "Did they actually mean to click one
of the inputs inside of it?" So I always
like to think of event delegation as very
responsible parents, like UL with a class
of "plates," and very negligent children
who don't necessarily hear any
instructions from the parents. So what
we're saying is, "Hey, plates. When your
children inputs get clicked,
can you please pass this click on to
them?" Rather than you handling the click
directly, we're just telling you because
you're the only one responsible here.
So that when someone clicks it, if it's
for one of your children,
I don't know if they're your current
children or you're going to make more
children in the future, but if you make
more in the future, make sure you tell
them to handle this click. So you've got
to think of like, responsible parent,
negligent child who doesn't necessarily
know what to do with the click.
So the parent has to tell it what to do.
So let's go back to this code here.
We're going to delete these checkboxes
here if you type that. We just want this
populatedList and addItem with that
listener. We are going to listen for the
click on the unordered list, which is this
itemsList right here.
So we'll say, just duplicate this,
"itemsList.addEventListener."
We're going to listen for a click. When
that happens, we're going to "toggleDone."
Then, inside of here, I'm going to
console.log the E. Let's go back to our
console here. Now, let's click on one of
these. Uh-oh. Okay. That's interesting.
We're getting two different mouse event
handlers. Let's click on this one right
here. Whoa. What's going on here? So we're
getting two different event listeners here
when we click on something. What we can do
a little bit further is if we look at the
target of that event, let's see what we're
working with here, click on Tacos,
ah. So what's happening here is that we're
clicking on the item,
and we're also clicking on the checkbox.
Because our click on Label is in turn
checking the checkbox, which will trigger
a click on the actual input.
Okay, good. Then, what else? Like if we
click on something here that isn't
necessarily the list item or the input,
you see the label is there,
if we click like right here in between,
what do we got? We get the LI.
So you see as we click different items,
the target is going to be a little bit
different. What we want to do here is we
want to check if the target matches the
thing that we're looking for. So we'll
say, "If the e.target.matches," this is
the new API in the browser, "input," and
this is sort of like if you've ever worked
with jquery.isaninput, it's the same thing
as .matches, then we want to return.
Which means they skip this unless it's in
input. Then, let's console.log the target.
There we go. Now, wherever we click, we're
only getting input checks.
Good. So now, we have that working. Again,
that's event delegation,
where we listen for a click on something
higher, and then inside of it we check if
it's the actual thing that we want because
it could trigger on a few different
things. Now, what we want to do is we want
to go to our items array,
and we want to find the one that was
checked and set the done to be "true" or
"false," depending on what state it's in.
So we can first get the index,
and this is why I gave each input a
data-index value, because we can then use
that to reference where it is in the
array. So if we say "const el = e.target",
so put it in its own, now that we have
that element, we can console.log,
el.dataset.index. This is why we put a
data-index on each of the checkboxes.
You check one, it's going to tell you the
index of the corresponding item in the
array. Then, from that we'll take that
index, we'll stick it in its own variable
just for simplicity's sake, and then we'll
take our items with the index and we'll
access the done property. We'll set it to
itself, but this is the trick,
the opposite. So if this is true, it's
going to be the opposite,
which is false. If this is false, it's
which is true. So this is just
flip-flopping between true and false.
Then, we're going to do the same thing
that we did with the stringify,
localStorage right here. Take that. Stick
it right in here. Then,
we will run populateList once more, which
will update the actual visibility part on
here. So we're going to change the
property, we're going to store that in
local storage, and we're going to visually
update what's on our page.
Now when we refresh "tacos", and I should
refresh the page now,
"tacos" is always going to be "true". Why?
Because if we go to our application and we
look at our local storage here, you should
see that "tacos" is "true" and done is
"false". If I were to just mainly change
this to "false" and the first one to
"true", then I refresh the page, you'll
see now "fish" is checked and "tacos".
So every time we make a change, we are
going to mirror that to local storage,
and then rerender the entire list. Or even
better, if you can figure out,
"How do I rerender just that one?" that's
even better. So that's it for today's.
What I will now challenge you to do is
make a button right here that says Clear
All or Check All, or Uncheck All. When you
click that Delete button,
it'll delete all of them. When you click
Check All, it will make them all checked.
When you click Uncheck All, it will
uncheck all of them and mirror it to local
storage, as well as rerun this populated
list. Thanks a lot, and I'll see you in
the next one.
♪ [music] ♪