Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
Today we are going to be learning
all about mouse move
and we're going to recreate this.
I've created this on
flexbox.io. It's a website for one of my
other courses and when you move your
cursor over top of the window, the shadow
sort of follows you around...and just to
show you what's going on here, if we
inspect this right here, you see that I'm
just dynamically updating the style of
that h1 tag depending on where your mouse
is on the actual page. Now, you can also
do this on your phone where I've tapped
into the accelerometer and depending on
how far you're tipping your phone will
also follow you around. So it's what we're
going to be building today. This is,
we kind of go crazy at the end here,
moving it up and down, but we're going to
start with just this which has our
emoji "woah!" and you can edit it.
I've put a content editable on there
and we have a hero here.
So, what we're going to do is we're going
to listen for a mouse move event on our
hero, and when that changes, we are going
to figure out how far and where we should
put the text shadow on this woah here. So
we're going to go into our script tag here
and first we'll grab the hero, and we'll
also grab the text inside of that hero
which is our h1 tag. Now what we need to
do is make a function called shadow.
It's going to pass us the event and then
down here, we're going to take our hero
and add an event listener for mouse move.
When the mouse is moved,
we are going to run the shadow. Good.
Maybe we will just console log the event
inside of here, see what we're dealing
with. Go to our console. Good.
Now anytime I mouse over, what we're going
to do is we get all this information about
what happened and in there, like many of
these other videos, we find out that we
have some information about
the offset left. So let's go into
here, and first of all what we need to do
is get the width and the height of the
thing that we have hovered over which is
the hero. So say const and we're going to
use some ES6 destructuring here because...
let's code it without destructuring
first and then we'll rename it. So
width is equal to hero.offset width,
and height is equal to hero.offset
height. If you're a hotshot,
you can do it in one line. So you can
const offset width is going to be equal to
width and offset height is going to be
equal to height and that is equal.
We destructured that right off the
hero element. So these two things,
these two lines are like this, whatever
you prefer to read. You can do that and
then we also need to get the information
about where the person's cursor was.
So we'll say let and I'll tell you why
we're going to do let instead of
const in just a second, offset x is going
to be equal to the variable x.
Offset y is going to be equal to the
variable y, and we're going to be taking
that off of the event. That's the same
thing as having e.offset x and e.offset y.
We want these values right here,
180 and 100. Now let's console.log x
and y. Hey, look at this. Okay, so go, go
to the top corner and you see zeros.
Go to the very bottom right and you see
700 or however big your actual one is.
So that's looking good.
We're seeing information,
but one weird thing is if you hover
right in the top corner of this h1 tag,
you see that these values are close
to zero. Now, what's going on here?
If we put a background on this element
here, and I hover over top the top corner
of the red, it's giving us values like
zero. Look at, it's like 140 right here,
and then zeros right here. Huh, and what's
happening is that the event,
even though we're listening for the mouse
move on the hero, if there are children
elements inside of the hero it's going to
give us the x and the y of the actual
element that we hovered which is kind
of a pain. So we need to do a little bit
of normalization here to say okay, if the
thing that we're actually hovering is this
h1 instead of the hero, then modify the x
and the y values, so that they're going to
be consistent across all of them. So what
we do here is we say if this does not
equal event.target, then...hold on,
what is this? Console log this.
This is going to be a div with a class of
hero. Okay. What is going to be
event.target? The target is going to be
the thing that it actually triggered on,
whereas this is going to be the thing that
you listened on. So it's always going to
be hero for this, but
the target, what it got
triggered on will sometimes change. So
hero, hero, hero. Watch this.
Ah, I'm hovering over here and you see
that I see this is equal to the hero but
the target is equal to the h1. So if those
two things are not the same,
which is what this if statement is doing
right here, then what we'll need to do,
we say x equals x plus event
or e.target.offset left
and the same we'll do with y and
offset top. So essensially what we're
doing is we're figuring out if someone
hovers in the top left hand corner of
woah, this h1, we're going to add the
like two pixels that it's given us plus
whatever it is from the left and whatever
it is from the top. So dealing with x and
y is a bit of a headache in Javascript and
this is the best fix that we can find
to work with that. So now if I console log
x and y and that, by the way that is why I
used let, because it's possible that we
needed to reassign the values here.
Now if I hover over the top left hand
corner you see those values aren't back to
zero. It doesn't change depending on where
we are. Good. Now what we need to do is
figure out how far the text shadow should
actually go. So we need something that I
like to call a walk. If you look at this,
if my cursor is all the way at the top
left, how much over and
back should it go? If it's all
the way over, how much over should that
go, how much all the way down should it
go, and I like to call that the walk. How
many pixels, at its most,
should it be stretched? So let's go up
here, and we'll say const walk equals,
let's make it 100 pixels. Just 100, and
we're going to use that in our math
equation. So now we will say const x walk
equal to...and here is where it gets a
little bit tricky. Because if it was all
the way over, like right here,
it's not going to be 200 pixels, and if
it's all the way over here it's not going
to be zero. If it's all the way
over it's going to be plus 100,
and if it's all the way over here it's
going to be negative 100.
So we say x walk equals x divided by the
width times the walk minus the walk
divided by two.
What? What are we doing here?
So essentially what that is, if 100 is as
high as we'll go, 0 is not as low as we'll
go, if 100 is our walk, then 50 should be
as high as we go and negative 50 is as low
as we should go. So our walk is 100 but we
want to go from 50 to negative 50,
and that's what this little bit of math is
doing for us here. It's sort of offsetting
it so we go to plus 50 and
negative 50 instead of 0
and plus 100. Then we can just swap out
this x walk, y, with this is going to be
height, then we should console log our x
walk and our y walk. See what we got here.
Ah, there we go. So now we've got a bunch
of pixel values, which is giving us...and
those are a little bit long, so we could
pop a quick math.round around them.
There we go. Now it's giving us some
good...if you go all the way to the top
left, you get negative 50, negative 50,
and all the way to the bottom right
you're getting plus 50, plus 50. So now
that's all left to us is we take our text,
and we can grab the style attribute and
set the text shadow to be..and I'm going
to use backtexts here. It's going to
be...and the way that the text-shadow
works is it's, like, 10px, 10px,
blur, which is going to be 0,
and then you want to give itself like red.
Something like that.
However, this 10px is not going to be
10px. It's going to be x walk.
This 10px is going to be y walk and we can
leave this red as we have it here.
So give that a refresh, and woah! It's
working. So give it an inspect.
You see how those values are now being
updated as we move? Negative 50,
negative 50. 50, 50. We're moving it all
around. That's pretty cool and what you
can also do with that is just do multiple
colors as you like. So RGBA
255, 0, 255, 0.7, something like that, and
then comma. We'll do it again,
which x walk times negative one will make
that one negative, and we'll make this
color to be zero. Just going around the
spectrum here. Take off that leading
comma. There we go. So now one of them is
going the opposite way of the way it would
go. So you go left. One of them goes left.
The other goes right.
Do it again with...we want to give that
first one our y walk value and this one
our x walk times negative one, and
finally, figure out y walk times negative
one and our x walk. It changes colors
around so they're not exactly the same.
0, 255, 0, and 0, 0, 255. Take
off that last trailing comma,
and there we go. We see all of them going
every which that way we have,
looking kind of fun. You can do some crazy
stuff by...go up, change your walk value,
where did we set that? Here and if you
change that to 500 and it goes woo!
All over the place. You can set
some blur modes in CSS
so that they change each
other when they overwrite.
There's all sort of fun stuff we can do
there. The real big thing that we learned
there is that when you're dealing with
events, you can use offset x and offset y
to get the position where your cursor is.
However, if you have nested elements
inside of that thing, you sometimes will
need to do a little bit of math to deal
with it. Hopefully, you enjoyed that, and
it wasn't too tough on the old noggin.
I will see you tomorrow.
♪ [music] ♪