♪ [music] ♪
Edited at https://subtitletools.com
Today we're going to be working with
JavaScript's array.sort method,
and we're going to be sorting this array
of band names, but kind of the catch we
have here is that you need to sort them
without "The," "An," or "A" in front of
the actual band name, because those are
articles and they don't go into
alphabetizing your actual
name of your band.
So go ahead and
pause the video. I think that you can do
this on your own, at least give it a good
shot, and try to build this where you sort
this array first, and then once you've
sorted the array without "the," "an," or
"a," then put them into the actual html
here, but notice how "The," "An," or "A"
still come along for the ride, they're
just not affecting the sort order.
So pause the video and come back when
you've given it a good shot.
Welcome back. So here I am, I'm going to
first make a sortedBands variable,
and we'll take the bands and we are going
to sort it. Now, we know that sort will
take a function name that gives us a and
b, and what is a? A is going to be the
first thing that it passes us, the b is
going to be the second.
It's sort of like it gives you two apples
in either hand, and you're like,
"Which one is bigger?" Then the bigger one
you move to the top,
and the other one you move to the bottom.
Or the one that comes earlier in the
alphabet you move to the top, and the
other one you put in the bottom.
Then you toss the bigger one, and you get
another apple in your hand,
and you've got that first apple from the
first bunch, and then the second apple
from the second bunch, and you say "Which
one's bigger?" You just keep doing that
over and over and over again until you
have a sorted list. That's why it always
gives you two things.
So normally what we do is we say "if a is
greater than b," and we can just do this,
even though they're not numbers. It's
still going to work with strings,
because they're alphabetical. So "if a is
bigger than b," then we will return 1,
else we are going to return -1. And let's
just console.log(sortedBands),
see what we've got here. So we've got our
data and it is alphabetizing it,
but it is basing it off of "A" and "The."
So what we need to do is go up here and
create a new function that I like to call
strip, and it's going to take in the
bandName, and then from there we are going
to return the bandName,
but we are going to replace the word
"The," or "A," or "An." So one way that we
could replace all three in one go is to
use a regular expression,
and we can say when it starts with, that's
what the caret is for,
and I'm by no means a regular expression
expert, if you know anything about regex
you can probably find a better way to do
this, but the way that I've done it is you
can say "a," "the," or "an," and you want
to make that insensitive.
So it's going to match "an," or "An," or
"AN," so there we go.
I'm sure there's a flag you can pass so
you don't need that space in there,
where you could say just match a whole
word. What I'm trying to do is make sure
that we don't catch this, where some word
like "Anywhere" starts with "An," but
that's not actually the article, "An." So
we are replacing. Make sure you spell
"replace" right, and we are going to be
replacing that with nothing,
and then we'll just call trim on the end
there just in case we have any spaces
after it. Good.
Then, what we can do...
Let's see if that works, actually.
So if I call that strip function
from the console, say "An old dog," it
returns to you "old dog," "anold dog,"
"arnold dog," it won't do it,
"The old dog" will give you "old dog."
Good. So that function is working.
Now what we can do is we simply just
change our if statement to a strip and
strip, and notice how we are only using
strip in the if statement,
and we're not actually going to be
modifying this data. So the data that we
use to decide where it goes is not
necessarily the data that is going to be
in the array. So we're using strip, now
let's see where we're at.
Good, Anywhere But Here, The Bled,
Counterparts, The Devil Wears Prada,
good. So now it's totally ignoring it. We
can make this a lot easier here,
so first of all what we can do, we could
simply just make it return,
strip (a) > strip (b), if that is true we
return 1, otherwise we return -1,
so we're just using a ternary operator
there. Still works good.
We can make this an arrow function, good,
still works, and now you see my editor's
yelling at me because it's... If the only
thing you're doing in a function is
returning something, you can use the
implicit return. So I'm going to take off
that bracket and the semicolon, take of
this bracket, going to put it on the same
line, and I'm going to remove the return
keyword, and that's doing the exact same
thing, just in one hot line.
There we go, working good. So we have the
bands.sort, and now we will go ahead and
grab our bands, which is here, say
document.querySelector('#bands'.
)innerHTML equals, we'll take our
sortedBands, and we are going to loop over
each of them. So we'll use map, and from
that map we will return the band,
but the band in a list item, and then
we will join it all in one go.
So what does that do, it takes the element
and sets the innerHTML to b,
and we can put this on its own line,
sortedBands, but we want to map over each
of those, and then that's going to return
an array, so we want to join it.
See where we're at...there we go. Anywhere
But Here, The Bled,
we're got everything being dumped into the
DOM there.
Let me show you real quick, if I take that
join off, you'll notice that we get these
commas showing up here, and that's because
what happens is we have this sortedBands
array, which is everything, and if you
were to call .toString on it,
then that's exactly what the DOM will do.
When you try to set something to innerHTML
that is not a string, like an array, then
it will just call .toString on it,
and by default it's going to put a comma
in between each one. So we need to put
that .join on the end so that will join it
into one big string rather than a bunch of
strings with a comma in between.
So let's double check that, working great.
Hopefully you enjoyed that,
I will see you tomorrow.
♪ [music] ♪