Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
Today we're going to be
solving a problem that I actually run into
fairly frequently, and that is I want to
add up the total number of minutes,
and seconds, and hours that is my actual
videos. So what I usually do is I'll
export all my videos and I'll upload them
to Youtube or whatever it is my host and
they'll give me like this time stamp here,
5 minutes and 23 seconds.
And I go, "Uh huh. I need to
add that up all together," right?
And it's just in HTML. So what I've done,
is I've sort of replicated what Youtube
generally gives me. They have like a list
item or a div, or something like that.
And there's going to be some sort of a dom
node that it's either like a span with a
class of time and inside of that it'll say
2 minutes and 34 seconds or usually with
Youtube they have a data-time attribute
that is a string containing the minutes
and the seconds of it.
So what I wanted to do is to figure out
how do I pull these out of the dom,
convert them to numbers, make them into
minutes and seconds, add it all up,
figure out how many hours,
minutes and seconds there are totally,
then finally console.log those actual
values. So we are going to be using reduce
in this one and I'm going to show you
how to first do it with map and reduce,
and then we'll look at how do you just
make it in one single reduce. So
we're going to our script tag here and I'm
just going to open this up. There's not
much to look at for this one.
It's kind of ugly but we're really just
concerned with this data-time attributes
here. So first thing that we want to do is
we want to select all of those nodes.
So we're going to say const time nodes
equals document.queryselectorall.
We're going to be looking at not just a
list item because you don't know if it's
just going to be a list item. We want to
say anything with a data-time attribute on
it. Now let's console log those
time nodes. Okay, we've got a bunch of
list items. Now what I want
to do is I want to turn
this from a node list into an array of
actual time strings. Let's just say
seconds equals timenodes.map and for each
one, we are going to take the node and
we're going to return to the
node.dataset.time. So watch what's going
to air out in here. Timenodes.map is not a
function. So map is not a function of time
nodes. Why is that? I thought it
was an array. Let's see it again.
Time nodes is looks like an array, walks
like an array, but it's not.
It's a nodeless and if you open up the
product type we do not have.
We have it for each which we could use but
it's not as clean. So what we want to do
is convert this sucker from
a nodeless into an array.
And there are two ways. You could spread
it it into a new array or you can run
array.from round the entire thing.
And now when we loop over it,
we should have our seconds variable which
is now going to be an array of all of the
times. Good. So what I did there is I took
the time nodes and I mapped it which means
I made it from an array of list items
and into an array of strings.
Good. Now what I want
to do is turn that into
just seconds, okay? So we're going to
.map it into that and that is going to
give us the time code. And from that we
are going to split it because if we have a
string like this, I want to break that
into minutes and seconds.
Let me show you an example here, right?
Might say something like string.split
and we split it on the colon
and that will give us,
the first thing is going to be the
minutes. The second thing will be the
seconds. So what we can do is we can use
ES6 restructuring there
which they say const, mins, secs is equal
to timecode.split. Then I'll split it on
that. Okay. Let's see where that gets us.
We want the console log,
the min, and the secs. And you see
that we've got a 5, 43, 2, okay.
We're good. We've got them into
their own variables however they are
black, and what that tells me is that they
are strings. And if we want to do any sort
of math because what we are going to be
doing here is we're going to return the
mins plus the minutes times sixty, plus
the seconds. And if we take a look at our
seconds array here, you'll see that these
are way bigger than they should be.
Zero, four, seven. That's not a number.
And that's because when we split
that string off of it, it's still going to
be a string. So if I take something like a
string of six ten and I split it, each of
the six and the ten are still strings.
So what can we do? We could just map over
that array real quick and you could pass
it. Parse float. And what that will do is
it's going to run the parse float function
against every item in the result array.
And that's going to return to us
an actual array of numbers. So we're
going to split then right away map that
into parse float. And that's the same
thing as doing this function,
stir and then returning parse float stir
but because we're just running this,
it doesn't make sense to run a function.
You can just pass at the function directly
and it will call that function against
every item in that array.
Good. So what have we got here?
Let's look at our seconds. Good.
We've got an array of seconds.
The first one is 343 seconds.
The second one is 47 seconds.
Let's double check that right here.
The first one is that. It looks good. The
fourth one is 47 seconds.
Good. So our numbers are all adding up.
Now we want to add them together.
So how would I do that? Well, reduce is a
really good way. So if map takes in an
array and exports an array, a reduce
will take in an array and return
anything you want. It could be
a number, it could be a string,
it could be an object. In our case, we are
going to take all of these numbers and
reduce them down into one big number. So
we'll call .reduce and that will give us
each, we'll call that a total in seconds.
And from that, we're going to return
the total plus the seconds.
And of course we can make that
a nice little tidy arrow function. We just
do it in one line. So by the way these
seconds is not the same as the seconds. If
you wanted to rename that to something
like vidseconds just so you
don't confuse yourself, go for it.
Good. Now let's see what our main
seconds variables at. Okay good.
We've got the total number of seconds for
every single video added together.
Good, I'm nice and happy with that.
Now what we need to do with this
seconds variable here is we need to chop
it down into hours, minutes,
and seconds. So I'm going to create a
variable that's sort of going to be a
running tally of seconds left. Because
we're just start chipping away
at the hours and minutes and seconds.
So we'll say let seconds left
equals seconds. Then we make our hours,
is going to be equal to...
Normally we do something like this seconds
left divided by 3600 and what that will do
if I save it, look at how many hours we
have. We have 4.9 hours. But we don't care
about the point nine so what we can
do is we can just grab the lower limit
of that. We only care about whole
hours. The point nine is going to make
itself into seconds and minutes. Wrap it
in math.floor and that's going to tell us
that we have four whole hours.
Now seconds left is equal to, how do we
figure that out? It was like point 9 so
does that mean there was like 90 seconds
left? No it doesn't...because math is
100 based and minutes are 60 based,
so how do we figure that out? Well what we
can do is we take the seconds left and we
use mod 3600. Now what does mod do?
Let's do a little quick side lesson.
I've got a box of Smarties and in
that box I have 10 smarties.
Now I have five children so I'm
going to divide that by five.
How many Smarties does each kid
have? Two. Every kid gets two Smarties.
Good. But what if I open up a box and lo
and behold there was 11 Smarties?
Well there's only five kids so how many
Smarties does each kid get?
Two point two smarties? There's no way
you're going to...oh by the way,
if you're not Canadian, a Smartie is like
an M&amp;M. It's a little chocolate treat.
So there's no way you're going
to cut a little Smartie up into
point two pieces. So what we're only
concerned with is how many whole Smarties
is each kid going to get math.floor. So
each kid is going to get two whole
smarties, good but now what we want to
know and that's what we've done right here
but now what we want to do is we want to
figure out how many Smarties are left for
dad because I get to eat whatever cannot
be evenly distributed between all the kids
So what we have is 11 Smarties mod 5,
and that's going to return to us one.
Why one? Because what mod does
is it says, "How many are left after
they've been evenly distributed?"
So after each kid gets two,
there's going to be one left. Same thing
if I have five oranges and I divide them
by two kids. There's going to
be one left because it doesn't tell us,
and let's do a seconds example,
if I have 73 seconds and I divide that by
60 seconds, we clearly have 1 whole minute
math.floor shows us 1 whole minute but
what does that point two seconds? That's
not twenty seconds because that's a
percentage. So 73 mod 60 will tell us that
after we chunk it out into 1 whole minute,
we have 13 seconds left. That's
exactly what we're doing here.
After we chunk it into the hours, we are
going to have these many seconds left.
So let's console log seconds
left. Seconds, there we go.
So we have 3538 seconds left. So we can go
ahead and do minutes now, const mins
equals, we'll do the same thing math.floor
take the seconds left and we'll divide
that by 60 because there are 60 seconds in
a minute, then we update our seconds left
variable just like we did here but instead
we use 60. And this is why I used led up
here because we need to reassign this
value over and over. So console log hours
and minutes. 4 hours, 58 minutes and then
we can just use the seconds left because
that's what's left at the end of the day.
There's no need to convert it.
So we have our seconds left variable. So 4
hours, 58 minutes, and 58 seconds.
You can test that. You can take this one
that's 404 and change it to 406.
And if you refresh, it will show you
4 hours, 59 minutes, and 0 seconds left.
That's how I would do it. Also I've
done this into map and reduce.
Just so I can show you what we're doing
in every step of the time but if you
really understand what's going on here,
this could be all done in a single reduce.
You've taken this array of nodes. You
convert the dataset.time into minutes and
seconds. You convert that, then
into seconds then you convert that into
whole number of seconds where they have
the number, and then finally add it all
together. So it's up to you whether you do
it in one shot or make it a little bit
more readable and chunk it into separate
ones. And that allows you to write little
comments above each of them. Hopefully you
enjoyed that. I will see you tomorrow.
♪ [music] ♪