Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
Today we are going to learn all about
speech recognition in the browser.
While it's not perfect, it's actually
really impressive that you can do this
without any libraries or external APIs,
just do it straight in the browser.
So let's open up our index - start and
Phyllis open. All right,
I'm just going to get this sucker running
while I'll explain what we got going on.
Some hilarious results here.
So we've got speech recognition. It's a
global variable that lives in the browser
and that lives on top of the window. Now
in Chrome it lives at Webkit speech
recognition and currently it's only
available in Firefox.
So right here what we're doing is we're
just setting it to be speech recognition
even if it is Webkit speech recognition.
Then what we need to do is go ahead and
create a new instance of speech
recognition. Let's see,
this guy's still going, yes.
So we will say const recognition equals
new speech recognition and then we need to
take that recognition variable and set
something called the interim results.
And that has to be true. And what that's
going to do is as you are speaking,
you can see right here...as I'm speaking
it's sort of populating it.
And if you don't do that, you need to stop
speaking before it will give you anything.
That's a bit frustrating. So we want to be
able to see what we're saying
as we are speaking.
So we got our interim results here. Then
what we need to do is create a paragraph.
And if I inspect this right here, you'll
see what's happening is that I'm updating
the last paragraph in here. And then when
I stop speaking, it creates a new
paragraph as if we were saying a new
sentence. And then when I stop speaking
again, is going to create a new paragraph.
And the browser is going to tell us when
it's finished processing what I'm...
the brams. This is the best one ever.
All right. So we've got that recognition.
We need to create a paragraph.
So let's say, let P equals... And I'll
tell you why I'm using "let" there
in just a second.
We'll say a document.create element
and that's going to be a paragraph.
And then we also need to get this words
right here. They've other class of words.
So we say const words equals
document.query selector.words.
And then we'll take that words and we'll
append the child P, which is going to be
our first one because we're
going to put it in the DOM
just as we are working with it.
Next this work is just the same as
listening for clicks. So we take our
recognition and we add an event listener
but we don't listen for click but we
listen for a result. And when the results
comes back, were going to get an event
which... Let's just take a look at what
that actual event gives us here.
Console log E. So give that a save. Now
you do have to run this through a server.
Just like we did with the WebCam, you
can't just run it on a file.
It has to be localhost or something like
that. So take your index file and run it
through some sort of server. If you're not
sure, I've created a quick...
Where is it here?
I've created a quick little server for you
here in the speech detection folder.
All you need to do is type MPM install and
then when that's installed,
you type MPM start and what that will do
is it's just going to open up a little
server for you and then we open up the
index - start. Now that will probably pop
open a little dialog box that will say
can this access your microphone and you'll
say yes or no. But as we start speaking,
actually we don't see anything just yet
and that's because we haven't started
this. Take your recognition and call
recognition.start as you don't want to
unnecessarily run it on page load
because you might want to prompt the
user that "Hey we're going to ask for your
microphone, don't turn it down otherwise
we won't be able to see this."
So there we go. Now it should be running.
So we see our paragraph tag being put into
here. We've started it. We have an all add
or add event listener result singular not
results. Now when you speak into the
microphone, you should be seeing something
popping up in your console. Now when
you speak into the microphone,
you should be seeing some speech
recognition events pop up
into your console.
Now when you speak into your microphone,
you should see some speech recognition
event results just flooding into your
console. Now if you don't see anything,
make sure that it don't have like the
answer or anything else that's jacking
your microphone up opened in another tab.
That's something I spent way too much time
debugging and you just have to realize
sometimes the microphone would be used
on another tab.
So we have this event and let's just find
a random one right here.
Open up that event and go to the results.
Inside of the results...let's just console
E.results. That is going to be a list of
results and I say list because it's not an
array. It looks like an array, but if you
open up the prototype and see what's in
there, you'll see that there is no Map or
for each or anything like that.
That's going to be a bit of an issue for
us so we can convert that to an array or
use ES 64 ave to iterate over it.
So here we've got a list and if you open
each of those up, you'll see there's
another thing inside of it. This data is
so nested. Opened it up once more time,
and then you see that is going to be. And
then the second one we'll say,
open it up again, it keeps jumping around.
That is going to be a list of.
And it tells you what the person said
and then as well as its confidence.
Like this one is 89% confidence. That's
what I said. And here it's like less than
a percent confident and it builds up
confidence over time as it gets to
analyze it a few more times. And then
finally, there is an is final build-in
here which tells us is the person done
speaking that sentence.
So what we really need to do here is to
take this sort of mess of nested stuff and
convert it into just a plain old string
that we can see. So let's go into here and
we'll say const transcript equals
array.from and we need to convert it to an
arrayE.results because it's not an
array by default. And then we're going to
just map over each of them and then just
turn it from one thing to another.
So first thing I want to do is just grab
the first thing from each of them because
this is the list and we need to grab the
first thing from each of them.
So we could actually just take.
So we are going to map over it and take
the first thing that we have there.
So even if it's on it's own line and we're
going to Map the results is going to
return the result [0] because that's the
first thing that is there. And then if we
console log the transcript, let's see what
we've got. "Hello, I love to pet dogs."
Let's see. Open it up. Some of them are
going to be two things.
Like this one will tell me that, "Hello, I
love." And the second thing that it gives
us is so nested, "The pet dog." And then
I'm sure that it would correct it
as we go along.
So good. Now we need to map over
that once more and return the
results.transcript. "Hello, I love to pet
dogs." There we go. Look at what we've
got  here. We've got arrays coming in.
All right one more time,
"Hello, I love..." There we go. Sometimes,
LOL... How did it know that I
was actually laughing out loud?
That's amazing.
I've got an array of the different
pieces that it thinks I said.
So what we need to do finally is join
those two pieces together because we don't
want two strings or three strings or one
string. We want one big string.
So join at the end. I'm going to take
this console log out. Now when I say
something... Now when I say something,
it tells me exactly what I have.
You will notice that if you stopped
speaking and then start speaking again,
it doesn't work. And why is that? And that
is because we're listening for the result
but then once the result is finished it
doesn't, like it unbinds itself, it's no
longer listening. So what we need to do is
add a second event listener for the end
event. And when that ends, we simply just
call the function. We can just tell it.
When it ends, run the function for us
recognition.start. We don't run it here
because that would run a page load but we
just supply the name of the function that
it will then call. So if we give that a
save. Now when I start talking...
and after a break, it will start up again.
And that's because this end event
is firing which in turn is going to
add the event listener.
It's going to start listening
for it again.
Good. Now what we need to do is create a
paragraph tag where we can put these
paragraphs. Actually we already have a
paragraph tag. So right down here we
simply have to say P.text content is equal
to transcript. Now when I start talking,
we should see it in the DOM, but when I
start talking again, it overwrites it.
What's going on here? Well, what's
happening is that if I'm done with that
sentence, this is going to run again and
replace it. So what we need to do is check
if the result is final. So let's say, if
E.results, the first one,
dot is final, then we need to create a new
paragraph. We are going to overwrite this
paragraph we created on page load. So
we just say P equals...nope don't put a
vowel letter in front of it. We're going
to overwrite this existing one here.
P equals document.create element P and I
will stick that sucker in the words.append
child P.
Now when we talk, it should add a
paragraph and when I talk again,
it should add a second paragraph and a
third, exclamation mark.
Do you get the point?
Sweet, seems to be working. So
that is the very basics of speech
recognition that we have here it's
actually not a lot of code. What you could
do with this now is that now that we have
this transcript, you could say like if
transcript. as it contains unicorn, then
console log unicorn. Whoa.
"I love dogs." oh, it's not contains
it's includes,
"I Love dogs. I love unicorns." And when
you say the word unicorn,
it triggers it and goes off. So what
you could do is you could listen if
includes like, "Get the weather" And then
it would run a function that would also
log getting the weather. "Siri, go get the
weather." And then it will run this
getting the weather function. Obviously
you'd have to debounce that or
only run it once every so often because it
will run it multiple times,
but you get the point here. I've seen
people hook this up to external weather
APIs or to other functions and you can
basically have a hands-off application
that listens for what you're saying behind
the scenes and when it sees those words
that you want, it will trigger some sort
of other function. Hopefully you
enjoyed that. I would love to see what you
build with this. There is just a whole
world that opens up when you have speech
recognition. So please let me know what
you create. Thanks and
I'll see you tomorrow.
♪ [music] ♪