♪ [music] ♪
Edited at https://subtitletools.com
Today we are going to be learning about
geolocation and not just getting the
latitude and longitude with geolocation,
although we can do that if you like.
But there is also information that comes
along with geolocation, and that is the
heading, which is essentially
like a compass, or how
many degrees of north is the person
currently at. And it also will tell us the
speed at which somebody is
running, which is kind of cool.
In Chrome, we can fake coordinates,
but we cannot fake heading,
and we cannot fake speed, so really the
only way that I found to do this so far is
with the iOS Simulator. And if you don't
have a Mac, you might have to sit tight on
this one, or you can run it on your phone,
and then start running down the street to
actually test it, because you need
some real data to get it going.
So I've downloaded Xcode here, and if you
don't have a Mac, I maybe can do this with
Android, I'm not totally sure. You go to
Xcode, Open Developer Tool and then
Simulator, and then you can change the
hardware from hardware device iOS 10, and
then you might have to download
some of these things first, so I've got
it open on an iPhone 7 Plus.
Now the next thing is just like our last
two, you cannot run access to your users
webcam, to their microphone and now you
cannot access their geolocation unless
you're on a secure origin. And that hasn't
been a problem for us so far because what
we've been doing is we did our npm
install here, which will install just that
BrowserSyncs, and it will do a npm start
for us. Now that will give us a localhost
which is a secure origin, but because I
want to open it up on a different device,
it's going give us a external IP
address or internal IP address, sorry.
It'll say https://192.168.1.107, and that
is the address that we need to visit on
our devices. Now BrowserSync ships with
what's called a self-signed certificate,
which allows you to have https on your
computer. It's still going to throw this
really scary warning, but that's because
it is a self-signed certificate, and it
doesn't trust it. So you have to go to
Advanced, and you have to proceed to the
localhost in order to get that to work,
it's still going to cross us out,
but that is standard for getting it
working on your local computer.
So what we want to do is actually copy
this https here, open up your Safari on
your simulator here and visit that
website. Now it's going to yell at you
that this is not a trusted...cannot verify
the identity. You want to click on
continue there, and then it's going to
serve it over in a secure origin,
and then we go to our index-FINISHED
to see where we got. Now
it's going to ask you, "Can you
access your location?" You say,
"Yes," I want to have access to that
location ask me a second time,
oh, and there we go,
so what's happening
here is that I've gone
to my simulator here.
You go to Debug, Location and you can
select a number of different jaunts,
so this is simulating somebody running,
having a bike ride at the Apple Campus,
walking around, I guess, or a freeway
drive. And it's going to simulate updating
the location as well as the actual speed.
That's why we need to use this iOS
Simulator in here, so that's how that
one works, but we want to go back
to our index-START.
One other thing you might want to do is to
open up Safari, and the beauty of Safari
is that you can take Safari, you can go to
Develop. You can find, like, this is the
phone that I'm using right now, but you
can also have your simulator,
and you can see, you can open up Dev Tools
for whatever it is that's currently open
on your phone or in the simulator that's
pretty cool. So that's going to be
helpful to have that console
window open for us just in case
we need to see if we
have any errors now, so
let's go back to our script tags here, and
let's get going with coding this. First
thing that you need to do is to select
both the arrow, which is this right here,
and the kilometers per hour that we are
running on, so go to our script tag here
and we'll say const arrow equals
document.querySelector.('arrow').
Do the same thing for speed.
Now that we have that,
we need to listen
for the user's position,
so we access that on
navigator.geolocation., and now there's
two ones here there is watchPosition, and
there is getCurrentPosition.
We want watchPosition because
getCurrentPosition will just give us the
one, and watchPosition is going to just
watch it over time, and it's just going to
give us data as frequently as we need it.
The person's not moving around too much,
it's going to give us less frequent
updates. If the person is flying down the
highway, it's going to give us
a lot more frequent updates, so
we have that data that comes in here, and
it's going to run a function, and let's
just console.log the data to see what
we've got. Then give that a save,
it's going to ask the user location, and
then I'm going to open up my Safari Dev
Tools here, and here we go look at this.
This is data that's streaming in, and this
is giving us this geoposition, I'm
going to go bump the size up here.
Inside of that, we have a timestamp
as to when that happened
as well as coordinates
for what happened.
So here, we've got accuracy, and I believe
that is number of meters it is accurate
to. We've got heading, this is really
good, so that is the numbered of degrees
relative to North that we are, and then
we've got the latitude and longitude to
where they are, you could put that on a
map if you want, and then speed,
and that's coming in at kilometers per
hour. So if you're some weirdo from the
states that uses miles, you got
to do the math, but us, the rest
of the world, will use kilometers.
Now we've got this data here, and what we
simply have to do now is we can update it,
so we say speed.textContent equals
data.coords.speed. Now when we refresh
that sucker, see that we're automatically
seeing this, and if you wanted too,
you could pop it in a Math.round,
and that would just give you 34.
I find that it doesn't change very often,
so you're not sure if it's working or not,
so I like to keep the decimal places
there just so that we can see exactly how
fast they're changing. That's good.
Now what we need to do is rotate this
compass right here, which is our arrow,
depending on where we are, and we simply
just take the arrow, and we apply the
style.transform, and this is just a CSS
transform, and that's going to rotate
and normally be, like, 20 degrees, let's
try that. So you see what happened,
that it rotated it 20 degrees, but we
don't want to rotate it 20 degrees, we
want to rotate it, the
data.coords.heading,
and that is the number of
degrees relative of north,
and it's already 360 base, so you
don't have to do any math on that.
Give it a save, and now you see that
this thing is slightly turning depending
on where the person actually
currently is in their jog,
and it will just tilt
itself as we go along.
Last thing we need to do here is if
someone... This right here is called the
success callback, so when someone
successfully gives you access to it, this
will run, but what happens if they say,
"No." Then what we have to do is run a new
function here, which is our error, and
we'll just console.log or console.err that
error message, and then maybe, like, alert
to the user, "Hey, you gotta allow that to
happen!!!" Or whatever it is, and then you
have to display instructions to the user
on how to re-enable it if
they've blocked it from happening.
Give that a save, BrowserSync.
We can switch it around, change our
location, let's go on a run instead.
We're going a lot slower, and there's a
lot more turns in something like that,
so that's pretty cool. You can look at
the latitude and longitude inside of this
data.coords if you like, maybe if you want
to try do a Google Map, but this is a
framework-free series, so there's not
too much we could do with the latitude and
longitude. Hopefully you enjoy
that, and I'll see you tomorrow.
♪ [music] ♪