Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [ music] ♪
A couple weeks ago Stripe launched
this new page and I hovered over the
navigation and I was
like, "Whoa. How are they doing that?"
Because you know if you have a drop down
and you hide one and show the other,
you can't just transition the background.
You can't just move the unordered list
from one to another, because it's two
different elements. So, I figured out how
to do it, and we're going to build a
replica of this in a coming video.
But what I wanted to do was start with
something simple, just so we can get the
ideas. Because it's a bit of a doozy. They
obviously have some really good developers
at Stripe to build this thing. But I
really want to understand, sort of,
the fundamentals of what's happening. So,
this is what we're going to start with,
and then in a couple videos down the road,
we're going to replicate this sort of
thing with the Stripe navigation.
So, here's what we're doing. We've got
these links on the page,
and when you hover over one of the links,
we've got this little pill that's going to
both resize itself, so it's short and
long, as well as follow you around the
page wherever that is going. So let's
open up our index-start and get going.
Go down to our script tag here. So, first
thing that we need to do,
is to get all of what I like to call
triggers. Things that will be hovered,
that need a background behind it. So I'm
just going to do every single link that's
on the page.
So it's "const triggers =
document.query selector all A."
Every single link on the actual page. Then
what we need to do is create what's called
a highlight. Because if you haven't
figured it out yet, how does this actually
work? If we inspect it here, and we look
at our DOM, you're going to see that we
have the span with a class of highlight,
that I've just tacked into the DOM here.
And when you highlight over something, it
will figure out the width,
the height, and where on the page that
actual item is. And because there's CSS
transitions on this element, it's just
going to transition itself from place,
to place, to place. And the width, the
height, and the transform translate X,
and translate Y values, are gong to
be moved on over.
So we will first make that highlight
ourself, rather than having to go into our
HTML and do it we're going to make it in
there. So, we'll say "const highlight
= document.create element." And we're
going to make a span.
We're going to add a class of highlight,
and then we're going to put it into the
DOM.
When we open this up in our browser here,
you actually won't see that highlight
anywhere, and it's because it does not
have a width or a height or anything like
that. But if we inspect, you should see
that we do actually have this highlight
element in here. Good. Now what we need to
do is listen for someone enters into a
link. So we'll make a function called,
let's call it highlight link.
And we'll just console.log highlight. And
then we'll listen for the mouse enter
event on each of our triggers.
Triggers.for each and then take our link,
and we're going to take the link and we're
going to add the event listener for mouse
enter. And when that happens we are gong
to run the function highlight link.
Good. Now let's try it out.
Console highlight over it, there we go.
We've got highlight triggering on all of
the links on the page. And you can tell
that by console logging this.
And you'll see it will log the actual link
that we're looking for.
Good. So, we've got that working so far.
But now, what needs to happen is we need
to figure out the width, the height, the X
and the Y. We need to figure out how big
is the element that we hovered? And where
on the page is that actual element?
So, we're going to use a method called
"get bounding client rect,"
which is a bit of a mouthful to say. But
we'll say const link coords,
this is going to give us the coordinates,
and this, this is going to be equal to the
thing that was triggered, which is going
to be each of the links.
Dot get, bounding client rect. And then
just console log those link coords to see
what we have here.
So I'm going to hover over this sucker. Ah
and look what we get here.
We get the client rect. We've got the
bottom, the height, the left,
the right, the top and the width. So it
gives us all the information about where
on the page does that thing actually live.
Now that we have those coordinates here,
we can simply take our highlight element,
and we can apply the style.width
is gong to be equal to, and we'll
take the link coords.width and you need to
put on PX on the end, otherwise it's just
going to be 399 or 409 or something that
we don't know. And we'll do that also with
the height. Let's see where we're at with
that. Hover one of these. Okay, so that
matches up. And then when you go from one
to another, it's dynamically applying the
style to it.
And if you go to our style.css and you
look for the highlight selector,
.highlight, there we go. We have this
transition on here of 0.2 seconds.
So in order to change that to two seconds,
you'll see that it will just change itself
over that amount of time. And like, these
links are a little bit shorter than these
links. So it will grow both in width and
height. So that is why.
If we didn't have that transition on there
it would just be immediate snaps,
and that's not what we want. We want it to
animate itself. So where the fun part
comes in is where we start to animate the
left and the right values.
And we're going to be doing that. Rather
than doing it with CSS.left and .right,
or top and bottom, what we will be doing
is we will be using the transform property
to apply it and that can have some
benefits when you're looking for some
really smooth animation.
So, we'll take our highlight. We'll apply
the style of transform.
And normally how it works is that we say
something like translate and then you give
it an X and a Y. So 100 and 100. You see
how it animates itself to 100 100?
Well, we want to make these 100 and 100
dynamic. But we take our 100,
and replace it with our variable here. So
we'll say linkcoords.left,
and this one is going to be
linkcoords.top. And that will give us the
value right from the top. Now if we hover
over any of these items here,
everything is looking good. You can also
go up into one of your ones and maybe put
a break tag in or something to make it
bigger. You can see that it's going to
transition both the height, the width, and
the X and the Y.
Now, you might think you're done, and a
lot of people do this,
but they don't try...like open your DEV
tools, and scroll down a little bit.
Now hover over one of them. Oh. What the
hell is going on? They're like a little
bit messed up. If I scroll down a little
bit, you see how it's off by the amount
that I've scrolled down? Hmm. That's a
little bit of a pain here.
And how we compensate for that is, you can
do it in a couple of ways.
First, we can figure out what the offset
of the actual parent is.
And we're going to do that in the next
one. But in this case, I think we can just
simply take how far the person has
scrolled down, and then take that away
from our actual item. So how do we do
that? Well, let's go into our window here.
Window.scroll Y is going to give us zero.
Scroll down a little bit and re-run that.
It's going to give you 67. That's how far
we actually are. So,
let's go back and refactor this code a
little bit.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to make
our own coordinates here.
So we'll say "const.coords =." It's
going to have a width, which is going to
be equal to the linkcoords.width. The
width and the height are fine.
Right. But the problem is with our X and
our Y, or our top and our left.
So the top is now going to be
linkcoords.top minus wondow.scroll Y.
And then we'll do that for our left which
is link.left and we can also do scroll X
just in case we have any horizontal scroll
there. Then what we'll do is we'll switch
out the reference to link coords, with
just the coords. Object,
which we've done here. We've done a little
bit of math there.
Now when I refresh and scroll down a
little bit, it still doesn't work,
and that's because I minused them, we
should add them in, not take them away.
There we go. Now if I scroll down anywhere
on the page it's always going to follow us
along regardless of where we are on the
page. So, that is the very basics.
Really, what I wanted to get down there is
this concept of the get bounding client
rect, and then applying it to the inline
style. In a couple more videos,
we're going to go ahead and build out the
entire drop down, which is a lot more
involved. I'll see you then.
♪ [music] ♪