Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
- [Karen] Okay folks, today we are going
to use the browser's Speech Synthesis API
to create this one bomb diggity
Voiceinator 5000 application. Ready?
Smiling pile of poo.
- [Male] All right. I hope you enjoyed
that introduction. What we're going to be
working with today is the Speech Synthesis
API that comes in most modern
browsers. Much like we did Voice to Text a
couple days ago, we're now going to be
doing Text to Voice. So let's take a quick
look at our HTML that we've got set up
here. We've got a select which is going to
contain a list of all of our possible
voices. If we look at the answer here,
you'll see them here.
There's a lot more. I'm currently
filtering just for the English ones.
Then we also have an input with the name
of rate which is going to change...
- [Alex] Hello, I love JavaScript. Hello,
I love JavaScript, thumbs up.
- ...how fast the person talks.
- Hello.
- You get the point. And we also have
pitch.
- Hello.
- Ah, oh boy. And then finally we've got a
text area with the name of text which is
going to contain whatever the person says,
right, we're going to write it in there.
Now, only...the important thing we need to
know there is that rate,
pitch, and text, the names of all these
inputs here, they are important that they
are that because the name of them is going
to line up with the property on the
utterance which is essentially
the voice that's going to say it,
so those are important. Don't change
those. And we've got the stop and speak
buttons to start and stop it. Now, let's
go down here. I've got you some you
starter code here. We've got a message
which we're going to create a new speech
synthesis utterance and that essentially
means what is the person going to say.
And on that utterance, it's going to
contain information about how fast do they
say it, what is the pitch that they say
it, what is the voice that they say it in,
and what will they be saying. So all these
four things that we have here,
those are going to be put onto our
utterance. So we're creating a new version
of that into message.
We have an empty array here which our
voices are going to be dumped into.
And then I've just gone ahead and selected
the drop down. I selected the rate,
the pitch, and the text area all in one
go. I call those options.
We have the speak button here which is
going to start it and then the other one
that's going to stop it. Good. So what we
need to now do is on page load,
whatever is in this text area, I want to
set that to be the default.
So what we'll do here is we'll say
message.text equal to. And normally
to say hello, testing in here. What we
want to do is we want to select this box
right here and set it to be whatever is in
there. So we'll say document.querySelector
where the name is equal to text and we'll
call the value right out of there.
Give that a save and a refresh, open up
your DevTools here. And if you type in
M-S-G, you should see that we have our
speech synthesis utterance and the text is
now equal to, "Hello, I love JavaScript,"
however there is no voice being set
just yet. So let's go ahead and populate
all the different voices. So what we do
is we take a global variable...if this is
a speech synthesis utterance,
that's sort of like one thing that
a person might say,
we also have another global variable
called speech synthesis.
And what speech synthesis will
do is you can call .speak on it and pass
it an utterance which is going to be our
message. Now, if I were to do that right
now and try call SpeechSynthesis.speak and
pass it our utterance because the
utterance is the thing that we say, it
doesn't work just yet and that's because
there is no voice. But we can take that
global variable which is speech synthesis
and we can add an Event Listener to it, so
add Event Listener.
And there is an event called voices
changed. And when that happens,
we're going to populate our voices. So
we're going to make a function called
populateVoices and then right before
that, we'll make that function.
Then what we say is we will take that
voices array that we've declared up here
and we'll just overwrite it with this,
.getVoices. And let's just console.log
voices and see what we have.
So when...and this just can't be called on
page load because when speech synthesis
loads, it has to fire the voices changed
because sometimes it'll take a hot second
in order for it to load, so we need to
wait until we run the voices changed.
So...whoa, look at this. And if you are on
a Windows machine, you might not see as
many. The Mac comes with a whole bunch of
voices built in which is pretty fun and
you can open it up. Each of this is a
voice where they have a name like Alva and
a language code that they speak in. So
what we want to do is loop over all of
those speech voices and set them as
options in this drop down.
So we'll say, "const voiceOptions equals,"
we'll take our voices and we'll map over
it because I like to map over absolutely
everything. Put that on its own line here.
And we have our voice and from the voice,
we're just going to return an option where
the value is going to be the voice.name.
And then in there, we're also going to put
the voice.name, but in brackets. I also
want to put the voice.lang just so you can
see what language that
voice is meant to be.
And then once you've done that, we
we click join on it and then
we will take our voices drop down and set
the innerHTML to be voiceOptions.
Or if you'd like, you can just put this,
[removed] right away inside of here and
then you've done away with this one extra
line here. So let's take a refresh of that
Refresh your page and you'll see
that as soon as the voices load,
you'll get a huge drop down of all the
possible voices. Now again,
you might not see all these voices but it
looks like Google does include some of
their own voices as well for Chrome. Now
that those voices are actually loaded on
the page, we can take a look at our
message here and open it up.
There still is no voice on it but because
those voices have been loaded into the
page, it will just default to our buddy
Alex which is the default one.
So we can now call speechSynthesis.speak,
pass it our utterance which is such a
hilarious thing. It's a M-S-G.
And then when you call it...
- Hello, I love JavaScript, thumbs up.
- Ah, and then we say message.text is
equal to Wes is cool. And then we could
run it again.
- Wes is cool.
- So you get the point what's going on
here? We've got an utterance.
We've got a speech synthesis that will
then take that utterance and then talk out
whatever we have. But we want to be able
to choose one of this from the drop down
and that doesn't work just yet. So we're
going to make another function called
setVoice and that is going to be called
console.log changing voice.
That's going to be called when we change
from this drop down. So what is that?
We have our voices drop down. We're going
to add an event listener for change,
and when that happens we're going to call
setVoice. Let's try that.
Okay. So changing voice, changing voice.
Every time we change this drop down,
it's actually changing it. But we don't
just want to console.log it,
what we want to do is we have our
utterance which is msg and we want to set
the voice to be...and we can't just say
like Alex or something like that because
it's not a valid voice property. So what
we need to do is find the voice that lines
up with the value. And the way we can do
that is if you were to just console.log
this.value, Anna and Ellen and Luciana. So
we need to find not just the name of it,
but if you look at our voices array, we
need to find the corresponding speech
synthesis voice object. So the way we did
that is we'll say msg.voice is equal to
voices.find. So we're going to find the
one where the voice.name is equal to
this .value.
Essentially what that's doing is it's
going to loop over every single one of
these voices in the array and it's going
to find the one where its name attribute
is the same as the option that was
currently selected like Alva,
right? So it's going to loop over until it
finds a voice.name that's equal to Alva
and then we've gone ahead and set it.
So let's try that now. Refresh.
Go ahead and select Amelle and then we can
manually call speechSynthesis.speak, MSG
- [Amelle] Hello. I love JavaScript
[Speaking in Foreign Language 00:09:20]
- Ooh, la, la. All right. Let's check out
Ellen from the Netherlands.
- [Ellen] Hello. I love JavaScript
[Speaking in Foreign Language 00:09:26]
- And Fiona.
- [Fiona] Hello. I love JavaScript,
thumps up.
- I have found that some of these Google
ones take a bit to load.
So if you do select it and it's not
working, maybe you just wait a second.
I haven't figure that totally out. See.
- [Female] Hello. I love JavaScript
[Speaking in Foreign Language 00:09:42]
- There we go, seems to be
working nice. Carmit.
- [Carmit] Hello. I love JavaScript
[Speaking in Foreign Language 00:09:50].
- It does speak the emojis in the native
language, but then just does English words
in the accent of that language which is
kind of funny. So we've got that.
Now, what I want to do is make a function
that's going to...every time I change one
of these things, I want to restart it. So
that's going to be a function called
toggle. And what we're going to do is
first we're just going to cancel anything
that we have that is currently
speaking. So we're going to call
speechSynthesis.cancel, and watch this.
So if I run something,
it immediately call toggle.
It will cancel it right there. That's
what cancel do, stop it from speaking and
then we'll just restart the entire thing
which is speechSynthesis.speak.
Then we'll go back up to the set voice and
just call toggle on the end.
So now we'll go to Carmit.
- Hello. I love JavaScript...
- So every time you change...
- [Female] Hello, I love JavaScript.
- Hello.
- You get the point, right? It's going to
stop it and start it again.
You can also pass a flag here. I'm going
to call startOver, because sometimes you
might want to call pass false so it will
not restart itself and that's what you can
pass as false. So we're going to say if
startOver, and it's by default going to be
true so you don't have to pass anything
unless you explicitly want it to not
start over. And then we run it like that.
Double check this, it's still working.
- Hello. I love JavaScript.
- [Female] I love JavaScript [Speaking in
Foreign Language 00:11:30]
- I could toggle false and it
will stop it whereas toggle itself would
just restart it and toggle false will stop
it all. That's what this statement does
here. Good. Next up, what we want
to do is work with our rate,
our pitch, as well as our message. So
we're going to go down here and we're
going to take all of our options
which...let me take a look at.
What are our options? Options are
three inputs, the slider,
the second slider and the text area. So
we'll take all of our options here.
The options.forEach option,
option.addEventListener and we're going to
listen for the change event. And when that
happens, we are going to run a function
called set option which we'll then code
here , function setOption.
And inside of that function, we
could...let's just do this console.log,
this.name and this.value. So when I slide
this rate here, it's going to tell me...
I got to go to all...the rate has changed
to 0.3. The pitch has changed to 0.4.
The pitch is at 1.9. Wes is cool.
And then I click away the text area.
The text property, I changed to I love
JavaScript, Wes is cool.
So now we've bound all of these options.
When they change, we know what property
will change which is this.name, and what
it was changed to which is this.value.
So we simply need to take our message and
set what property changed,
this.name, to what changed, this.value.
And then we can run the thing...we can
stop it and start it over again.
So let's try that now.
So I'm going to change the rate up.
- Hello. I love JavaScript, thumbs up.
- Then it'll say Wes is cool, and go to
tab away or click away.
- Wes is cool.
- And then it will rerun that. Why?
Because these things have changed.
We're also doing that on here.
- [Ellen] Wes is cool.
- Awesome. Then these buttons right here,
we got to listen for a click on them.
So we'll take our speak button which is
the speak one right here,
speakButton.addEventListener, click. When
that happens, we are going to run the
function toggle and that's just
going to manually run it.
- Hello. I love JavaScript, thumbs up.
- And you can put some poops in there.
It's pretty funny when you
put emojis in there.
- Smiling pile of poo, eyes.
- [Female] [Speaking in Foreign Language
00:14:17]
- I like it. Oh, remind me...you're not
going to remind me. We should filter this
list for just English ones if that's what
you're looking for. But we do have to run
our speak button and then we also need to
listen for a click on our stop button.
So when the stop button is clicked, toggle
false. Oh, how do you do that,
folks? How do you pass an argument to a
function? Well, you might think like,
"Okay, I could... I can make it a function
like this and there's a toggle false."
Let's see if that works, so.
- Hello.
- Okay. That works but that seems a little
bit big. Is there another way
we could do it? You can't call toggle
false like that because
that's just going to run on page load.
- Hello. I love JavaScript, thumbs up.
- It doesn't do anything because
this function is not returning a function.
So, okay. Huh. So what we could
do, there's a couple different ways we
could do it. You can call .bind, pass it
the value of this which is going to be
nothing and then pass it your first
argument which is going to be false.
And that's what bind does is you take a
function and then you call it in the
context of this and pass it an
argument, a false.
- Hello. I love...
- Works great. Or this is somewhat
popular in react right now.
And you could just do an inline function,
arrow function right here.
You say toggle false. So downside to that
is this is creating another function,
same with bind and same with the function
but that is another way to do it.
- Hello. I love...
- And it's really not that big of a deal
in this case, unless I was creating lots
and lots and lots of these. So we've got
that. Last thing I wanted to do is filter
this list for only ones that are English
like our friend Karen from Australia.
So what we'll go do before we map, we'll
simply add a quick filter in there for the
voice and we say, "If the
voice.lang.includes EN." And that should
just trim that list down to ones that
include EN before we map over it.
And then when I refresh, you only see a
smaller subset of the list of the ones
that we have there. So that is the
Voiceinator 5000. It's actually pretty
simple to get all of this code up and
running. We just created a couple
different functions that will listen for
when the different elements are changed
and then it says it for us. Hopefully you
enjoyed that. I love to see what you make
of it and I will see you tomorrow.
♪ [music] ♪