Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
Today we're going to do something that...
this is probably one of the very first
things that I learned in jQuery when I was
first starting to learn JavaScript and it
was how do I actually fix a nav when you
scroll to it? So this is what we're going
to be building here where you've got
this nav that's just position rolled over
static and then as soon as you hit that
point where it hits the top of the
browser, we're going to make it fixed
so the content scrolls underneath. And
then we can also do some hotshot stuff
like scroll out the logo or something like
that. So first thing we're going to do is
grab this nav right here. So I'm going to
say const nav = document.querySelector
and we're going to look for the nav with
the ID of main and then we're also
going to make a function called fixNav
that is then going to run every single
page scroll, awesome. So what this is
going to do is we're going to figure out
where the top of this navigation black bar
is. Let's say it's 500 pixels from the top
and then when we scroll, we're going to
figure out how far are we scrolled?
Let's say, right here, I'm about 400
pixels scrolled. But as soon as I hit that
threshold of scrolling more than the top
of the nav is, so as soon I've scroll 501
pixels, the nav bar is going to go, "Oop,
I'm off screen, I should now fix myself."
So what we need to do on page load is
grab wherever the top of this nav
actually looks. So let's say
const topOfNav = nav.offsetTop.
Then when you console.log(topOfNav)...
let's just console.log that every single
time that we run it, open up your dev
tools. I recommend putting your dev tools
at the side here so that won't mess up
your top of nav here. You could also
update this variable every time that your
window resizes just so that if somebody
does resize or open dev tools, you've got
it. So I'm going to scroll here and you
see, it's 542 pixels, that is the top
of the navigation at that point.
So what we can then do is we'll say
if(window.scrollY)... Why?
Because what is window.scrollY? Let's go
back to that topOfNav and then we'll also
console.log window.scrollY.
We've done this in a couple of tutorials
so far now. So now you're going to
see that the second value, 1,
that's how far we've scrolled. And then
you're going to see that as we get closer
and closer to where it's going to hit the
top, we're just about at that point where
the 542 pixels is going to be equal
to the 542. And at that point,
we want to make that nav fixed. So we're
going to go in here, we're going to say
if(topOfNav >= window)...
or other way around,
window.scrollY >= topOfNav,
if that is true,
what we're going to do is we're going to
pop a class and when I do things like
this, I like to pop a class on the body
just so that I can always target any of
the children when we're in the fixed nav
state. Some people like to put it on the
nav itself, but I found that if I
want to target anything else,
it's nice to have it nice
and high on the body,
document.body.classList.add('fixed-nav')
and then we'll say else,
and we'll just duplicate this,
which you're going to remove.
Now that's not going to
get us all the way there,
but if we save that now
and refresh, now as you scroll,
you'll see this fixed-nav is being added
and removed, but it's not actually fixing
itself. So we need to go over to our
style-start.CSS and find our navs CSS
and this isn't the greatest CSS because
it's using just the element selectors
here. It should probably have a class or
something like that, but I'm trying to
keep it as simple as we can. And I'm going
to say when the body has a class of
.fixed-nav, the nav itself is going to be
positioned: fixed; and then I'm going to
put a quick little box-shadow on there to
just give it a little bit of a shadow so
when it is in that fixed state, you have a
shadow showing that you have some depth
there. All right, so now, when I hit this
point... oh, you see what's happening?
Now it seems to be working, but it
seems kind of janky. You see what's going
on here? As soon as we hit that little end
point there, the content jumps up and why
is that happening? Well, the reason for
that happening is because when you make
this nav fixed, it is no longer
taking up space in the document.
You know this from CSS. When you make
an element fixed, it no longer takes up
space. It sort of floats on top of
the browser. And by doing that,
what's happening is that we cause a reflow
on the page and this site wrap right here,
it says, "Oh, this nav is no longer taking
up space, well, I don't mind if I do,"
and it moves on up the exact amount of
space that it gave up, which is however
many pixels. So what we need to do is we
need to offset that amount by adding some
padding to our body. So just as
we make it fixed, we need to
offset that amount so they don't
get this jerky jump right here.
So let's go back to our element
right here and we're going to
take our document.body.style and
we're going to set the paddingTop,
and if you have something
that is a padding-top,
you cannot do that in JavaScript,
so that's a camel case.
And we're going to set that
to be the nav.offsetHeight.
Why? What is that going to give us? If I
were to run this in my console here,
nav.offsetHeight is going to give
us however large this nav is.
And I've seen people just like hardcode
64px, but don't do that because then what
happens if your nav changes or your font
changes or anything else and then you're
going to be off just a couple pixels. So
programmatically grab the height of the
pixels and then add on px to the top. And
then what we'll also do is on the opposite
end, we'll just set the padding top
to be zero, good. So now when...
Ooh, look at that,
so now we've got this nav, nav, nav,
normal, normal, normal, and then fixed.
And as soon as we hit that point, we don't
have that jump anymore. And your can go
into your Elements panel and take a
look at what's going on here. See this?
style= padding-top: 0 and then as soon as
we that point, the class of fixed goes on
and then the padding-top is 64px.
Again, you might be asking why don't
I just like put it in here when I have a
class of fixed-nav, give it padding-top
of 64 px? It's that we don't know how high
this nav is going to be and I'd rather do
it programmatically and do in line than
have to guess and update that every time
the nav changes itself. So that's looking
pretty good. So that's working great.
There're a couple other things that
we can do. If you open up your nav,
you're going to see that we have
an li with a class of logo.
If we look into our style sheet here,
you'll see that I gave it a max-width
of 0 and give it an overflow of hidden.
So it's there, it's just not being shown
at all because it has a width of zero.
Then what we're going to do is we're going
to say, "When the body has a class of
fixed-nav, the li with a class of logo is
going to have a max-width of
something bigger than it will ever be,
like 500px," and I'll show you why in just
second, why we didn't use width
in this case. So give that
a save and now watch what
happens when we scroll, when we hit
that point, ooh, it slides itself out.
Why? Because we have set it to be default
0 and then when you have a max-width of
500, it's going to transition, which is
right here, you could set that to be 5px,
if you really like. And over five
seconds, it's going to animate itself in
and animate itself out. Now quick
question, this is a bit of an aside
nothing to do with JavaScript, why
didn't I do width and width: auto?
That's because you cannot animate
the width of something to be from zero
to auto. You do have to use a max-width
in order to get that transition to kick in
here. So nothing brings itself in,
obviously, let's do over half a second
instead. Brings itself in. And then
one last thing that I did is if you look
at this site wrap, you'll see I've given
it a scale of 98%. We can do here is
when the body has a class of
fixed-nav, this site-wrap is going to...
we're going to transform,
we're going to scale it up to 1.
So it's just going to go from 98% to 1.
You're going to get this little...
You see how it sort of brings
itself in, a little bit effect.
I really like these things because all we
did there is add one class to the body
and then everything else is just
taken cared of in our CSS.
So hopefully you liked that, it's really
interesting. There's not a lot of code
but understanding that you need to take
care of that extra space when you fix it
is really the key to this one.
Thanks a lot. I'll see you tomorrow.