Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
Quick, short, and sweet lesson today, and
it's going to be about .addEventListener.
We're not going to be building anything
huge here, but there's a couple concepts
that I need to make sure that we all get
down pat, because we've been using these
.addEventListeners throughout all these
videos, but there's going to be edge cases
that you run into where these things are
going to be helpful. So what I've got here
is I've got three divs. I've got a div
with a class of one, two, and three.
and they're all nested inside
of each other. What I want to do is
explain to you a couple things about
propagation, bubbling, event capturing,
as well as using this new property called
once. So go into your scrip tag here,
and I want to just listen for a click on
all of these divs, so we're going to
select all those divs, and we're going to
make a function called logText.
Fix in the event, and we're just going to
console.log(this.classList.value).
When somebody clicks a div,
we're going to log it, so we'll say take
all the divs, loop over each one,
we're going to take the div, and we're
going to add.EventListener click,
and when that happens, we're going
to call LogText. This is the one...
You may see me autocompleting this, and
we have this capture?: boolean right here.
That's really what we're going to be
looking at here today, we'll leave that
there for now. So give it a save.
Now, I'm going to click on, and obviously
this purple one is div with a class of
one, the misty rose one is two, and the
coral one is three. So when I click on the
coral one, what is going to log? Don't
cheat, just tell yourself what will
console that log? Click it, three, two,
and one. Wait, I just clicked on the third
one, which is the very most inner one,
but I also console.logged two and one.
That's weird. Well, also if you
console.log this, you'll see the actual
elements themselves, three, two,
and one. So what's going on here?
Well, what is happening is if we go
to our Elements panel here,
and we go to the div that we clicked on,
we clicked on three, but we really also
clicked on two, because it wraps around
it, and we also clicked on one,
we also clicked on the body, we also
clicked on the html tag, we also clicked
on the current tab, and we also clicked on
Google Chrome, and we also clicked on our
OS X operating system, and we also clicked
on the world, and it just keeps zooming
out and out and out. So that's the
concept of something called bubbling,
where the browser will figure out what
you clicked on, but it will also trigger
clicks up every...and they'll ripple
all the way up. So case in point,
if I take document.body and I add the
EventListener of click, and when that
happens, I'm going to logText, and we
have to give our body a class here,
so class="bod". Now watch, I'm
going to click on the coral one,
three, two, one, and bod. So what's
happening is that when you make a click,
it will ripple all the way up to the top
of the document and trigger clicks on
those elements as well. Now, you don't
always see them, because you're not
necessarily listening for a click on those
elements, but if you're listening for
a click on multiple nested elements, in
this case, we're listening for a click on
three, two, one, and bod, then
it's going to trigger a click
on all of those, right there.
So I want to explain to you how this
actually works in JavaScript.
The way that it works in modern
browsers is that the browser will first
do something called a capture, which
means that when you click on the element,
it's going to ripple down. It's going to
say, "Okay, you clicked on the body,
you clicked on one, you clicked on two,
and you clicked on three." So it actually
goes from the top down, and then it
captures all of those events,
and then it starts at the bottom, and then
starts doing something called a bubble.
So the capture goes from top down, and
then the events...the events haven't fired
yet. It just captures where you clicked,
and is storing them. Then it will start to
bubble up, which means that it's
triggering the events as you go up.
So it says, "Okay, we've done figuring out
what you've clicked on all the way down,
now I'm going to start firing off
those click events," on three,
then two, then one, then body, and
anything else you're listening for.
So if we go to our .addEventListener here,
and let's get rid of this document.body
here, after our function [inaudible
00:04:43] a third argument,
which is an options object, and we say
capture is going to be equal to true,
what that will then do is when I click, we
go one, two, three, and what's happening
is that this function, logText, is not
going to get run on the bubble up,
it's going to get run on the capture down.
So we go to the Elements here,
it's going to say, "Oh, they clicked on
one, fire it. They clicked on two,
fire it. They clicked on three, fire it."
So that is what capture means
is that we will run the function on the
way down rather than on the way up.
Now let me put that back to false. By
default, it is false, so that's the normal
version that we have here.
Another thing we have is called stop
propagation. So we just talked about
events bubble up, meaning that if you
click on the innermost one,
it will also trigger an event on the
parent and that parent as well.
However, what you could then do is
you take your event in your function,
and you call e.stopPropagation(),
and what that will do is it will say,
"Stop bubbling this event up. I clicked
the one that I actually wanted."
So now if I go in here, and click on
the middle one, I just see three,
then two, and then one. Why is that?
Because we run... What happens is the
browser starts at the very lowest one,
it runs that function, and then we say
stopPropagation, which essentially means
stop bubbling! and it will no longer
trigger events on the parents on the way
on up. So that's stopPropagation. You can
wrap that in an if statement if
you needed to get the middle one,
or something like that, but that's what
stopPropagation does. You can also use
that in conjunction with your on your way
down, right here, if I were to click on
the middle one, or sorry, if I were to
click on three, what are we going to get
with capture: true and stopPropagation?
Just one. Why? Because capture makes it go
on the way down, one, and then we run
stopPropagation, which stops it from
going down even further.
Last thing I wanted to show you was
something called once, and this is very
new in the browser we have here. So I'm
just going to console.log that propagation
out and bring this capture back to false,
just so we can get our defaults going back
here, three, two, one. We also have an
option called once. If you set that to
true, what will happen is it will listen
for a click and then unbind itself,
and unbinding itself is
the same thing as saying
div.removeEvent.Listener('click', logText.
So it will listen for a click once,
and then unbind itself
so that there's no future clicks on it.
Now if I click on one of these here,
here we go, I'm clicking as many as I can.
It ran once, it fired all those events,
but it will never run again, until I rerun
the page. So that could be helpful if
you have a button. Let's just make
ourselves a quick button here,
and we'll grab it, and you only ever
wanted somebody to click that button once,
we just say button.addEventListener click,
and then when that happens we'll run
a quick function here that just
console.logs click, watch this.
So we've got this button, if I click it
over and over and over and over,
we're going to get it,
but if I were to add that third options
argument here, where we have once
is equal to true, I should only be able
to click this once and never again.
And where I've used that specifically is
in store checkouts, where you do not wish
for someone to click that button more than
once, you can unbind it and stop them from
clicking it multiple times.
So hopefully you learned a few things
there. I know that propagation and
bubbling and capturing, all of those words
used to be very, very confusing to me.
It's not something you use every day, so
it's one of those things where you just
sort of put off from learning, so
hopefully, you spent a couple minutes
and just learned exactly what propagation
and bubbling and all of that stuff does.
Thanks, and I'll see you tomorrow.