Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
A couple of videos ago, we looked at this
really slick nav that Stripe has on its
pricing page and when you hover over top
of it, of course, it shows the dropdown.
But the really cool part about it is that
the background of the dropdown seems to be
able to transform itself from the width
and the height as well as wherever it is
on the page. So its x and its y
coordinates. And when I first saw that, I
was like, "How did they do that?
That's incredible." And what I found out
is that the dropdowns themselves like the
content, the texture, those are separate
elements, but there's this sort of like
little puppy div that follows each of
those dropdowns around and will resize
itself based on wherever it is on the
page. So this white thing that you see
moving, that's the actual background
that's just moving itself around and it's
just sort of absolutely positioned behind
those elements. And we did a really simple
example like that a couple days ago when
we hovered over a link,
we had a little div that would sort of
resize itself and go behind where that
element is. So today, we're going to step
it up a little bit and build something
like this, which is the proof of concept
Stripe navigation. It looks a little bit
different, but it has the same idea where
when you hover over top of one of these
navigation links, it's going to resize
itself, it's going to match the width and
the height of actual content and animate
itself wherever it's going to go or
transition itself wherever it's going to
go. Let's jump in to looking at our html
real quick. We have a nav element right
here and you could give that a class of
top if you like, then you've got a
dropdown background. That's what the white
is going to follow around. You see this
little white dip part?
That's not three separate divs, that's
just one and it's going to follow along
with the content as we go. So that's what
you have and then we have a span with a
class or arrow, which is going to be that
little notch that we have there.
Okay, good, and you noticed that I put
this inside of this nav.
In the last one, we just put it straight
in the body so that we didn't have to
worry about any, like, margin or padding
on top of our nav here.
But in this one, I want to show you how do
you actually deal with this if you're
trying to get the actual position of an
element inside of a nav.
Because it's not always your job to pick
the html, sometimes you have a CMS and
it's going to generate that html for you
and I want to make sure that we're not
just making this as easy as possible and
then you go to implement it in your own
and you're like, "Oh, this is actually a
little bit harder than we actually thought
it was." So we've put it in here just to
show you a different way to do it.
Then we have unordered class with a class
of cool. We have our list items.
These are our lis. We have three of them.
We've got our link and then what's called
the dropdown, and the dropdown can be any
element. In this case,
it's a div that has some info on me. In
this case, it's an unordered list that has
more list items inside of it. But the
important thing is that these lis,
the top level lis, they will be our
triggers. They are the things that are
going to be hovered on them. And the
reason why these lis are going to be the
things that we hover is because if you
hover onto this A link and then you try to
hover into something inside of it like
Twitter, Facebook or blog,
you're technically hovering off the anchor
link and then it would trigger the off and
it would fade itself out. Here what we're
doing is even though my mouse is right
here, I'm still inside of this parent li,
then we've got the second one as well as
the third one. In terms of CSS, there's
not a whole lot going on here.
Most of this is just so it looks half
decent. None of it really has anything to
do with the positioning on the page other
than this position relative right here
that we have. We are going to be writing
the CSS, that is important for ourselves.
First, we need the triggers and those are
those three lis. So let's say,
"const triggers =
document.querySelectorAll" and we'll say
"cool li." And that's going to be all the
direct descendants of that cool,
that are our list item. Then we also need
to grab the dropdown background which is
that white div. We'll call that
"background." Make sure that you use only
query selector here because we don't need
a node list. We need just one element.
And then we'll also do that for our nav
which we put a class of top on.
Then what we want to do is listen for a
hover in and a hover out or a mouse enter
and a mouse leave on each of those list
items. So we're going to make two
functions here called "handle enter" and
we're going to make one called "handle
leave." Then we'll listen for the mouse
enter and the mouse leave and trigger each
of those functions.
[silence]
I'll handle enter on that one then we'll
just duplicate it over and we'll listen
for the mouse leave event, which is going
to trigger our handle leave.
All right, so we just wrote a bit of code
there. Let's make sure that these all
work. So ENTER and LEAVE. Make sure we
didn't get anything wrong here.
Any syntax errors in our console, no, then
you go to your console,
hover over top of them, good. You should
be getting ENTER and LEAVE console logs
whenever you hover in and out of any of
those elements. Good. So next what we need
to do is we need to break this down into
two parts. First part is I just want to
get the contents of the dropdown showing,
meaning that if I hover over this last
one, this ul here, it should show itself.
I'll take the opacity off,
the display none off. You see, there's the
content for each of them.
I want to show whenever I hover over li, I
want to find the dropdown inside of it and
then display it. And the way that's going
to work is we're going to be adding and
removing classes and then leaning on our
CSS to actually do that for us.
So we'll go into our handle enter function
here, and we will grab this.
What is this? This is the list item. I'm
going to put the class on the list item
.classlist.add and we'll say,
trigger-enter. And then what we want to do
is also add a class of
trigger-enter-active after 150
milliseconds. And this is going to become
more clear as to why I've done this when
we get into the second part, which is
.follow along div. So I'm going to say set
timeout. We are going to... I'm going to
show a little trick here with arrow
functions, I'm going to use a normal
function here and then I'm going to say,
after 150 milliseconds, this.classList.add
trigger-enter-active.
Now this isn't going to work. Why not?
Cannot read property add of undefined.
So it cannot find class list of this and
why is that? If you console log this,
it gives you window and you probably have
like, "Yeah, Wes, you showed me this in
your ES6 course, I understand it now."
When you enter into a function,
the value of this changes. However, if you
change that into an arrow function,
the value of this is inherited from the
parent function, which is going to be
exactly what we want. Good. So we can make
this into a nice little short one-liner
arrow function here. There we go. Does
this still work? Good, got it.
So we've got this.classList.add
trigger-enter-active. Then we want to go
into our CSS, so scroll up and this is why
I've included the CSS in the file for you
here because it's actually a bit long.
It'd be better suited towards a separate
CSS file, and we'll find our dropdown
which is here, and you'll notice that the
way that I show the dropdown is with both
I hit it with opacity zero and displayed
none. And the reason why I've done that is
because you cannot go from opacity zero to
one as well as display none to display
block. That's a bit of a pain,
but what we're going to do is we're sort
of going to step it where when we have
trigger-enter, our dropdown is going to be
display block, but it's still going to be
opacity one. And I'll show you opacity
one. See, that will just immediately show
it, but I want it to sort of transition
itself in, which is why we have this here.
So, what I want to do is not put the
opacity there but after a second,
we're going to have this class of
trigger-enter-active. So watch this.
See how they after 150 milliseconds, we
get that second one and then when it has a
class of trigger-enter-active, because it
was already shown with the display block
just a split second earlier, then we go
into our opacity and set it to be one.
And this is how, if you've ever used
animations in either react or angular,
this is how animations or transitions work
inside of those frameworks.
They just apply two separate classes when
something enters or leaves and then you
can use your CSS just to do that sort of
staged move there. So now if we give it a
save and refresh, it looks like it's not
showing opacity one, because I need to say
.dropdown. Ah, there we go. See how they
animate themselves in or transition
themselves in? And then, of course, on the
other side of things,
we can go into our LEAVE and we simply
just need to duplicate that one and we
will just remove the class of
trigger-enter and then I'm going to do it
all in one shot. I'm not going to animate
it out. We'll say, "trigger-enter-active."
Good. You see these things are nice fading
in. So that's a lot of JavaScript just to
do something that CSS can do out of the
box, but the next piece and the reason why
we need to do this with JavaScript, is
because the next piece is that we're going
to figure out how big is this ul with a
class of dropdown and then can that little
white div go behind it so we get this
little animation that we have here?
So let's go here. The first thing we need
to do is get that white thing on the page
and that white thing is our background.
It's what we have right here.
So we'll say "background.classList.add"
and it's going to have a class of open and
then just duplicate that and remove it on
our LEAVE. So now we should look at our
dropdown background here and then when you
hover over top of one of them,
you should also add a class of open. So if
we go into our CSS,
we see it here. When our dropdown
background also has a class of open let's
say, opacity one. Ah, you see? See that
the little white guy in the corner is
showing itself? Makes sense. So now we
need to do, which is really the heavy
lifting, is to figure out, okay, we have
this dropdown, just Twitter or Facebook
blog course catalog, how wide, how high
and where on the page do you live so that
we can take this white thing and move it
on over to where that exists.
So we're going to go down here below where
we did all those class lists and first
thing that we need to do is figure out
what that dropdown actually is.
So we'll say, "const dropdown =
this.querySelector." Now we're going to be
looking for a dropdown. You might be
asking yourself, like, "Why didn't we do
that up here [[00:012:01]] with our nav?"
Well, you can't do that here because
there'ss three different dropdowns and it
needs to be dynamic.
You need to find the one dropdown that
exists inside of the thing that got
hovered. So if we console.log that
dropdown, go to our console here.
You should now see that we get a different
dropdown in the console whenever we hover.
Good. So we can then take the coordinates
from that just like we did in the previous
one. We'll say, "const dropdownCoords =
dropdown.getBoundingClientRect" Put those
together. Let's just console.log
dropdownCoords, we're going to save.
So you see what's happening here is that
we get information about where on the page
from the bottom, the left, the top, the
right and the width is that actual item.
Now the other thing is that we need to get
information about where the nav is because
you cannot assume that this nav tag is
always going to be the first thing on the
page. You might have an h2 that says
"hello" and when that happens,
you bump everything down. And this
information, it gives you information
relative to where on the page it is,
absolutely on the page, and it doesn't
take these things into account. So what
we'll need to do is then grab the
coordinates for the nav as well. So go
down, down, down "const navCoords =
nav.getBoundingClientRect." We should also
have the coordinates for the nav and the
reason why I do that on every single time,
something might change,
sometimes you have a banner that opens and
closes. We can't assume that it's always
going to be the same on page load as it is
when you hover. You got these nav coords
as well, let's console log those. Good.
We've got that. And then what we need to
do is figure out where are the coords for
everything, so we're going to put those
two coordinates that we just got together
"const coords =" and then the height is
just going to be equal to the
dropdownCoords.height and the width is
also going to be "dropdownCoords.width."
Let's just stop it there and work with the
width and the height before we get any
further. Now that we have the width and
the height here, we can just take our
background which is that white thing.
We can set the style and we'll say,
".setProperty" and we're going to set the
property, the width to be, coords.width
and we're also going to do that with the
height. And that doesn't seem to be
working, how come? Because you need to
give it pixels, so you could just wrap
these suckers in a template string and add
px to the end and that should do it for
us. Ah, look at this. So when you hover
it, it will know how big and how wide that
actual element is and that's another
reason why we do that sort of two stage
adding trigger-enter and
trigger-enter-active so that when you
enter it, even though it's not shown on
the page, it's display block and we're
able to get these bounding client rects
from it. Because otherwise if it was
hidden, you can't tell the width and the
height of a hidden element, so it needs to
be on the page even if it's visibly not
there with opacity. So we've got our width
and our height and the reason why that is
animating itself if we go up to our CSS
here, you see this dropdown background?
I have a transition of the opacity is half
a second and then everything else is 0.3
seconds that translates to 0.2 seconds. So
if I make that two seconds and make this
one three seconds, the width and the
height will just take two seconds to
actually grow, but you want that to be
nice and short and you can kind of play
around with how nicely that goes. Good.
That's working. And the last piece of the
puzzle is actually working with the top
and the left values. So if we go back down
here, let's say the top is going to be
let's just say "dropdownCoords.top" and
the left is going to be the same thing and
then we are to go down here and set our
transform because this is a CSS property.
It's going to be...normally,
it would be a translate and we will give
it our x and our y, but in our case,
it's going to be "coords.left.px,
coordsTop" then give that a save.
Seems to be working, but if I were to go
up here, again, just do what we did before
and maybe put like "h2," say like "cool."
Now see how everything is messed up?
And that's because the coordinates that we
get are off a little bit because that
navigation is pushed down. So you can't
always assume that everything is going to
be anchored to the top of the actual page.
And that's why we went ahead and grabbed
this nav coordinates right here because we
need to take our dropdown coords and then
offset them with the top nav. So if the
top nav is 30 pixels, we know it's been
bumped down 30 pixels, so the value the
top of this white box needs to be moved up
30 pixels and same for the left
navCoords.left. And those two values are
just going to offset them and it's going
to perfectly put itself...a-ha,
buttery smooth you've got it going on.
This is probably the hardest part.
That took me a while to figure out, when
you have something nested inside of it,
these values don't care and you need to do
the math yourself. That's one that jQuery
did really nice for you. If you ever use
.offset inside of jQuery,
you didn't have to worry about it because
it did all the math behind the scenes for
you there. Other than that, working really
nicely for us, there is one little thing
where if you sort of go bananas on it,
take the nav, the ul, open this up.
You see, like why is there
trigger-enter-active here? And if you,
like, really mess with it, like, go really
quickly, you'll see like okay sometimes
you see the content before you actually
get to it. And then if you mess with it,
sometimes you're going to end up with
active here and what's happening is that
it's the set time up here. Immediately
when we enter, we're going to add a class
of trigger-enter and then 150 milliseconds
later, we're going to enter
trigger-enter-active. But sometimes I'm
already hovering off before this is even
added. So there's a bit of problem here
where you try to remove the active one
before it's ever been added, so you run
the remove and then a little bit later,
you actually add it on. That's a bit of a
pain. So what we want to do is take this
function that we're running here, put that
into its own and we'll say if
this.classList contains trigger-enter,
then we want to add a class of active and
then you can see it. You can just go crazy
with it and you'll see that you're never
seeing the content too early because that
active one is never being added and you
never see them on here. Another way that I
like to write it is it's a little bit
shorter where I'm going to take it back to
what we have here, take that,
take the statement out, take this block
out that we had here, bring it back to
that arrow function and what you can do is
you say, this.classList that contains
trigger-enter and this class.add. And
that's sort of short circuiting this where
if this is true, then this will run. If
this is false, then it doesn't bother
checking the second one. So it's a bit of
a hack there where you take advantage of
this Boolean and. But that means that the
add will never run unless it actually
contains trigger enter. It's just like the
if statement that we have there in things.
Oh no, I broke it! Token, we got too many
tokens. Is it that one?
Maybe, yes, there we go,
working nicely for us. So hopefully,
you enjoyed that one. I really liked it. I
think that the people that work at Stripe
they have...if you look into it, if you
noticed like when just hover into it,
they have this, like, really cool sort of
fold down effect that they have going on
and I think that their code is probably
six or seven times as large as this.
But if this is something that you love
working with, which is coordinates and
timing and all of that, I would definitely
encourage you to try and make that little
fold down animation work as well. Thanks
so much and I will see you tomorrow.
♪ [music] ♪