Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
Today we're going to learn how to do click
and drag from scratch.
This is an effect that I saw on this
website Hover States. I scroll down to the
bottom here and I noticed that
you can scroll this if you want,
it's just a horizontally scrolling div,
which is kind of cool because it works
without Javascript. However, you can also
take your cursor, click and drag as you
want to go through it and I thought that
was kind of a cool effect.
So, that's what I would like to do here is
when you click, drag your mouse and go
somewhere, we want it to sort of come
along with it and this whole mouse event
and mouse positioning stuff, I find it to
be a little bit complicated,
so I thought that this would be a really
nice exercise to get us comfortable with
what's going on here. So, pretty simple,
what we've got going on here,
we've got our style that's CSS, I've added
some sort of fun CSS to it,
like when you click it, we add a class of
active and it will bring it up a little
bit. And then I also used this rotate y
and a perspective, so that when you move
it, you see how 17 is "oh, I can barely
see it, oh, now it's totally looking at
us." Just some fun stuff, it has nothing
to do with it other than it looks pretty.
So, let's go down to our script here. And
really what we want to be doing here is
selecting the items, which is this white
box right here and then we're going to be
listening for a number of different
events. So, when I first click down,
we're gonna add a class of active and
we're gonna figure out where did I click
down. Then when I move my mouse
either to the left or to the right,
we're gonna figure out okay, let's say if
I click right here. This is 500 px and if
I scroll to the left, 20 px, we know that
we should scroll the div 20 pixels.
If I scroll to the right 20 pixels, we
know that we should scroll the div 20
pixels that way. And that's really how
it's going to work, we're just going to
anchor it down as soon as we click and
then depending on how far either way we
scroll, that's how much we're going to be
scrolling the div or we can do it a
multiple of that, if you'd like for the
scrolling to go a little bit bigger.
It's just a combination of mouse down,
mouse leave, mouse out,
up and mouse move. So, let's first go
ahead and grab the sliders so we say const
sliders equals document.query
selector. We are going to look for the
item, that's the white div that surrounds
everything. And then we need a couple of
variables, they're all gonna be let
because they're gonna be updated.
So we're going to say let is down, to
build a false. That's gonna be our flag
variable, that's either gonna be true or
false, depending on if I'm clicking or if
I'm not. And then we also need one
called start x and scroll left, so we say
let start x and let scroll left. You'll
notice how I'm not assigning any values to
them, because that's gonna be happening in
our events. And we'll understand exactly
what these are in just a second. Then what
we need to do is attach a whole bunch of
different listeners, so we're gonna be
working with mouse down,
mouse leave, mouse up and mouse move.
And I've paced these in here.
And we're gonna listen for an event on
each of them, so we're just gonna say
slider.add event listener. And you can
farm these off to separate functions.
I'm gonna do them in line just because
right now I think it's important that we
attach the code that is happening
directly to the event. However,
once you're done it would be great to
refactor those out into separate functions
and then just pass them into your event
listener, like we've been doing with a lot
of our videos so far. We've got mouse down
mouse leave, mouse up and mouse move.
So first let's handle the is down that's
happening. So when someone mouses down,
we're gonna take this is down variable,
set it to true. When someone leaves,
so if I'm dragging here, and then
I leave this thing and come back,
it shouldn't work because what happens is
someone leaves, they come back,
they let go and then they come back here
and it's still in the down state,
so what we need to then do is to take this
is down and set that to be false.
When someone mouses up, we want
to set that to be false as well.
And then in mouse move, that's where all
of our magic is going to happen,
so let's just inside of that, console log
is down. And then we're gonna console log
do work. Open that up, open up your
console, I want to see what's going on
here. And you see like, I'm console
logging a lot here and I haven't even
clicked anything. This console logging
shouldn't show anything at all unless I'm
actually mouse down. And if I click it
and mouse around me says true,
true, true, I let go, false, false, false.
So what we want to do first thing here is
in our mouse move, we'll say if is not
down, we are just going to return.
And what that will do is stop the function
from running and then this console log is
down and do work won't get logged unless
you're clicked in the click state.
Here we go, let go, let me clear this out.
See I'm moving around,
nothing, nothing, nothing? Click down,
move around, it starts to work.
Let go, there's no updated. And we could
console.log, if you change that to
console.count and just to see how many
times that happens. None, none, none,
drag, drag, drag, good. Then it stops,
then it goes again. Good,
so we have that mouse down. Next thing I
want to do is we'll take the slider.
When you mouse down. We're
gonna take slider.add event listener.
Nope. We'll take the slider, class
list.add, active, then we'll also do that
the opposite when someone leaves, so
remove, and then once my mouse is up,
it'll also remove class of act, good.
So now when you click it,
you see it get a little bit of effect
there. Why is that happening?
That's happening because if you look
at our style, that CSS.
When we have a class of active,
I just change the background,
I change the cursor. You have to change it
to... I didn't even know you had to
vendor prefix cursor, it's been a
while since I've seen that.
And then transform the scale up to one, so
it goes from 98 percent to one.
It just gives you a little bit of a cool
effect that goes in and out.
Now let's think about how this is going to
work. When I click down here and I drag 20
pixels to the left or 20 pixels to the
right, we need to know where that anchor
point is when I scroll to the left or to
the right. Because as many times as I move
around, until I unclick or mouse up, we
need to know where that initial click down
was. And that's what that start x variable
is for, where we created right here.
So when someone clicks down, before they
start moving to the left or to the right,
we need to record where they did that
initial click down. That's going to happen
in our mouse down here. And we're going to
go up to our function and past the event.
Now, if we're to console log that event,
let's see what information we get on
there. Yeah, I got the mouse event,
I got all kinds of information.
Client x, client y, etc., etc. One way to
tell where we clicked inside of it and
we've done a couple of different ways in
this series is to console log e.page x.
And then it's going to tell us exactly
three, nine, six. It's telling us exactly
what the x coordinates on the actual page.
However, if there was some margin in
between this item here, like margin 50 px.
If we really brought it out,
then that would be off. We need to know
where did they click inside of this thing,
not on the page. So we just take
start x is equal to e.page x,
but then we'll attract the slider.offset
left and that will just offset it.
If there's 50 px of margin in between the
page and the item that we care about,
then subtracting it will handle that
offset for us. So then we can console log
start x and if I click here, we should
get a really low number, 18.
If I click over here, we'll get a high
number, good. Then,
what's important about that is when we
move our mouse, we should be able to
console log start x over and over. See
it's 645 regardless of where I'm moving my
actual cursor here, that's pretty cool.
And then when I let go,
we don't really care about it. We click
again, now it's 547, we care about that.
The other thing we need to log at
the time of click is the scroll.
Because let's say I'm scrolled 200
pixels in and then I want to
scroll to the left and to the right of
this div. Then we need to figure out
where the initial scroll was when we
started it. And that's what this other
variable is for, which is scroll left.
So we'll take this, we'll say scroll
left is equal to slider.scroll left.
And the reason why we're going to
keep that in a variable is because it's
going to move. If I go to the
answer here, it's going to move,
but we always need to go back
to that initial state when it started,
when you did that first click down. We got
our start x and we got our scroll left,
we can take these console logs out of
here. Good. Now we'll go down to our mouse
move and start doing the work. So first of
all, I'd like to take the event and then
just call an e.prevent default on it. And
that will stop any selecting of text
that's inside of there or any of the
sliding to the left or any other weird
stuff that the browser might think you're
actually trying to select some text,
that will stop it for us. Then what we
need to do is figure out where the cursor
is when they moved it. We already know
where the cursor is when they initially
clicked down, but we want to know where
the cursor is when they move it to the
left and to the right. So we'll say const
x is equal to e.page x minus slider.offset
left. That's the exact same code that we
just used up here. Here we're using it to
say where did they initially click and
here we're going to recalculate every
single time that we move the mouse. So now
if we just console.log x as well as what
was that other one called here? Start x.
And a little tip here, if you want to know
what those variables are, just throw them
in an object and you'll see the values.
Now, when I click in the middle here, you
see that the x value is changing and the
start x is not changing at all. So we can
simply then take that and I'm going to
call that the wok. Const wok is equal to,
we'll take the x value and subtract the
start x. And this is going to tell us how
far have we deviated from that initial
space. Console log wok, get rid of that
initial console log and now we're seeing,
ah, look at that! So I'm going to click
here. I'm going to move 20 pixels to the
right. So we've gone 20 pixels to the
right. Then I'm going to go back and 20
pixels to the left gives me negative. So
it's telling us, how far have we deviated
from that initial point, which we could
put like a red dot there when you clicked,
because then you can see exactly how far
to the left and to the right you are
working. So next up, what we need to
actually do is change this div here to
scroll and we do that with a scroll left
property. So we'll say slider.scroll left
is equal to...now you might think,
okay, we'll just set it to wok and
let's see what that does for us.
It kind of works, but it's really jumpy.
And the problem is that is we're
recalculating the scroll left every single
time. So the reason why we captured the
scroll left value when we did that initial
click is so we could reference it inside
of this function. So we'll take
slider.scroll left, set it to the scroll
left value, which is what we initially
captured, we've put it in a variable
and then we minus the wok value.
We give that a save here and now we should
be able to click and drag beautifully back
and forth. If you feel like this is a lot
of work just to get over,
what you can then do is put this in
parenthesis and then multiply it by like
three or something. So for every pixel
moved, you're gonna scroll the slider
three pixels. There you get a bit of a
nice slider effect as we're going on in
there. So I think that's it for what we've
got going on here, looking pretty good.
It's a simple ISH code, however actually
building this the first time took me
a while to understand. "Oh, you need to
put these variables, you need to capture
them at the time of your mouse down and
then reference them whenever someone
moves the mouse." So hopefully you
enjoyed that. Obviously there's a lot more
to libraries, if you take a look at this
one right here, you can just flick it
and you don't have to worry. It really
gives me appreciation for people who
build bouncy scrolling and inertial
scrolling, you see how like it fades
out at the end. There's a lot of math that
goes into building these different
libraries. But it's really important to
know how they're working under the hood
in case you ever wanted
to build your own.
I should also note that with this mouse
down, mouse leave, mouse up,
mouse move dance that we've done here, you
can also implement your own drag and drop,
so if that's something you're interested
in doing, I would challenge you to do
that. Thanks a lot, I'll see you tomorrow.
♪ [music] ♪