Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
Today we are going to be taking two of the
things that we've done in the past,
which is working with mouse move events
and second working with HTML5 video.
And we're going to sort of put them
together. We are going to mash them into
our colab. So this is just an idea that
I've had. I don't know if it's totally a
great idea but I know that it was a fun
thing to build regardless.
So I run a video site where I've got a lot
of people watching my videos,
and I'm always thinking about how do I
make the viewing experience a little bit
better? So one thing that a lot of
developers like to do is they don't watch
their videos at 1x. They watch them at
like 1.5 or 2 or like they like to speed
it up and slow it down depending on how
quickly or how boring,
or how exciting something is, or how
important something is.
So what I really wanted to do here is just
experiment with a new sort of input that
would control how fast the video goes so
that rather than you having to click up
and down to change the video speed, you
can sort of just like DJ it here as you're
watching the video to go slower and
faster. So I'm just going to give you a
little play here. And then chipmunk, and
then you slow it down.
So you see what's going on here. As I move
this, like the lowest is going to be 0.5x
or 0.4x and then the highest is going to
be all the way up to 4x.
And then as you mouse over or as you click
and drag, depending on how you like to do
your interface, we are just changing that
value and then it's indirectly going to be
setting the playback rate on this video.
So let's jump into it.
This won't be too big of a one. So far
what I've done is I've selected the speed,
which is the entire white bar here, and
then we have the speed bar which is going
to be the field in here or with that sort
of blue gradient right here.
And then I've just got a video sort of
playing here streaming off of Dropbox.
Hopefully it doesn't get shut down.
So it's a lot of bandwidth.
And then I've got a video element here,
which is the actual video here.
Now, I'm going to take auto play off just
for our sanity's sake so it doesn't keep
playing every single time. And then what
happens is when you hover over top of this
we are going to change the playback rate
as well as update the actual visual.
So let's do the visual part first and then
we'll work on the playback rate.
So first thing we need to do is take our
speed and add the event listener of mouse
move. And when that happens we'll have a
function. I'm using a proper function here
because I need this to be equal to the
video itself. Sorry, not the video,
the actual speed bar when you mouse over
it. And cool. In that function pass
yourself the event and then let's just
console log the event when you mouse over
it. Open that sucker up in your browser
and you should see this video that we've
got going on and our thing. Now when I
start hovering over top of it,
you will now see all the different events
that we have going on it.
So first of all we need to get where like
this is going to be zero pixels and this
is going to be however high it is. Let's
talk look look look- 410,
so that's going to be 410
pixels. So how do we get that?
We'll say cons y is equal to and we'll do
the same thing we did in the last video,
e dot page y and we are going to take the
offset of this, dot offset top.
Why? Because we can't assume that this bar
is going to be at the top of it.
There might be padding, or merging or
anything or another element in-between it.
So let's console log y, see what we've got
there. There we go.
You see at the top, you're getting zero.
All the way at the bottom we are getting
around 410. So that's showing us how far
along we are. We want to turn that into a
percentage. So if this is a 410 pixel, if
I go to 205 pixels, right around here,
that should be 50%. Let's say const
percent is equal to let's take y divided
by this dot offset height. That's a way to
get the height of the actual one that we
have there. So let's console log the
percent. There we go. So that is a one.
That is zero. And we could bump those up
to get to what we want.
Then we also need a min and a max because
want this to be 0.4 and this to be 4,
right? So how do we do that? I would say
const min equals 0.4 and const.
Max is equal to, I don't know, max is
equal to 4x or whatever you think the
crazy upper bound. Then what we do is
we'll make a height variable and we're
going to set that to...the percentage
right now is like 0.99 and we want to turn
that into 99%. Take our percent variable,
multiply it by a hundred and then we'll
wrap that sucker in, I thought, round. And
then add percent to the end and console
log the height. See what we've got here.
All right. So now we actually are getting
a full percentage that we're looking for
rather than a zero point something
whatever, and then we'll take our bar
which is the speed bar, a bar,
that style. The height is equal to height.
Look at this. So so far,
we've got it up and going. Looks good.
Next thing we need to do is update that
number that's inside of there, and the way
that we do that is we will then calculate
what the playback rate is. Let's say const
playback rate is going to be equal to.
This is going to be a bit of a weird one
because we don't want the minimum to be
zero and the maximum to be one. That's not
the playback rate. At a 0% height,
it should be 0.4x and at a 100% height it
should be 4x. So we sort of need to do a
little bit of math to get that lower and
upper bounds. And the way that you do that
is you take your percent and you multiply
that by the max minus the min plus the
min. And that's sort of how you can offset
your height. We did that in a couple of
videos ago when we were doing the
tech shot at one when you
needed to hover negative 50 and plus 50,
not 0 to 100. And that's just a neat way
that we can do that.
We have that playback rate and we can take
our bar and set the text content to be
that playback rate. See here.
So you see it's just like a crazy number.
So we can take that and just run dot two
fixed on it and just give us two decimal
places. There we go and then you can tack
on your little x or something onto the
end. So plus x or you could use a template
string to pop up that in. Looking pretty
snazzy. Last thing we need to do is
actually to take that playback rate that
we have here, console log,
playback rate. Let's see what we got going
on here. Three point five.
We've got to take that value and apply it
to our video. So let's say video dot
playback rate. And what playback rate is,
take a look at it in our console here,
video dot playback rate. One is just
normal speed. So two is equal to,
if we were to play it ourselves...ten. The
audio stops at some point.
Four, zero point two. The audio stops at a
very slow amount as well.
Like 0.5 is as low as you can get it.
Sounds like I'm just wasted trying to
teach you Flexbox. So video dot playback
rate equals playback rate.
And don't worry about those long
percentage. I know some people are irked
when you have like very long decimal
places but it won't be issue there.
Now we'll give it a play. Looks good. Nice
and fast. Slow. Fantastic.
So that was kind of cool. We did there is
we both calculated the height as well as
attached the playback rate. If you don't
like doing both your presentation and your
functionality in a single function, you
could shell that off to two separate
functions which you would just then call
from your mass move event right here and
then also we could take this function out
and call it handle move and then up here
we'll make a function or replace that
function. We'll call it a handle move.
Then you're just going to hook that up to
mouse move but maybe you'll also want to
hook it up to touch move or any other
event that you wanted. Got that.
Still works wonderfully. Excellent.
So hopefully you enjoyed that
and I will see you tomorrow.
♪ [music] ♪