Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
Today we are creating a countdown timer
that will show us how many seconds
are left in some sort of task, like
you've got a quick 5-minute break,
or you have a 15-minute break,
or you've got a lunch break going on.
You need to be able to click these
buttons or you can put in the number
of minutes that you'd like.
It's going to count it down as well as
show you what time to be back.
This is just because when I teach,
we have breaks and people need to know how
long a break is left and they always ask
me, "Hey, Wes, how much time is left in
the break?" And I say, "I'm not your dad."
Then we built something so we could
stop asking that question.
We want to first go into our scripts here,
and I'm just going to make a function
called timer, and we're just going to
work in the console to start.
Then what we are going to do
is update this actual interface here.
I'm going to make a function called timer.
That's going to take in the number of
seconds you wish for the timer to be in.
And then we are going to do two things.
Now, how do timers work? You have the
amount of time that you wish for it to
have, and then you simply elapse that time
over however many seconds it is.
In the past what I've done is I would just
set an interval, which has a function and
that function itself, let's get rid of all
this junk, it would run every second and
then what I would do is I would just say,
seconds, minus, minus.
Then it would just decrement the amount of
seconds every single time.
However, I did run into issues with that
because said interval does not run
sometimes. I found sometimes when I tab
away for a long time, it would simply just
stop running it. I don't know if the
browser does something funky there with
pausing its intervals when it's not
necessarily running. Then I also found on
iOS, when you are scrolling,
it will pause all of your intervals.
I think it does that for performance
issues as well as making your scrolling
nice and buttery smooth. Similar to how,
if you scroll a page,
your animated gifs will also stop.
So it's not really a good use case there,
because if I were to be scrolling for
10 seconds, then it would add an extra
10 seconds onto the break. So rather than
doing that, we will use an interval but in
a different way. What we want to do is
figure out when the timer started,
just const now equals date.now. That's
kind of a new one to the browser.
Previously we had to do like, new date and
then get time but there's a new static
method on date called now, and that will
just give us the current timestamp in
milliseconds. Then we also want then,
which is now plus the number of seconds
that you wish to run the timer for, but
that now is going to be in milliseconds
and seconds is obviously in seconds.
So we just multiply that by 1000.
So it's console log, now and then just to
see what we've got going on here.
If I were to refresh this, run timer 10,
you see our now and our then values that
we have here. Good, so those are working
for us. Next thing we need to do is every
single second, we need to display the
amount of time left. This is where we set
an interval. This is okay to use an
interval here because we're really not
worried about it running every single
second if something happens.
But like, let's say it were to skip two
seconds. It would just update two seconds
later and show us those two less seconds
rather than one. So, it's fine to use it
here, we are going to run it every second,
which is 1000 milliseconds here.
Then what we need to figure out is
how much time is left on the clock.
We'll take our then, which is when it
stops, we'll say const seconds left is
equal to then minus and we can't just say
now because that was captured when it ran,
but we need to run date.now once more.
Again, now it's going to be in
milliseconds so we want to divide that
by 1000 so we can get seconds.
Console log seconds left. Let's see what
we got here. Eight and a half,
seven, six, five, so we have a bit of
a rounding error here. Oh,
that's a bit of a funky one. I guess just
because we're dealing with milliseconds
and doing this division here, so you can
wrap the entire thing in the math.round.
Then run it at ten, nine, there we go. You
may have just seen that it started going
negative after awhile. And why is that?
Because intervals don't know when to stop
themselves. So what we need to do here is
before we display it, we need to check if
we should stop it. How do you stop? I'll
say if the seconds left is less or equal
to zero, then we want to stop it. So,
obviously, we could return which will stop
the function from running, but that's
not really going to help us,
and I'll show you here. That's not going
to totally stop this interval from
running, it's just going to run but not
show us anything. What we need to do is to
store this interval in its own variable.
I'm going to go up here and say let
countdown and that's going to be
our sort of higher-level variable.
In this case, it's a global variable,
it's going to live on the window,
but you could pop that into IFFE and not
have it in the global name space.
Then here we're going to simply update it.
Countdown is equal to.
Then here we will call clear interval and
pass it the name of our timer which is
countdown. Then when we run it,
let's run it with three seconds left,
two, one, and then it will never
run again because we hit this here.
Real quick aside, sorry that I have to
jump in here though, but I said less or
equal to, but that ends up with leaving us
one second. Obviously we want less than
zero seconds, which is going to give us
two, one and zero. Not less or equal to,
just less. All right, back to scheduled
programming. Now, one other issue that we
are running into is if I run 10 seconds,
watch what happens. Only after one second
elapses does it actually run. The
problem with that is that set interval,
what we have right here, that does not run
immediately. It has to wait for the first
second to elapse. So what I want to do is,
we'll create a second function down here
called display time left which takes in
seconds. Here we're going to console log
the number of seconds left, and we're
going to change that to minutes and
whatnot. Down here, instead of console
logging it, we're going to display it
which it should still do the same thing,
still after a second.
But then we could also run that
as soon as the function is invoked.
We'll run display time left and we'll
pass it seconds. We're going to run it
immediately once, and then once again,
every single time that we do that
interval. Here we go, a timer. See? It
does 10 immediately and then we'll count
down from 9 to 6, all the way down to 1.
Good, so this little countdown function
that we've written here is looking pretty
good, now I want to go down into our
display time left and start working with
converting it to minutes and seconds.
In a previous video, what we did is we
took all of our seconds and converted it
to seconds, minutes, and hours. You can
go grab that code right now if you'd like.
Or if you want a little bit of practice,
figure it out yourself.
We're only going to do minutes and seconds
here, but you are welcome to do hours as
well. So I'll say, const minutes is equal
to seconds divided by 60 and let's just
console what we have left. If I were to
run 70, we have 1.16 minutes left,
1.13. So what's going on here with that?
Well, that's because we only want whole
minutes. We don't care about those
remainders here. So we'll say math.floor,
we'll grab the lower bound of that number.
And now if I were to run,
let's do 124 seconds. So, two minutes, two
minutes and then eventually it should get
to one whole minute, there we go. Now
we're worried about how many seconds are
left. So I say const remainderSeconds and
that is going to be seconds mod 60 and mod
will give us the remainder that we have.
Minutes and remainderSeconds timer,
Here we go, three, two, one. That goes
down to 1 minute and 59 seconds.
Good. So we've got our minutes in our
remainderSeconds, now we can start
working with our HTML. We've got
this display time left div here.
If we were to put that in a variable,
const timer display is equal to
document.querySelector. We want to look
for that. Then we'll go down here and
create another variable which is
going to be our display time,
which is going to look something like
11:11, right? How do we get the number of
minutes left? Simply just
minutes: number of remainderSeconds.
Then we take our timerDisplay which is
our div, we set the textContent to be
display. We can get rid of this console
log because now we're dealing with actual
DOM elements here. If I were to run it,
oh, I spelled it wrong. Minutes.
Minutsas. Now we run it. Oh, okay, kind of
working but you see what the problem is
here? When you have less than 10 seconds
left, it just says 4 seconds,
but we should be 04 seconds left. How do
we do that? Well, we could go to this
remainderSeconds, and we'll say if the
remainderSeconds is greater than 10,
or sorry, less than 10, then we want to
return a zero. It's a question mark,
this is a shorthand ternary operator, and
otherwise, we're just going to return
nothing. And that will give us a zero.
And then, finally, on the end here,
you can just give us the remainderSeconds
left. So if we run it now,
with 124 seconds, we have that padded zero
on the front until it gets there.
Another thing is we should update
the tab on our browser here,
it just says countdown timer. We can
simply just say document.title.
Document.title is the title tag in your
HTML, is equal to display.
Now we're going to run it. Here we go.
It updates it as we're updating it.
You can put that really wherever it is
that you like. Now I want to work on that
other function which is showing the ending
time. If it's 2:30 and you have a
five-minute break, I want to say be back
at 2:35. We'll create a function called
displayEndTime. That's going to take in
a timestamp of when you want to finish.
That's our then time right here. Takes in
a timestamp and we got to turn that
timestamp into a date. Const end equals
new date. You want to pass it the
timestamp. Why? If you've never worked
with timestamps before, this is how they
work. You have date.now which is just a
number of milliseconds since January 1st,
1970. That's when God created the earth.
That's the number of milliseconds that has
elapsed since that amount of time. Now, if
you were just to take this and then put it
in a string and then come back to
JavaScript, you'd be like, "Okay,
I need to convert this back into a date."
You say new date and you pass it the
number of milliseconds that you have.
It's going to convert that.
It's December 1st right now, convert it
into a proper timestamp for you.
What's cool about that is you
could put it in a variable called X
and then you can call
X.getDate, X.getDay, X.getMonth,
and you get all the information about
what day and month and all that.
That's a proper date. That takes
in a timestamp. We create a new date
object from that. Then we can simply just
get the hours. We'll say const hour equals
end.getHours and const minutes is equal to
end.getMinutes, then we'll say end-time
which we don't have that yet.
Let's go back up to the top here.
What is our end time? Display end time.
Grab that sucker, const endTime is equal
to document.querySelector. We'll grab
the thing with the class of display,
end-time. Okay, so we got this
endTime.textContent is equal to,
and I'm just going to set it here.
Previously, we put it in a variable called
display. Why? Because I needed to use it
more than once. I needed to use it to
update the title, as well as update the
text content. But in this case I just want
to do it directly inside of here. We'll
say "Be Back At" and then we will grab the
hour and we will grab the minutes. That
easy, right? No, it's not going to be that
easy, but let's give it a shot. In our
timer, we're not going to run this in our
interval, it doesn't need to be updated
every second, it just needs to happen once
when you run the timer. So, simply
just displayEndTime, you pass it then,
which is the endTime. So if I were to
run our timer with, I don't know,
3,000 seconds to pass it into it, we got
50 minutes left. But the problem here
is that I am not European, and I do not
understand what 15:00 is.
I do know that I should be back at 3:11.
So we need to then, go in here,
and if you're European, congratulations.
You can leave this part and maybe go get a
pop or something like that. But we
Canadians and Americans and whoever else
is normal needs to go into this hour and
we'll say, if the hour is greater than 12,
then we need to return the hour minus 12,
otherwise we want to just return the hour.
And if this is a little bit too funky for
you, you can simply just go in here and
create a new variable const adjusted hour
is equal to, we'll return the hour minus
12. So, if it is 13:00, take away 12, it
is 1:00 and take that adjusted hour and
put it here, so how's that looking?
Okay, be back at 3:12, good.
But what if I were to run it with
2700 seconds? Be back at 3:07,
so we got the trailing minutes again.
If the minutes is less than 10,
then return a 0 otherwise return nothing.
And then we'll tack the minutes onto the
end again. Be back at 3:07. Beautiful.
Okay, so we've got our timer working,
our function is working, it's updating,
displaying, and everything.
Last thing that we need to do now is hook
it up to all of these different buttons as
well as our minutes here. If we look at
our HTML, you'll see that each of these
buttons here, has a data-time and the
number of seconds we wish to run it on it.
And then we have a form here which is a
custom number of minutes, not seconds.
Let's deal with these buttons, we'll knock
them off first. We'll go in here and first
we'll select all of those, so say, const
buttons equals all. And you want to select
anything with a data-time. Not just a
button, it might be a picture,
it might be something else, anything
that has a data-time attribute.
When that happens, we'll go down here and
we'll say buttons for each button,
button.addEventListener, we want to listen
for a click, and when that happens,
we could run a function
called startTimer.
We'll go here, we'll make a function
called startTimer and we will
simply just console log this.
Okay, let's see what we got here.
Twenty seconds button, got it. How did we
get this data-time out?
Well, this.dataset will give us
an object with the time on it.
This.dataset.time will give us
a string of the number of minutes.
So we can just put that into a variable,
const seconds is equal to
this.dataset.time you want to wrap it
in a quick parseint, turn it into a real
number and then we'll
console log seconds.
Twenty, 30, good.
Working really nicely for us.
What we want to do is then we can
simply just call timer, seconds,
that other function. So click it, ah-ha,
looks like it's working really nicely,
although, watch this, click on work five.
Oh, back and forth, back and forth,
back and forth.
So what's going on here?
And if I click a couple of them...let's
just go to town, here. If I just click,
like, 100 times. Oh my goodness,
what's going on? Well I just queued up
like, 1000 timers and there's no way for
the timers to cancel themselves out unless
the number of seconds hits zero. That's
annoying. Like, what if you click the
wrong one. Do you have to like, refresh
the page and then start again?
That's not really any way to live your
life. What we want to do is when we start
our timer, we'll just clear any existing
timers. Let's clear interval countdown.
If there is a timer in countdown,
it will clear it. If there's not,
the variable still exists and it's not
gonna error out on us. Now,
if I say, "Oh, not 20, I meant 5." It's
not going back 15, it's not going back,
you see that? Our "be back" time is
also updating itself nicely.
Good, good, good. Last thing is this form
here where you enter in maybe 30 minutes.
So we want to take this form right here,
which, if you go into our HTML you'll see
that this form has a name of custom form,
so we'll go into here.
Before you select it, I kind of wanted to
show you this little thing.
I actually didn't know about it for the
longest time. I was just selecting all of
my elements. But did you know that you can
type document., and then if it has a name
attribute on it, custom form, you can just
type document.customform and that will
give us the form element. Similarly,
if your input also has a name,
it'll just nest itself .minutes and that
will give us the input.
Whoa, we don't have to select a single
thing. Let's go into our scripts here and
we'll say
documentcustomform.addeventlistener and
we're going to listen for it, what? Click.
Enter? No. Submit. Then we are going to
run a function, a proper function here,
I'll show you why in a second,
past the event. Now, if we submit this
now, type 10, it refreshes the page and
you see the URL says minutes equals 10.
How do we stop it from reloading the page
and sending the data over a get? A call,
e.preventdefault. That will stop it from
running. Ten. Good, nothing happens. Then
we can get the mins which is going to be
this, because this is the form.minutes,
which is going to be that text box there
that we typed into, the input.value.
And console log our mins, 10, got it.
We can quickly call this .reset and clear
out the value, 10, it'll clear the value
and console log it. Then we simply just
take that number of minutes that we want,
we pass it to our timer, we can't pass it
minutes because our timer requires
seconds. Multiply that by 60, and if we
do it right, so 5 minutes should give us
5 whole minutes. Very nice. So that is
our timer. We got a couple of different
functions going on here, we have our time
out and whatnot, hopefully you enjoyed
that. I'd love to see how you
can take this a little bit further,
either adding some animation and some
interaction, or adding some features in
terms of hours and whatnot.