Edited at https://subtitletools.com
♪ [music] ♪
Here we are on day 30, and to have a
little bit of fun today we are going,
well like you didn't have fun the whole
time. But we're going to be building a
game so you can have fun and play it and
just have a great time.
So what we are building is Whack-a-mole,
and what happens is when you run the game
you're going to get these little critters
popping up in random holes for for random
amounts of time. And then when
you click them you get a point,
you sort of have to follow it along with
your mouse. So there's a couple things we
need to know here, the game itself is
going to be 10 seconds long,
but which hole the mole pops up in and for
how long that mole peeps his head up from
the ground is totally random, it's all
going to be between like 200 milliseconds
and a couple of seconds, and then the mole
hill that it's going to pop up from is
also going to be totally random as well.
So I've gone here and I've gone ahead and
selected all of the holes, I've gone ahead
and selected the scoreboard which is the
seven right here, and I've gone ahead and
selected all the moles.
So look at our HTML here, you've got your
holes, you've got your moles in your
holes, and were ready to roll with our
moles in our holes. So we first need a
function that's going to give us a random
amount of time between hover minimum and
maximum. So we're going to say, "function
randTime" and that's going to take a
minimum and a maximum. And that will
return a "Math.random() * (max-min) +
min;" And we've done this whole offset
thing a couple of times,
now I'm not going to explain it again.
That should give us a function that if we
open up in our browser here and we run
"randTime" and if we go between 20
milliseconds and 2 seconds, it's just
going to give us a random amount of
millisecond. We could probably also pop a
"Math.round" around that just so we can
get a nice, clean number of milliseconds
back. There we go, now we're going to get
a random amount of time that it's
going to be popping itself up.
So that's one function, that's sort of a
bit of a utility. Then we needed other
function that's going to pick a random
hole for the mole to pop up from.
So, "function randomHole()" and that is
going to take in a list of holes,
which is going to be, in our case it's
going to be this holes that we have here,
however this could be any list of DOM
Elements. Essentially this is just a get
me a random DOM Element function there.
And what we're going to do here is,
let's just console log holes. Now if I
were to run "randHole()" and pass our
"holes" variable, we're going to get six,
why? Because holes is a node list that
contains all six of our holes. Okay, good.
So we need to find a random index between
zero and five which is going to give us
that one, so we say "const idx =
Math.floor(Math.random() * holes.length;
const hole = holes[idx];" why?
Because that's going to be like hole
zero, one, two, three, four,
all the way up till five. So idx, then
let's just console log the hole itself.
So now if we run that function by passing
it our holes, this is five.
Oh, five again, that's going to be a
problem for us. One, one,
oh, one again, that's going to be a
problem for us. One again,
what are the chances? I guess one in six.
Hole, three, hole two.
You see how it's giving us a random one.
But the problem that we're running into is
that sometimes we get the same one,
it's a one and six chance,
so it's going to be pretty common, and you
don't want the same mole popping up.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to create a variable up here,
we're going to say "let lastHole;" and
that's just going to create a variable.
And then down here we're going to say, at
the very bottom put a line in between
that, we'll say "lastHole = hole;" and
what this will do is it will save the
reference to what one got popped up last
time this function was called so that in
here what we can do it we'll say, "if(hole
= lastHole)" like if it was the same
one that popped up last time, we'll just
console log "Ah nah that's the same one
bud." And then we'll simply just run this
function "randomHole()" again by passing
"holes." Now this function is just console
logging but that's not really what we want
because we can't get the reference to the
DOM node if we just consolel log it.
So what we need to do here is return the
hole which is what we have,
and then up here if it was the same one
we'll just return that function itself
which will in turn get called. So you've
got some recursion going on here returning
the hole. Now if we rerun that we should
never get the same one twice in a row.
So, oh, we've got two things going on
here, why do we? Oh, because we are
running it and we're console logging
it, and that's...so this one,
this little thing is saying it's returned
and we're console logging,
so we can take that console log out and
run it, we have one, two,
three, two, six, three. There we go, never
getting the same one,
every now and then we're getting,
"now that's a same one, bud." Why?
Because it's, it is, in this case it was
one and then it found one again,
but rather than returning it, it just
returned the function which will call
itself again. If you call that a few more
times you might get a chance where it will
run it more than once. Aha, there we go,
see, it ran it once, it had one,
ran it again and got one, ran it again and
got one, and then ran it again and got
three. So we've got them running now.
So we've got a random time,
we got a random hole, maybe we should
rename this to "randomTime",
keep that consistent, random and
"randomHole." Next what we need to do is
actually get the moles popping up. So
we'll go here and we'll make a function
called "peep()" which is, there're going
to go hoop, they're going to pop up from
their holes. And we will get some time,
which is a random time,
it's going to be between 200 miliseconds
and one second, and we're going to get a
random hole which should give us
"randomHole()" we pass it "holes." So now
we just console log time and hole see what
we got here. Now when I just run "peep" we
get 450 milliseconds, hole5 should pop up,
hole4 should pop up for 821 milliseconds,
hole3 should be just under one second. So
you see how we're getting a random hole
and a random amount of time? So what we'll
do here is we'll take that hole,
we'll add a class to it of "up" and that
is going to trigger our CSS to be "top:0;"
and that's just going to animate itself in
because by default I have put them
"top:100%;" and I put a transition
of 0.4 seconds to pop up on it.
So there we go, let's try this here.
Hey, there he is. I'll do it again,
hey, and again, and again, and again, and
again, and you see that they are all
slowly popping up. However, we
don't...they don't go away, and what we
need to do now is after this random amount
of time we need to remove the class of
"up" from this random hole. So
"setTimeout()" which is after how many
seconds time? And when that happens we're
going to take our hole and we're going to
remove the class of "up." No, not remove
class, just remove...removeClass is
jQuery. So here we go, and I will say peep
and then it goes down,
peep again and then it goes down, peep
again, wohoo! Having some fun here,
awesome. Then, what we need to do is
unless the game is over we just need to
run it again, when it's done we'll run
"peep()." So if you were to kick off
peep like that it's just going to run
indefinitely because there's no way to
actually stop that. So what we'll do here
is we'll go up to our top,
and we'll create a variable called
"timeUp" and we'll set that to "false,"
and we'll go down here and we'll say if
the time is not up then we'll run
"peep()." So if there is the variable
"timeUp" is ever set to "true" then it
will stop. So here we go, we'll run
"peep()", it's going to run forever but
then we're going to take this "timeUp"
variable, it's set to "false," we can set
it to "true," and it never starts again
because it just...well,
"peep()" will call itself and then it'll
call itself for the last time because this
will not run. Okay, that makes sense so
far. Then what we need to do is make a
function called "startGame." So we'll say
"function startGame()." And the first
thing we need to do is just reset the
scoreboard here, just in case we're
playing again. So we'll say
"scoreboard.textContent = 0;" then we'll
say "timeUp = false;" again we set that on
page load I know, but if you were to
run "startGame()" again like you want to
play twice then you could do that.
Then we want to kick off "peep()" there
which we'll run it, so let's see here,
startGame(), so they're running like
crazy. But what we also want to do is
after 10 seconds we want to set that
variable that we time up,
we want to set it to true. So
"setTimeout()" after that happens we'll
say "timeUp = true" and that will run
after 10 seconds, 10,000 milliseconds.
Well, let's do it after two seconds now
just so we can see if it works.
So we'll run it, two seconds has
elapsed and no longer is running.
Good, so we'll set that back to 10
seconds. So we've got our "startGame(),"
we've got our "peep()" and we can make a
button now that when clicked we can maybe
put a button right here that says
"onClick="startGame()"" there's "Start!"
and then when you click it it will start
playing the game for you.
Wohoo! The last piece that we need
is when you click on a mole,
we need to bonk them on the head. So we
are going to make a function called "bonk"
that's going to take in the event, it'll
just console log the event.
Then we'll take all of our moles and we'll
listen for a click on each of the moles,
then we'll run "bonk." Bonk, like that. So
now we have to get a little bit crafty
with our clicking. So, start it, click.
Oh, I got the first one.
All right, let's take a look at this.
"MouseEvent", all kinds of information in
here. The first thing I want you to do is,
you might say like,
"Oh, Wes, but I can fake a click with
JavaScript," good matches like do that
and win the entire game. Well, on all of
your events you have this thing called
"isTrusted" and it will say "true." If you
fake clicking something with JavaScript
that's going to be false because you can
simulate a click which is handy in some
cases, but we need it to be true that this
actually came from the user's mouse input.
So the first thing we're going to do is
we're going to say "if(!e.isTrusted)
return;" and that will...we'll just say
"cheater!" So someone's
trying to fake the click without their
mouse. Okay, good. Then what we want to do
here is when someone clicks something
we've got to give them some sort of score.
So let's go up to the top here and we'll
say, "let score = 0" and when we start the
game we'll set score to zero as well just
so that if we restart it we can do that.
And then we'll go down here and we'll
simply say "score++;" and we will move
that little guy down, so
"this.classList.remove('up');" because if
you smack them they should move down even
if they have like a second or so left on
the clock. And then we take our
"scoreBoard" which have we selected that?
Yes, yes we have "document.querySelctor"
and we'll set the text content to be
[inaudible]. I got eight, then
you click start, it'll run again and you
can keep playing with all of your values
there. So that is our Whack-a-mole game,
there's a lot more you could do. First of
all what would be really be cool is if you
had like an all time scoreboard and you
were to save that in local storage so if
someone were to come back then you
could reload the highest score,
and you save them in local storage. It
would also be cool if you had like levels,
like this is like a pretty clickable, but
if you were to say like expert level,
and then you were to change this random
time to like between 50 milliseconds and
300 milliseconds and then it'll be like
super hard like woo, woo,
woo, woo, woo. Like some people would
be really good at that, not me,
but oh I got one, sweet. So you could do
expert mode and you can just create extra
all kinds of different controls up here
along with the dashboard and I would just
love to see where you take this one.
Hopefully you enjoyed that and I won't see
you tomorrow because that is it. Hopefully
you enjoyed it and I'll have a little bit
of an outro video for you as well.
Thanks a lot.
♪ [music] ♪
.