♪ [music] ♪
Edited at https://subtitletools.com
You did it. Congratu-freaking-lations.
You killed it. You did all 30 days.
Or, you're just watching this video.
For some reason, you want to see
what the last video is.
Don't do that. That's a jerk move.
Great job. I'm really proud of you
for doing all 30 days.
And what I want to leave you with is
sort of some motivation to keep going.
Keep building more stuff. I said a
1,000 things is what you've got to
build. Well, you've got 970 left.
You're just getting started with
this sort of thing.
So how do you keep it going?
For some people, the best way
is to just start teaching others.
So help other people out
on this course. Write a blog post.
Create a YouTube tutorial, whatever it is.
The way that I got into this stuff is
I initially started blogging and
putting up tutorials on YouTube.
And it really helped me solidify my skills
by having to explain it to other people.
So being involved in open-source doesn't
just mean building these frameworks.
There's a lot of really smart people
that are out there building frameworks and
libraries and plugins and all that stuff.
But if that's not really where you're at
right now, where I think you can
contribute is by sharing what you
know. You just learned a whole
bunch of stuff in this course.
Now turn around, start telling other
people about it. Share it.
Make lots of examples for everybody.
Really, keep it up. Keep building stuff.
Don't let this stop you. You've got 970
more things to build. Thanks a lot.
And I will see you in my next course.
♪ [music] ♪